{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The point on the celestial sphere vertically below the observer's position, is called", "opta": "zenith", "optb": "celestial point", "optc": "nadir", "optd": "pole.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The parallax equation  is applicable to entire overlap of the photographs only if parallax is measured", "opta": "normal to base line", "optb": "parallel to base line", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stereo plotting instruments are generally manufactured on the principle of", "opta": "optical projection", "optb": "optical mechanism projection", "optc": "mechanical projection", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Latitude of a place is the angular distance from", "opta": "Greenwich to the place", "optb": "equator to the poles", "optc": "equator to the nearer pole", "optd": "equator to the nearer pole along the meridian of the place", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "International date line is located along", "opta": "standard meridian", "optb": "Greenwich meridian", "optc": "equator", "optd": "180\u00b0 longitude", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shortest distance between two places measured along the surface of the earth, is", "opta": "length of the equator between their longitudes", "optb": "length of the parallel between their longitudes", "optc": "length of the arc of the great circle passing through them", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The correction for parallax, is", "opta": "- 8\".8 cos \u03b1", "optb": "+ .8\" sin \u03b1", "optc": "+ 8\".8 cos \u03b1", "optd": "- 8\".8 cos \u03b1.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle between the plane of the equator and the plane of the ecliptic, is known as obliquity of the ecliptic and its value is", "opta": "22\u00b0 30'", "optb": "23\u00b0 27'", "optc": "23\u00b0 30'", "optd": "24\u00b0 0'.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Systematic errors", "opta": "always follow some definite mathematical law", "optb": "can be removed by applying corrections to the observed values", "optc": "either make the result too great or too small", "optd": "are also known as cumulative errors", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Perspective centre relates to", "opta": "parallel projection", "optb": "orthogonal projection", "optc": "central projection", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most convenient co-ordinate system for specifying the relative positions of heavenly bodies on the celestial sphere, is", "opta": "altitude and azimuth system", "optb": "declination and hour angle system", "optc": "declination and right ascension system", "optd": "declination and altitude system", "opte": "azimuth and declination system.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a tropical year, the number of sidereal days, are", "opta": "365", "optb": "365.2224", "optc": "365.2422", "optd": "366.2422", "opte": "366.2224.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Sidereal time at any instant is equal to the hour angle of the first point of Aries", "optb": "Local sidereal time of any place is equal to the right ascension of its meridian", "optc": "Sidereal time is equal to the right ascension of a star at its upper transit", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polaris is usually observed for the determination of the azimuth when it is", "opta": "at culmination", "optb": "at elongation", "optc": "neither at culmination nor at elongation", "optd": "either at culmination or at elongation.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The latitude (\u03bb) of a place and the altitude (\u03b1) of the pole are related by", "opta": "\u03bb = \u03b1", "optb": "\u03bb = 90\u00b0 - \u03b1", "optc": "\u03bb = \u03b1 - 90\u00b0", "optd": "\u03bb = 180\u00b0 - \u03b1.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b1, H, A and \u03b4 be the altitude, hour angle, azimuth and declination of a circumpolar star at its elongation, in latitude \u03bb, the following relation holds good", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Places having same latitude", "opta": "lie on the parallel of the latitude", "optb": "are equidistant from the nearer pole", "optc": "are equidistant from both the poles", "optd": "are equidistant from the equator", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The relation between the air base (B), photographic base (b), flying height (H) and the focal length (f) of a vertical photograph, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference in longitude of two places expressed in time is equal to the difference in their", "opta": "sidereal time", "optb": "apparent solar time", "optc": "mean solar time", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The scale of a vertical photograph of focal length f taken from height of H metres above M.S.L., at a point of reduced level h, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the general ground level of any area is 10% of the flying height, the principal points may be used as the centres of radial directions for small scale mapping even in tilted photograph up to", "opta": "1\u00b0", "optb": "2\u00b0", "optc": "3\u00b0", "optd": "4\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The station which is selected close to the main triangulation station, to avoid intervening obstruction, is not known as", "opta": "satellite station", "optb": "eccentric station", "optc": "false station", "optd": "pivot station.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The relief displacement of a minar 72 m high on photograph is 7.2 mm and its top appears 10 cm away from principal point. The flying height of the camera, is", "opta": "500 m", "optb": "1000 m", "optc": "1500 m", "optd": "2000 m.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following. The difference between the longitudes of the places is obtained.", "opta": "by subtracting their longitudes if places are in the same hemisphere", "optb": "by adding their longitudes if places are in the different hemispheres", "optc": "by subtracting the sum of their longitudes exceeding 180\u00b0 from 360\u00b0 if places are in different hemispheres", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While making astronomical observations, the observer is mainly concerned with", "opta": "the direction of the vertical, the axis of rotation of the instrument", "optb": "the direction of the poles of the celestial sphere", "optc": "the direction of the star from the instrument", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At western elongation, the pole star moves", "opta": "eastward", "optb": "westward", "optc": "northward", "optd": "southward.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Refraction correction is zero when the celestial body is in the zenith", "optb": "Refraction correction is 33' when the celestial body is on the horizon", "optc": "Refraction correction of celestial bodies depends upon their altitudes", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hour angle of the heavenly body for Greenwich meridian equals the hour angle of the body for any other meridian + longitude :", "opta": "mean sun", "optb": "true sun", "optc": "vernal equinox", "optd": "star", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By raising the z-column of right projector, maximum y-parallax is introduced in the model at", "opta": "position 1", "optb": "position 2", "optc": "position 4", "optd": "position 6", "opte": "position 4 and 6.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The height displacement on a vertical photograph", "opta": "increases as the horizontal distance increases from the principal point", "optb": "increases as the ground elevation increases", "optc": "decreases as the flying height increases", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equation which is obtained by multiplying each equation by the coefficient of its un-knowns and by adding the equations thus formed, is known as", "opta": "observation equation", "optb": "conditional equation", "optc": "normal equation", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Accidental errors", "opta": "do not follow any definite mathematical law", "optb": "cannot be removed by applying corrections to the observed values", "optc": "are generally small", "optd": "are also known as compensating errors", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b8 and \u03b4 be the latitude of a place and declination of a star respectively, the upper culmination of the star will be north of zenith if its zenith distance, is", "opta": "\u03b4 - \u03b8", "optb": "\u03b8 - \u03b4", "optc": "\u03b8 + \u03b4", "optd": ".", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a tropical year, the number of sidereal days are", "opta": "one less than mean solar days", "optb": "one more than mean solar days", "optc": "equal to mean solar days", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The position of a heavenly body on the celestial sphere can be completely specified by", "opta": "its altitude and azimuth", "optb": "its declination and hour angle", "optc": "its declination and right ascension", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle between the axis of earth and the vertical at the station of observation is called", "opta": "astronomical latitude", "optb": "astronomical co-latitude", "optc": "co-declination of star", "optd": "declination of star.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For any star to be a circumpolar star, its", "opta": "declination must be 0\u00b0", "optb": "declination must be 90\u00b0", "optc": "distance from the pole must be less than the latitude of the observer", "optd": "hour angle must be 180\u00b0.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The elevation of the star at elongation is obtained by", "opta": "sin \u03b1 = sin \u03c6 cosec \u03b4", "optb": "sin \u03b1 = sin \u03c6 sec \u03b4", "optc": "sin \u03b1 = cos \u03c6 sec \u03b4", "optd": "sin \u03b1 = cos \u03c6 cosec \u03b4.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The necessary geometrical condition for triangulation adjustment, is :", "opta": "The sum of the angles around a station should be 360\u00b0", "optb": "The sum of the three angles of a plane triangle should be 180\u00b0", "optc": "The sum of the eight angles of a braced quadrilateral should be 360\u00b0", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The correction applied to the measured base of length L is", "opta": "", "optb": "where w is the weight of tape/m", "optc": "where h is height difference of end supports", "optd": "Reduction to mean sea level =", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle between the direction of star and the direction of earth's axis of rotation is called", "opta": "co-declination", "optb": "co-latitude", "optc": "declination", "optd": "latitude.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If v, t and  are the ground speed of the aircraft, the shutter speed of the camera and the scale of the photograph respectively, then the amount of image displacement", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "The angle between the plane of the negative and the horizontal plane containing perspective axis is the tilt of the photograph", "optb": "The direction of maximum tilt is defined by the photo principal line", "optc": "The principal plane is truly vertical plane which contains perspective centre as well as principal point and plumb point", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The circle in which a plane tangent to the earth's surface at the point of observation, intersects the celestial sphere, is called", "opta": "visible horizon", "optb": "sensible horizon", "optc": "celestial horizon", "optd": "true horizon", "opte": "none of the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b8 and \u03b4 be the latitude of an observer and declination of a heavenly body respectively, the upper culmination of the body will be south of zenith if its zenith distance, is", "opta": "\u03b4 - \u03b8", "optb": "\u03b8 - \u03b4", "optc": "\u03b8 + \u03b4", "optd": "(\u03b8 - \u03b4).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Invar tapes used for measuring base lines, is made of nickel-iron alloy containing nickel", "opta": "24%", "optb": "36%", "optc": "40%", "optd": "60%.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Triangulation surveys are carried out for locating", "opta": "control points for surveys of large areas", "optb": "control points for photogrammetric surveys", "optc": "engineering works, i.e. terminal points of long tunnels, bridge abutments, etc.", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The movement of the projector in y-direction, introduces in the model a y-parallax", "opta": "maximum at position 1", "optb": "maximum at position 2", "optc": "maximum at position 5 and 6", "optd": "maximum at positions 3 and 4", "opte": "equally throughout the model.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The threshold markings are", "opta": "4 m wide", "optb": "1 m clear space between adjacents", "optc": "45 m in length", "optd": "placed symmetrically on either side of the runway centre line", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bearing of the longest line of a wind rose is S 45\u00b0 E, the bearing of the runway will be numbered", "opta": "135\u00b0", "optb": "315\u00b0", "optc": "13", "optd": "31", "opte": "both (c) and (d)", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the proposed runway stated in if the aerodrome reference temperature is 17\u00b0.2, the net designed length of the runway is", "opta": "2716 m", "optb": "2816 m", "optc": "2916 m", "optd": "3016 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Landing speed is directly proportional to the wing loading", "optb": "Wing loading remaining constant, the take off distance is directly proportional to the powder loading", "optc": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Approach zone survey is carried out to determine the elevations of the protruding obstructions above horizontal, conical and transitional surfaces", "optb": "The wind data of an air port is depicted in the form of a chart known as wind rose", "optc": "The landing and take off of the air craft is made against the wind direction", "optd": "The product of wind loading and power loading is called air craft rating", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lift off distance is the distance along the centre of the runway between the starting point and", "opta": "end of the runway", "optb": "end of stopway", "optc": "point where air craft becomes air borne", "optd": "point where air craft attains a height of 10.7 m", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Approximate geometric centre of the landing area, is called air port reference point", "optb": "The boundaries of horizontal surface and conical surface are marked with reference to air port reference point", "optc": "The location of the air port on a map is the position of air port reference point", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The runway orientation is made so that landing and take off are", "opta": "against the wind direction", "optb": "along the wind direction", "optc": "perpendicular to wind direction", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An aircraft is flying in an atmosphere of 30\u00b0C with a speed of 1260 km ph. Its speed is known as", "opta": "subsonic", "optb": "sonic", "optc": "super-sonic", "optd": "Mach.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.C.A.O. the slope of transitional surface at right angles to the centre line of runway, is kept", "opta": "1 in 4", "optb": "1 in 5", "optc": "1 in 6", "optd": "1 in 7", "opte": "1 in 10", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depressions and undulations in the pavement, are caused due to", "opta": "improper compaction of subgrade", "optb": "impact of heavy wheel loads", "optc": "punching effect", "optd": "flexible gears", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "In single engine aeroplanes, the engine is provided in the nose of the aircraft", "optb": "In double engine aeroplanes, one engine on either wing is placed symmetrically", "optc": "In three engine aeroplanes, two engines are placed on both wings and one engine is placed in the tail", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The speed of the aircraft relative to the ground, is called cruising speed", "optb": "The speed of the aircraft relative to wind, is called air speed", "optc": "When wind is blowing the direction of the flight, air speed is less than cruising speed", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Airport elevation is the reduced level above M.S.L. of", "opta": "control tower", "optb": "highest point of the landing area", "optc": "lowest point of the landing area", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reduced level of the proposed site of an air port is 2500 m above M.S.L. If the recommended length by I.C.A.O. for the runway at sea level is 2500 m, the required length of the runway is", "opta": "2500 m", "optb": "3725 m", "optc": "3000 m", "optd": "3250 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.C.A.O. the recommended length of air ports is decided on", "opta": "sea level elevation", "optb": "standard sea level temperature (15\u00b0C)", "optc": "effective gradient percentage", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The basic length of a runway is increased at a rate of 7% per 300 m of elevation of M.S.L.", "optb": "The standard temperature at the site is obtained by reducing the standard sea level temperature of 15\u00b0C at the rate of 6.5\u00b0C per 1000 m rise in elevation", "optc": "The aerodrome reference temperature is the monthly mean of the mean daily temperature for the hottest month of the year", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The meterological condition which influences the size and location of an air port is", "opta": "atmosphere pressure", "optb": "air density", "optc": "reduced level", "optd": "wind direction", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The distance between the points of intersection of the extreme tangents to the transition curve is kept greater than 7500 m x sum of grade changes at the point of intersection", "optb": "The rate of change of grade is limited to 0.3% per 30 m length of the curve", "optc": "According to I.C.A.O. the maximum longitudinal gradient along a runway is limited to 1.5%", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conical surface of the approach area rises outwards", "opta": "1 in 10", "optb": "1 in 15", "optc": "1 in 20", "optd": "1 in 25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness design of the pavement, is decided on the load carried by", "opta": "main gears", "optb": "nose wheel", "optc": "tail wheel", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For Class A Air port the difference of reduced levels of higher and lower edges of the conical surface, is", "opta": "25 m", "optb": "50 m", "optc": "75 m", "optd": "100 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Beaufort scale is used to determine", "opta": "strength of winds", "optb": "direction of winds", "optc": "height of air-crafts", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fuse large includes", "opta": "passengers chamber", "optb": "pilot's cabin", "optc": "tail of aircraft", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Air screw converts the energy given by the engine into speed", "optb": "The propellers which are driven by turbine engines, are technically called turboprops", "optc": "The aircrafts which obtain the thrust directly from turbine engine, are called turbo-jets", "optd": "The aircraft which is filled with a fan infront of turbo-jet engine, is called turbofan propelled aeroplane", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance between main gears is 10 m, and the distance of nose gear from centre of main gears is 30 m. If the angle of turning is 60\u00b0, the distance of centre of rotation from the nearer main gear, is", "opta": "12.30 m", "optb": "11.30 m", "optc": "10.30 m", "optd": "9.30 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To cope up high temperature of 196\u00b0C, the taxi ways and aprons are constructed with", "opta": "asphaltic concrete", "optb": "rubberised tar concrete", "optc": "plain concrete", "optd": "epoxy asphalt concrete", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct abbreviation from the following:", "opta": "I.L.S. (instrument landing system)", "optb": "V.H.F, (very high frequency)", "optc": "L.O.M. (low powered outer marker)", "optd": "L.M.M. (low powered middle marker)", "opte": "All the above", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wing loading of an aircraft is", "opta": "load of the wings", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "Channelization of pavement is caused by constant use of tri-cycle gears of aircraft", "optb": "Blast pads are used over cohesionless soils to resist erosion due to tremendous speed of the jet blast", "optc": "Over-run areas of at least 300 m length on either side of the runway are provided", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "From the end of an instrumental runway, the approach surface rises outwards", "opta": "1 in 20", "optb": "1 in 30", "optc": "1 in 40", "optd": "1 in 50", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Speed of", "opta": "sound at 0\u00b0C is 1190 km p.h.", "optb": "sound varies 2.4 km p.h. per degree centrigrade rise in temperature", "optc": "sound at 0\u00b0C is called one Mach", "optd": "an aircraft flying at 2975 km p.h., is called 2.5 Mach", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The centre line of the approach area coincides with that of the runway", "optb": "Approach areas are measured in horizontal surfaces", "optc": "The imaginary inclined plane which is directly above the approach area is called approach surface", "optd": "Obstruction clearance surface and approach surface are same", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coordinates of the ends of a runway are (5000, 5000) and (8000, 7000). The co-ordinates of an other runway are (4600, 5100) and (7000, 5300). The co-ordinates of the A.R.P. are", "opta": "(6500, 6000)", "optb": "(5800, 5200)", "optc": "(61500, 5600)", "optd": "(8000, 7000)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A gradient of + 0.08% is followed by a gradient of - 0.07%. If the permissible rate of change of grade is 0.003 per 30 metres, the length of the transition curve, is", "opta": "150 m", "optb": "140 m", "optc": "160 m", "optd": "175 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "F.I.R. stands for flight information regions", "optb": "F.I.C. stands for flight information centre", "optc": "Radius of control area is 160 km", "optd": "Radius of control zone is 40 km", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bearing of the runway at threshold is 290\u00b0, the runway number is", "opta": "N 70\u00b0 W", "optb": "290\u00b0", "optc": "29\u00b0", "optd": "W 20\u00b0 N", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The best direction of a runway is along the direction of", "opta": "longest line on wind rose diagram", "optb": "shortest line on the wind rose diagram", "optc": "line clear of wind rose diagram", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "International Civil Aviation Organisation (I.C.A.O.) was set up at Montreal (Canada), in", "opta": "1929", "optb": "1939", "optc": "1947", "optd": "1950", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The air is blowing at a speed of 75 knots in the direction of the aircraft flying at a ground speed of 775 knots. The air speed of the aircraft, is", "opta": "775 knots", "optb": "75 knots", "optc": "850 knots", "optd": "675 knots", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the taxiways, the following statement is true", "opta": "The maximum longitudinal grade is 3%", "optb": "The permissible rate of change of grade is 1%", "optc": "The permissible transverse grade is 1.5%", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Runway edge from the landing side, is called threshold", "optb": "Localizer indicates to the pilot his position with respect to the proposed alignment", "optc": "The glide slope indicates the correct angle of descent", "optd": "L.O.M. and L.M.M. help the pilot to judge his position for the runway", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum length and pavement strength of the runway is that of", "opta": "A 1", "optb": "B 2", "optc": "B 3", "optd": "G 7", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to the International Civil Aviation Organisation (I.C.A.O.), the runway lengths of aerodromes, have been coded by", "opta": "Seven English alphabets", "optb": "Last Seven English alphabets", "optc": "First Seven English alphabets", "optd": "First seven natural numbers.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "L.O.M. is installed at 7.2 km from the threshold", "optb": "L.M.M. is installed at 1.0 km from the threshold", "optc": "Localizer antenna is installed at 300 m from the other end of the runway", "optd": "Glide slope antenna is installed at the centre of the runway about 150 m on one side", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to the International Civil Aviation Organisation (I.C.A.O.) the strength of runway pavements, have been coded by", "opta": "Seven English alphabets", "optb": "Last Seven English alphabets", "optc": "First Seven English alphabets", "optd": "First seven numbers", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The strength of winds is measured with the help of", "opta": "Benfort scale", "optb": "Wind indicator", "optc": "Barometres", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The landing and take off of the air craft is made against the direction of wind. In no case the centre line of the runway should make an angle with the wind direction exceeding", "opta": "10\u00b0", "optb": "20\u00b0", "optc": "30\u00b0", "optd": "40\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.C.A.O. all markings on the runways are painted white and on taxiways", "opta": "black", "optb": "red", "optc": "yellow", "optd": "green", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the width of the approach area near the runway end is 150 m, the width of the approach area at a distance of 3 kilometres from runway end will be", "opta": "1500 m", "optb": "1200 m", "optc": "1000 m", "optd": "800 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre of gravity of a triangle is at the point where three", "opta": "medians of the triangle meet", "optb": "perpendicular bisectors of the sides of the triangle meet", "optc": "bisectors of the angle of the triangle meet", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The forces which meet at one point and have their lines of action in different planes are called", "opta": "coplaner non-concurrent forces", "optb": "non-coplaner concurrent forces", "optc": "non-coplaner non-current forces", "optd": "intersecting forces", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At a given instant ship A is travelling at 6 km/h due east and ship B is travelling at 8 km/h due north. The velocity of B relative to A is", "opta": "7 km/hrs", "optb": "2 km/hrs", "optc": "1 km/hrs", "optd": "10 km/hrs", "opte": "14 km/hrs.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equation of motion of a particle starting from rest along a straight line is x = t3 - 3t2 + 5. The ratio of the accelerations after 5 sec and 3 sec will be", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The locus of the instantaneous centre of a moving rigid body, is", "opta": "straight line", "optb": "involute", "optc": "centroid", "optd": "spiral.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A projectile is thrown at an angle a to the horizontal with \u03b1 velocity v. It will have the maximum centripetal acceleration", "opta": "at the start", "optb": "at the top of the trajectory", "optc": "as it strikes the ground", "optd": "else where.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The c.g. of the shaded area of the below figure whose curve OM is a parabola from y-axis, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit of Moment of Inertia of a body, is", "opta": "m", "optb": "m2", "optc": "m3", "optd": "m4", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a body moves in such a way that its velocity increases by equal amount in equal intervals of time, it is said to be moving with", "opta": "a uniform retardation", "optb": "a uniform acceleration", "optc": "a variable acceleration", "optd": "a variable retardation", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the gravitational accelerational at any place is doubled, the weight of a body, will", "opta": "be reduced to half", "optb": "be doubled", "optc": "not be affected", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cable loaded with 0.5 tonne per horizontal metre span is stretched between supports in the same horizontal line 400 m apart. If central dip is 20 m, the minimum tension in the cable, will be", "opta": "200 tonnes at the centre", "optb": "500 tonnes at the centre", "optc": "200 tonnes at the right support", "optd": "200 tonnes at the left support.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A particle moves along a straight line such that distance x traversed in t seconds is given by x = t2(t + 1), the acceleration of the particle, will be", "opta": "3t3 - 2t", "optb": "3t2 + 2t", "optc": "6t - 2", "optd": "6t + 2", "opte": "3t - 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Law of Polygon of Forces states that", "opta": "if a polygen representing the forces acting at point in a body is closed, the forces are in equilibrium", "optb": "if forces acting on a point can be represented in magnitde and direction by the sides of a polygon taken in order, then the resultant of the forces will be represented in magnitude and direction by the closing side of the polygon", "optc": "if forces acting on a point can be represented of a polygon taken in order, their sides of a polygon taken in order, their resultant will be represented in magnitude and direction by the closing side of the polygon, taken in opposite order", "optd": "if forces acting on a point can be represented in magnitude and direction by the sides of a polygon in order, the forces are in equilibrium.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Parallelogram Law of Forces states, \"if two forces acting simultaneously on a particle be represented in magnitude and direction by two adjacent sides of a parallelogram, their resultant may be represented in magnitude and direction by", "opta": "its longer side\"", "optb": "its shorter side\"", "optc": "the diagonal of the parallelogram which does not pass through the point of intersection of the forces\"", "optd": "the diagonal of the parallelogram which passes through the point of intersection of the forces\"", "opte": "half the sum of the diagonals\".", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is true ?", "opta": "The tangent of the angle of friction is equal to coefficeint of friction", "optb": "The angle of repose is equal to angle of friction", "optc": "The tangent of the angle of repose is equal to coefficient of friction", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The beam shown in below figure is supported by a hinge at A and a roller at B. The reaction RA of the hinged support A of the beam, is", "opta": "10.8 t", "optb": "10.6 t", "optc": "10.4 t", "optd": "10.2 t.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The product of mass and velocity of a moving a body, is called", "opta": "moment", "optb": "momentum", "optc": "power", "optd": "impulse.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Engineer's units of force, is", "opta": "Newton in absolute units", "optb": "Dyne in absolute units", "optc": "Newton and dyne in absolute units", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Joule is the unit of", "opta": "work", "optb": "force", "optc": "power", "optd": "torque", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum velocity of a body vibrating with a simple harmonic motion of amplitude 150 mm and frequency 2 vibrations/sec, is", "opta": "188.5 m/sec", "optb": "18.85 m/sec", "optc": "1.885 m/sec", "optd": "0.18845 m/sec.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the tension in a cable supporting a lift moving upwards is twice the tension when the lift is movng downwards, the acceleration of the lift, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Newton force, is", "opta": "103 dynes", "optb": "104 dynes", "optc": "105 dynes", "optd": "106 dynes", "opte": "107 dynes.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The masses of two balls are in the ratio of 2 : 1 and their respective velocities are in the ratio of 1 : 2 but in opposite direction before impact. If the coefficient of restitution is , the velocities of separation of the balls will be equal to", "opta": "original velocity in the same direction", "optb": "half the original velocity in the same direction", "optc": "half the original velocity in the opposite direction", "optd": "original velocity in the opposite direction", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle which an inclined surface makes with the horiontal when a body placed on it is on the point of moving down, is called", "opta": "angle of repose", "optb": "angle of friction", "optc": "angle of inclination", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work may be defined as", "opta": "force x distance", "optb": "force x velocity", "optc": "force x acceleration", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A square hole is punched out of a circular lamina, the diagonal of the square being the radius of the circle. If r is the radius of the circle, the C.G. of the remainder from the corner of the square on the circumference will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A bullet weighing 200 g is fired horizontally with a velocity of 25 m/sec from a gun carried on a carriage which together with the gun weighs 100 kg. The velocity of recoil of the gun, will be", "opta": "0.01 m/sec", "optb": "0.05 m/sec", "optc": "1.00 m/sec", "optd": "1.5 m/see.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tension in a cable supporting a lift", "opta": "is more when the lift is moving downwards", "optb": "is less when the lift is moving upwards", "optc": "remains constant whether its moves downwards or upwards", "optd": "is less when the lift is moving downwards.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A satellite moves in its orbit around the earth due to", "opta": "Gravitational force", "optb": "Centripetal force", "optc": "Centrifugal force", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If g1 and g2 are the gravitational accelerations on two mountains A and B respectively, the weight of a body when transported from A to B will be multiplied by", "opta": "g1", "optb": "g2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If three rigid rods are hinged together to form a triangle and are given rotary as well as translatory motion, the number of instantaneous centres of the triangle, will be", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mechanical advantage of an ideal machine is 100. For moving the local through 2 m, the effort moves through", "opta": "0.02 m", "optb": "2 m", "optc": "2.5 m", "optd": "20 m.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body in equilibrium undergoes an infinitely small displacement, work imagined to be done, is known as", "opta": "imaginary work", "optb": "negative work", "optc": "virtual work", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The resultant of two forces P and Q acting at an angle \u03b8, is", "opta": "P2 + Q2 + 2P sin \u03b8", "optb": "P2 + Q2 + 2PQ cos \u03b8", "optc": "P2 + Q2 + 2PQ tan \u03b8", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To attain the synchronous orbit, the launch of a satellite, is done from a place", "opta": "on equator", "optb": "on 30\u00b0 latitude", "optc": "on 45\u00b0 latitude", "optd": "on 60\u00b0 latitude", "opte": "on the poles.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The vertical reaction at the support A of the structure shown in below figure, is", "opta": "1 t", "optb": "2 t", "optc": "3 t", "optd": "2.5 t.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Nature plays an important role in the launch of a satellite", "optb": "The earth's gravity reduces the speed of a satellite by 32 km per second", "optc": "The gravitational force relents as the satellite climbs higher", "optd": "The gravitational intensity declines with height", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the radius of the earth is 600 km the height of a mountain above sea level at the top of which a beat seconds pendulum at sea level, looses 27 seconds a day, is", "opta": "500 metres", "optb": "1000 metres", "optc": "1500 metres", "optd": "2000 metres", "opte": "25000 metres.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total time of collision and restitution of two bodies, is called", "opta": "time of collision", "optb": "period of collision", "optc": "period of impact", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of a Second's pendulum, is", "opta": "99.0 cm", "optb": "99.4 cm", "optc": "100 cm", "optd": "101 cm", "opte": "101.10 cm.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A load of 500 kg was lifted through a distance of 13 cm. by an effort of 25 kg which moved through a distance of 650 cm. The efficiency of the lifting machine is", "opta": "50%", "optb": "40%", "optc": "55%", "optd": "30%.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum efficiency of a screw jack for the angle of friction \u03c6, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A string of length 90 cm is fastened to two points A and B at the same level 60 cm apart. A ring weighing 120 g is slided on the string. A horizontal force P is applied to the ring such that it is in equilibrium vertically below B. The value of P is :", "opta": "40 g", "optb": "60 g", "optc": "80 g", "optd": "100 g.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reaction at the support A of the beam shown in below figure is", "opta": "2 t", "optb": "5.8 t", "optc": "0.2 t", "optd": "3.5 t.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "u1 and u2 are the velocities of approach of two moving bodies in the same direction and their corresponding velocities of separation are v1 and v2. As per Newton's law of collision of elastic bodies, the coefficient of restitution (e) is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The c.g. of a thin hollow cone of height h, above its base lies on the axis, at a height of", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two forces act an angle of 120\u00b0. If the greater force is 50 kg and their resultant is perpendicular to the smaller force, the smaller force is", "opta": "20 kg", "optb": "25 kg", "optc": "30 kg", "optd": "35 kg", "opte": "40 kg.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The C.G. of a right circular cone lies on its axis of symmetry at a height of", "opta": "h/2", "optb": "h/3", "optc": "h/4", "optd": "h/5", "opte": "h/6.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A uniform rod 9 m long weighing 40 kg is pivoted at a point 2 m from one end where a weight of 120 kg is suspended. The required force acting at the end in a direction perpendicular to rod to keep it equilibrium, at an inclination 60\u00b0 with horizontal, is", "opta": "40 kg", "optb": "60 kg", "optc": "10 kg", "optd": "100 kg.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a particle is projected inside a horizontal tunnel which is 554 cm high with a velocity of 60 m per sec, the angle of projection for maximum range, is", "opta": "8\u00b0", "optb": "9\u00b0", "optc": "10\u00b0", "optd": "11\u00b0", "opte": "12\u00b0.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of Raymond pile", "opta": "lengths vary from 6 m to 12 m", "optb": "diameter of top of piles varies from 40 cm to 60 cm", "optc": "diameter of pile at bottom varies from 20 cm to 28 cm", "optd": "thickness of outer shell depends upon pile diameter", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Queen closer may be placed", "opta": "in header course", "optb": "in stretcher course", "optc": "in header course next to first brick", "optd": "in stretcher course next to first brick", "opte": "in any position.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dado is usually provided in", "opta": "dinning halls", "optb": "bath rooms", "optc": "living rooms", "optd": "verandah", "opte": "roofs.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The foundation in which a cantilever beam is provided to join two footings, is known as", "opta": "strip footing", "optb": "strap footing", "optc": "combined footing", "optd": "raft footing", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The foundations are placed below ground level, to increase", "opta": "strength", "optb": "workability", "optc": "stability of structure", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stud(s) of a common wooden partition", "opta": "are vertical wooden members", "optb": "is the upper horizontal wooden member", "optc": "is the lower horizontal wooden member", "optd": "are the intermediate horizontal wooden members.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "inclined borings are made for taking samples under existing structures", "optb": "inclined borings are occasionally used instead of vertical holes.", "optc": "the spacing of inclined borings is kept such that one bore hole is vertically above the bottom of an adjacent bore hole.", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the commonly adopted geophysical method in civil engineering from the following :", "opta": "the seisomic method", "optb": "electrical resistivity method", "optc": "gravitational method", "optd": "magnetic method", "opte": "both (a) and (b) of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To ensure that supporting area of an offset footing of a boundary wall is fully compressive, the C.G. of load must act", "opta": "at the centre of the base", "optb": "within the middle third of the base", "optc": "within the middle fifth of the base", "optd": "neither (a), (b) nor (c).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The 9 cm x 9 cm side of a brick as seen in the wall face, is generally known as", "opta": "stretcher", "optb": "face", "optc": "front", "optd": "header", "opte": "side.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The taper of precast concrete pile should not be more than", "opta": "1 cm per metre length", "optb": "2 cm per metre length", "optc": "4 cm per metre length", "optd": "5 cm per metre length.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The under surface of an arch, is called", "opta": "soffit", "optb": "intrados", "optc": "haunch", "optd": "back.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The raft slab is projected beyond the outer walls of the structure by", "opta": "5 to 10 cm", "optb": "15 to 20 cm", "optc": "25 to 30 cm", "optd": "30 to 45 cm", "opte": "60 cm.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The process of making the back ground rough, before plastering, is", "opta": "dubbing", "optb": "hacking", "optc": "blistering", "optd": "peeling.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Black cotton soil is unsuitable for foundations because its", "opta": "bearing capacity is low", "optb": "permeability is uncertain", "optc": "particles are cohesive", "optd": "property to undergo a volumetric change due to variation of moisture content.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The loose pockets in soil mass can be bridged safely by providing a raft foundation provided the soft area is smaller than", "opta": "the column spacing", "optb": "one-third the column spacing", "optc": "half the column spacing", "optd": "three-fourth the column spacing", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The portion of a brick cut across the width, is called", "opta": "closer", "optb": "half brick", "optc": "bed", "optd": "bat.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concrete slump recommended for beams and slabs ; is", "opta": "25 to 50 mm", "optb": "25 to 75 mm", "optc": "30 to 125 mm", "optd": "50 to 100 mm", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The member which is placed horizontally to support common rafter of a sloping roof, is", "opta": "purlin", "optb": "cleat", "optc": "batten", "optd": "strut.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Louvered door is generally provided in bath rooms", "optb": "Flush  door  is  generally  provided   in dinning room", "optc": "Revolving door is generally provided in cinema halls", "optd": "Sliding door is generally provided in show rooms", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Grillage foundation", "opta": "is used to transfer heavy structural loads from steel columns to a soil having low bearing capacity", "optb": "is light and economical", "optc": "does not require deep cutting as the required base area with required pressure intensity is obtained at a shallow depth", "optd": "is constructed by rolled steel joists (R.S.J.) placed in single or double tier", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The exterior angle between outer faces of a wall, is known as", "opta": "turn", "optb": "junction", "optc": "quion", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In jack arch floor, the rise is kept", "opta": "1/6th of the span", "optb": "1/8th of the span", "optc": "1/10th of the span", "optd": "1/12th of the span", "opte": "1/15th of the span.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While designing a stair, the product of rise and going is approximately kept equal to", "opta": "350", "optb": "420", "optc": "450", "optd": "500", "opte": "600.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For constructing a terrazo floor. Pick up the incorrect statement from the following :", "opta": "a base course is prepared as in cement concrete flooring", "optb": "a 32 mm thick layer of cement concrete (1 : 2 : 4) is laid on the base course and the surface is made smooth by trowelling", "optc": "glass strips are driven into the layer according to the pattern required", "optd": "after final grinding is over, oxalic acid mixed with water is spread over and rubbed hard with soft material", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The entrained concrete is used in lining walls and roofs for making", "opta": "heat insulated", "optb": "sound insulated", "optc": "neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "both (a) and (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pile which is provided with a bulb filled with concrete at its lower end, is known as", "opta": "Simplex pile", "optb": "Mac-Arthur pile", "optc": "Raymond pile", "optd": "Franki pile", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of multi-storeyed buildings, the forms to be removed first are", "opta": "sides of beams and girders", "optb": "column forms", "optc": "bottom of beams and girders", "optd": "all the above at the same time.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For providing a raft foundation, the following activities are involved ramming the foundation bedexcavation of the soil upto required depthlaying the reinforcement over the foundation bedcuring the cement concrete placed over reinforcementpouring the cement concrete over the reinforcement. The correct sequence is", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5", "optb": "5, 4, 3, 2, 1", "optc": "2, 1, 3, 5, 4", "optd": "3, 2, 5, 1, 4.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum permissible deflection of a timber beam supporting a roof, is", "opta": "L/100", "optb": "L/150", "optc": "L/260", "optd": "L/360", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angular steps used for changing direction of the stairs, are called", "opta": "round steps", "optb": "angular steps", "optc": "winders", "optd": "radial steps", "opte": "circular steps.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During percussion drilling", "opta": "ground water observations are hindered due to entry of the slurry in the soil below the bottom of the hole", "optb": "caving or mixing of strata are caused in soft soils or cohesionless soils", "optc": "the soil to a considerable depth below the bottom of the hole gets disturbed", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In English garden wall bond", "opta": "one course of headers to three or five course of stretchers", "optb": "queen closer in provided in each heading course", "optc": "the middle course of stretchers is started with a header to give proper vertical joints", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A projecting piece usually provided to support a truss, is", "opta": "cornice", "optb": "coping", "optc": "frieze", "optd": "lintal.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The line of intersection of the surfaces of a sloping roof forming an external angle exceeding 180\u00b0, is", "opta": "ridge", "optb": "hip", "optc": "valley", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A solid core of rock is formed in side the cylinder in the case of", "opta": "auger boring", "optb": "percussion drilling", "optc": "diamond drilling", "optd": "wash boring.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The single stage well point system of dewatering an excavation can be used if the depth of excavation does not exceed", "opta": "5 m", "optb": "10 m", "optc": "15 m", "optd": "20 m", "opte": "25 m.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The piece of a brick cut with its one corner equivalent to half the length and half the width of a full brick, is known as", "opta": "queen closer", "optb": "bevelled closer", "optc": "king closer", "optd": "half king closer.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The brick laid with its breadth parallel to the face of a wall, is known as", "opta": "header", "optb": "stretcher", "optc": "closer", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A wooden block hinged on post outside a door, is known", "opta": "cleat", "optb": "stop", "optc": "horn", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following :", "opta": "The function of foundation is to distribute the load of super structure over a large bearing area", "optb": "No  timbering is  required  for  shallow trenches", "optc": "Shallow foundations can be constructed on made-up soil", "optd": "Grillage   foundation   is   classified as a shallow foundation", "opte": "Black cotton soil is very good for foundation bed.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In horizontal D.P.C, thickness of cement concrete (1 : 2 : 4) is", "opta": "2 cm", "optb": "4 cm", "optc": "6 cm", "optd": "8 cm", "opte": "10 cm.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following factors is considered for the orientation of buildings :", "opta": "the direction of the prevailing winds in the area", "optb": "the exposure of the walls and roof of the buildings to the rays of sun", "optc": "the extent up to which the sunrays penetrate with the verandah.", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following :", "opta": "Cement is added to lime mortar to increase its hydraulic properties only", "optb": "Lime surkhi mortar is used for pointing the walls", "optc": "Lime should be slaked before preparing lime mortar", "optd": "High early strength concrete is generally used in cold weather.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following rocks is used for monumental buildings :", "opta": "granite", "optb": "marble", "optc": "sand stone", "optd": "slate.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Auger borings are not common", "opta": "in soils that require lateral support", "optb": "in cohesive soils", "optc": "in soft soils", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The form work from the underside of slabs, can be removed only after", "opta": "1 day", "optb": "4 days", "optc": "7 days", "optd": "14 days.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Arches in the form of masonry arcs struck from more than four centres, are called", "opta": "two curved arches", "optb": "gothic arches", "optc": "ogee arches", "optd": "drop gothic arches.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If (\u03c6) is the angle of repose of soil of weight w kg/m3, the horizontal pressure p at a depth of h metres per metre length of wall, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Rankine's formula, minimum depth of foundations, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a mortar, the binding material is", "opta": "cement", "optb": "sand", "optc": "surkhi", "optd": "cinder.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lacquer paints", "opta": "are generally applied on structural steel", "optb": "are less durable as compared to enamel paints", "optc": "consist of resin and nitro-cellulose", "optd": "contain alcohol as thinner", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wrought iron contains carbon upto", "opta": "0.25%", "optb": "1.0%", "optc": "1.5%", "optd": "2%.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the polymineralic rock from the following:", "opta": "Quartz sand", "optb": "Pure gypsum", "optc": "Magnesite", "optd": "Granite", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "For thin structures subjected to wetting and drying, the water cement ratio should be 0.45", "optb": "For mass concrete structures subjected to wetting and drying, the water ratio should be 0.55", "optc": "For thin structures which remain continuously under water, the water-cement ratio by weight should be 0.55", "optd": "For massive concrete structures which remain continuously under water, the water cement ratio by weight should be 0.65", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ultimate strength to cement is provided by", "opta": "Tricalcium silicate", "optb": "Di-calcium silicate", "optc": "Tri-calcium aluminate", "optd": "Tetra calcium alumino ferrite.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Elastomers can extend upto", "opta": "five times their original dimensions", "optb": "seven times their original dimensions", "optc": "ten times their original dimensions", "optd": "three times their original dimensions.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bitumen felt", "opta": "is used as water proofing material", "optb": "is used as damp proofing material", "optc": "is made from bitumen and hessian fibres", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In   the   method   of   condensation polymerization,", "opta": "low-molecular substances are removed from the high molecular substance", "optb": "the reaction proceeds with an evolution of ammonia", "optc": "the reaction proceeds with an evolution of hydrogen chloride", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the cement the compound quickest to react with water, is", "opta": "Tricalcium aluminate", "optb": "Tetra-calcium alumino-ferrite", "optc": "Tricalcium silicate", "optd": "Dicalcium silicate.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The initial setting time of lime-pozzolana, is", "opta": "30 minutes", "optb": "60 minutes", "optc": "90 minutes", "optd": "120 minutes.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The clay to be used for manufacturing bricks for a large project, is dugout and allowed to weather throughout", "opta": "the monsoon", "optb": "the winter", "optc": "the summer", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rocks which are formed due to cooling of magma at a considerable depth from earth's surface are called", "opta": "Plutonic rocks", "optb": "Hypabyssal rocks", "optc": "Volcanic rocks", "optd": "Igneous rocks.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Quartzite is a", "opta": "metamorphic rock", "optb": "argillaceous rock", "optc": "calcareous rock", "optd": "silicious rock.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The variety of pig iron used for manufacture of wrought iron, is", "opta": "Bessemer pig", "optb": "Grey or foundry pig", "optc": "White forge pig", "optd": "Mottled pig.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sand stone is", "opta": "sedimentary rock", "optb": "metamorphic rock", "optc": "igneous rock", "optd": "volcanic rock.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the furnace is provided with insufficient fuel at low temperatures, the type of pig iron produced, is called", "opta": "Bessemer pig", "optb": "Grey or foundry pig", "optc": "White or forge pig", "optd": "Mottled pig.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stainless steel contains", "opta": "18% of chromuim and 8% nickel", "optb": "8% of chromium and 18% of nickel", "optc": "12% of chromium and 36% of nickel", "optd": "36% of chromium and 12% of nickel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the hypabyssal rock from the following:", "opta": "Granite", "optb": "Dolerite", "optc": "Basalt", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Depending on the chemical composition and mechanical properties, iron may be classified as", "opta": "cast iron", "optb": "wrought iron", "optc": "steel", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wrought iron contains carbon about", "opta": "1.5% to 5.5%", "optb": "0.5% to 1.75%", "optc": "0.1% to 0.25%", "optd": "none to these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main constituent of fly-ash, is", "opta": "aluminium oxide", "optb": "silica", "optc": "ferrous oxide", "optd": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bitumen in", "opta": "solid state, is called asphalt", "optb": "semi fluid state, is called mineral tar", "optc": "fluid state, is called petroleum", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The plastics made from cellulose resin", "opta": "are as clear as glass", "optb": "are tough and strong", "optc": "possess excellent electrical properties", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Kaolin is chemically classified as", "opta": "metamorphic rock", "optb": "argillaceous rock", "optc": "calcareous rock", "optd": "silicious rock.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is acid resistant asbestos:", "opta": "actinolite asbestos", "optb": "amosite asbestos", "optc": "anthophylite asbestos", "optd": "crocidolite asbestos", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to attack of dry rot, the timber", "opta": "cracks", "optb": "shrinks", "optc": "reduces to powder", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brittleness of cold is due to an excess of", "opta": "sulphur", "optb": "carbon", "optc": "phosphorus", "optd": "silicon.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the manufacture of Portland cement, the proportions of raw materials used, are", "opta": "lime 63% ; silica 22% ; other ingredients 15%", "optb": "lime 22% ; silica 63% ; other ingredients 15%", "optc": "silica 40% ; lime 40% ; other ingredients 20%", "optd": "silica 70% ; lime 20% ; other ingredients 10%.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Asbestos cement", "opta": "is brittle", "optb": "warps due to changes in humidity", "optc": "strength is lowered when saturated by water", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gniess is obtained from", "opta": "igneous rocks", "optb": "metamorphic rocks", "optc": "sedimentary rocks", "optd": "sedimentary metamorphic rocks.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rocks formed by gradual deposition, are called", "opta": "sedimentary rocks", "optb": "igneous rocks", "optc": "metamorphic rocks", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Galvanising means covering iron with a thin coat of", "opta": "tin", "optb": "zinc", "optc": "glaze", "optd": "coal tar.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For preparing porcelains, the clay should be", "opta": "sufficiently pure", "optb": "of high degree of tanacity", "optc": "of good plasticity", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polymerization helps to improve the property of", "opta": "strength", "optb": "rigidity", "optc": "elasticity", "optd": "all of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Good quality stones must", "opta": "be durable", "optb": "be free from clay", "optc": "resist action of acids", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sewer pipes are made of", "opta": "earthen ware", "optb": "stone ware", "optc": "refractory clay", "optd": "terracota", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fibre glass", "opta": "retains heat-longer", "optb": "has a higher strength to weight ratio", "optc": "is shock proof and fire retardent", "optd": "does not decay", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The theory of formation of concrete is based on the phenomena of formation of voids", "optb": "The bulking of sand is taken into account while volumetric proportioning of the aggregates", "optc": "The dry sand and the sand completely flooded with water, have practically the same volume", "optd": "The expansion and contraction joints are provided if concrete structures exceed 12 m in length", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In stone arches, the stones are placed with their natural beds radial", "optb": "In cornices, the stones are placed with their natural beds as vertical", "optc": "In stone walls, the stones are placed with their natural beds as horizontal", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The commonly used colour pigment in paints, is", "opta": "ambers", "optb": "carbon black", "optc": "iron oxide", "optd": "lamp black", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Varnish is a transparent or semi-transparent solution of resinuous substances in", "opta": "alcohol", "optb": "linseed", "optc": "turpentine", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Initial setting time of cement for asbestos cement products should be not less than", "opta": "30 minutes", "optb": "50 minutes", "optc": "75 minutes", "optd": "90 minutes.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The variety of pig iron used for the manufacture of steel by Bessemer process, is", "opta": "Bessemer pig", "optb": "Grey pig", "optc": "White forge pig", "optd": "Mottled pig.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For melting one tonne of cast iron", "opta": "700 m3 air is required", "optb": "20 kg limestone is required", "optc": "one quintal coke is required", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For filling cracks in masonry structures, the type of bitumen used, is", "opta": "cut-back bitumen", "optb": "bitumen-emulsion", "optc": "blown bitumen", "optd": "plastic bitumen.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Plastic", "opta": "is an organic substance", "optb": "consists of natural or synthetic binders", "optc": "finished products are rigid and stable at normal temperature", "optd": "is capable of flow when necessary heat and pressure are applied", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vanadium steel is generally used for", "opta": "railway switches and crossing", "optb": "bearing balls", "optc": "magnets", "optd": "axles and springs.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In basic Bessemer process, the steel heats the converter", "optb": "In open-hearth process, the furnace heats the steel", "optc": "In Siemens process, the impurities of pig iron are oxidised by the oxygen of the ore", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The process of manufacturing steel by heating short lengths of wrought iron bars mixed with charcoal in fire clay crucibles and collecting the molten iron into moulds, is known as", "opta": "Cementation process", "optb": "Crucible process", "optc": "Bessemer process", "optd": "Open hearth process.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For quality control of Portland cement, the test essentially done is", "opta": "setting time", "optb": "soundness", "optc": "tensile strength", "optd": "consistency", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If 1500 g of water is required to have a cement paste 1875 g of normal consistency, the percentage of water is,", "opta": "20%", "optb": "25%", "optc": "30%", "optd": "35%", "opte": "40%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Under normal conditions using an ordinary cement, the period of removal of the form work, is :", "opta": "7 days for beam soffits", "optb": "14 days for bottom slabs of spans 4.6 m and more", "optc": "21 days for bottom beams over 6 m spans", "optd": "2 days for vertical sides of columns", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wp and Wf are the weights of a cylinder containing partially compacted and fully compacted concrete. If the compaction factor  is 0.95, the workability of concrete is", "opta": "extremely low", "optb": "very low", "optc": "low", "optd": "high", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For given water content, workability decreases if the concrete aggregates contain an excess of", "opta": "thin particles", "optb": "flat particles", "optc": "elongated particles", "optd": "flaky paticles", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "M10 grade of concrete approximates", "opta": "1 : 3 : 6 mix", "optb": "1 : 1 : 2 mix", "optc": "1 : 2 : 4 mix", "optd": "1 : 1.5 : 3 mix", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For ensuring quality of concrete, use", "opta": "single sized aggegates", "optb": "two sized aggregate", "optc": "graded aggregates", "optd": "coarse aggregates.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.S. : 456, the number of grades of concrete mixes, is", "opta": "3", "optb": "4", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "opte": "7", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mixture of different ingredients of cement, is burnt at", "opta": "1000\u00b0C", "optb": "1200\u00b0C", "optc": "1400\u00b0C", "optd": "1600\u00b0C", "opte": "1800\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The risk of segregation is more for", "opta": "wetter mix", "optb": "larger proportion of maximum size aggregate", "optc": "coarser grading", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "After casting, an ordinary cement concrete on drying", "opta": "expands", "optb": "mix", "optc": "shrinks", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydration of cement is due to chemical action of water with", "opta": "Tricalcium silicate and dicalcium silicate", "optb": "Dicalcium silicate and tricalcium aluminate", "optc": "Tricalcium aluminate and tricalcium alumino ferrite", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To obtain cement dry powder, lime stones and shales or their slurry, is burnt in a rotary kiln at a temperature between", "opta": "1100\u00b0 and 1200\u00b0C", "optb": "1200\u00b0 and 1300\u00b0C", "optc": "1300\u00b0 and 1400\u00b0C", "optd": "1400\u00b0 and 1500\u00b0C", "opte": "1500\u00b0 and 1600\u00b0C", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Permissible compressive strength of M 300 concrete grade is", "opta": "100 kg/cm2", "optb": "150 kg/cm2", "optc": "200 kg/cm2", "optd": "250 kg/cm2", "opte": "300 kg/cm2", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The standard sand now a days used in India, is obtained from", "opta": "Jaipur (Rajasthan)", "optb": "Jullundur (Punjab)", "optc": "Hyderabad (Andhra Pradesh)", "optd": "Ennore (Madras)", "opte": "Cuttuck (Orissa).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum amount of dust which may be permitted in aggregates is", "opta": "5% of the total aggregates for low workability with a coarse grading", "optb": "10% of the total aggregates for low workability with a fine grading", "optc": "20% of the total aggregates for a mix having high workability with fine grading", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Proper proportioning of concrete, ensures", "opta": "desired strength and workability", "optb": "desired durability", "optc": "water tightness of the structure", "optd": "resistance to water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bulk density of aggregates does not depend upon :", "opta": "size and shape of aggregates", "optb": "specific gravity of aggregates", "optc": "grading of aggregates", "optd": "size and shape of the container", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Curing", "opta": "reduces the shrinkage of concrete", "optb": "preserves the properties of concrete", "optc": "prevents the loss of water by evaporation", "optd": "all of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While compacting the concrete by a mechanical vibrator, the slump should not exceed", "opta": "2.5 cm", "optb": "5.0 cm", "optc": "7.5 cm", "optd": "10 cm", "opte": "15 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Construction joints are provided", "opta": "where B.M. and S.F. are small", "optb": "where the member is supported by other member", "optc": "at 18 m apart in huge structures", "optd": "in concrete wall at sill level of windows", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An aggregate is said to be flaky if its least dimension is less than", "opta": "1/5th of mean dimension", "optb": "2/5th of mean dimension", "optc": "3/5th of mean dimension", "optd": "4/5th of mean dimension", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following proportion of the ingredients of concrete mix, is not in conformation to arbitrary method of proportioning", "opta": "1 : 1 : 2", "optb": "1 : 2 : 4", "optc": "1 : 3 : 6", "optd": "1 : 2 : 8", "opte": "1 : 4 : 10", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increased cohesiveness of concrete, makes it", "opta": "less liable to segregation", "optb": "more liable to segregation", "optc": "more liable to bleeding", "optd": "more liable for surface scaling in frosty weather", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the length to breadth of a wooden float, is", "opta": "4.5", "optb": "5.5", "optc": "6.5", "optd": "7.5", "opte": "8.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To ensure constant moisture content in aggregates", "opta": "area of each aggregate pile should be large", "optb": "height of each aggregate pile should not exceed 1.50 m", "optc": "aggregate pile should be left for 24 hours before aggregates are used", "optd": "conical heaps of aggregates should be avoided to prevent moisture variation", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Workability improved by adding", "opta": "air-entraining agent", "optb": "foaming agent", "optc": "oily-agent", "optd": "aluminium compound", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The commonly used material in the manufacture of cement is", "opta": "sand stone", "optb": "slate", "optc": "lime stone", "optd": "graphite.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If 20 kg of coarse aggregate is sieved through 80 mm, 40 mm, 20 mm, 10 mm, 4.75 mm, 2.36 mm, 1.18 mm, 600 micron, 300 micron and 150 micron standard sieves and the weights retained are 0 kg, 2 kg, 8 kg, 6 kg, 4 kg respectively, the fineness modulus of the aggregate, is", "opta": "7.30", "optb": "7.35", "optc": "7.40", "optd": "7.45", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Curing a concrete for long period ensures better", "opta": "volume stability", "optb": "strength", "optc": "water resistance", "optd": "water tightness and durability", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the construction of cement concrete floor, the maximum permissible size of aggregate, is", "opta": "4 mm", "optb": "6 mm", "optc": "8 mm", "optd": "10 mm", "opte": "12 mm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The process of proper and accurate measurement of concrete ingredients for uniformity of proportion, is known", "opta": "grading", "optb": "curing", "optc": "mixing", "optd": "batching", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Insufficient quantity of water makes the concrete mix harsh", "optb": "Insufficient quantity of water makes the concrete unworkable", "optc": "Excess quantity of water makes the concrete segregated", "optd": "Excess quantity of water causes bleeding in concrete", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The preliminary test is repeated if the difference of compressive strength of three test specimens, exceeds", "opta": "5 kg/cm2", "optb": "8 kg/cm2", "optc": "10 kg/cm2", "optd": "12 kg/cm2", "opte": "15 kg/cm2", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct proportions of chemical ingredients of cement", "opta": "Lime : Silica : Alumina : Iron oxide : 63 : 22 : 6 : 3", "optb": "Silica : Lime : Alumina : Iron oxide : 63 : 22 : 6 : 3", "optc": "Alumina : Silica : Lime : Iron oxide : 63 : 22 : 6 : 3", "optd": "Iron oxide : Alumina : Silica : Lime : 63 : 22 : 6 : 3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transport of concrete by pumps, is done for a distance of", "opta": "100 m", "optb": "200 m", "optc": "300 m", "optd": "400 m", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If X, Y and Z are the fineness modulli of coarse, fine and combined aggregates, the percentage (P) of fine aggregates to combined aggregates, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Slump test is done for", "opta": "clay", "optb": "sand", "optc": "lime", "optd": "concrete.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The high strength of rapid hardening cement at early stage, is due to its", "opta": "finer grinding", "optb": "burning at high temperature", "optc": "increased lime cement", "optd": "higher content of tricalcium.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The weight of ingredients of concrete mix, is taken in kilograms", "optb": "Water and aggregates are measured in litres", "optc": "The finished concrete is measured in cubic metres", "optd": "20 bags of cement make one tonne", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Concrete mainly consists of", "opta": "cement", "optb": "aggregates", "optc": "admixture", "optd": "water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vicat's apparatus is used for", "opta": "fineness test", "optb": "consistency test", "optc": "setting time test", "optd": "soundness test", "opte": "compressive strength test.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "M 150 grade of concrete approximates", "opta": "1 : 3 : 6 mix", "optb": "1 : 1 :2 mix", "optc": "1 : 2 : 4 mix", "optd": "1 : 1.5 : 3 mix", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Workability of concrete is measured by", "opta": "Vicat apparatus test", "optb": "Slump test", "optc": "Minimum void method", "optd": "Talbot Richard test.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rock which is not calcareous, is :", "opta": "lime stone", "optb": "macl", "optc": "chalk", "optd": "laterite", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Internal friction between the ingredients of concrete, is decreased by using", "opta": "less water", "optb": "fine aggregates", "optc": "rich mix", "optd": "more water and coarse aggregates", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For road pavements, the cement generally used, is", "opta": "ordinary Portland cement", "optb": "rapid hardening cement", "optc": "low heat cement", "optd": "blast furnace slag cement", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Construction joints are generally provided in concrete", "opta": "roads", "optb": "retaining walls", "optc": "lining of canals", "optd": "lining of tunnels", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following represents an activity", "opta": "excavation for foundation", "optb": "curing of concrete", "optc": "setting of question paper", "optd": "preparation of breakfast", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "An activity of a project is denoted by an arrow on the net work", "optb": "The tail of the arrow indicates the start of the activity", "optc": "The head of the arrow indicates the end of the activity", "optd": "The arrows are drawn to scale from left to right", "opte": "Each activity consumes a given time.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The technique for establishing and maintaining priorities among the various jobs of a project, is known", "opta": "Event flow scheduling technique", "optb": "Critical ratio scheduling", "optc": "Slotting technique for scheduling", "optd": "Short interval scheduling.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mile Stone charts were invented in the year of", "opta": "1910", "optb": "1920", "optc": "1930", "optd": "1940", "opte": "1950", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Frederick W. Taylor introduced a system of working known as", "opta": "line organisation", "optb": "line and staff organisation", "optc": "functional organisation", "optd": "effective organisation.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If to, tp and tm are the optimistic, pessimistic and most likely time estimates of an activity respectively, the expected time t of the activity will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the given figure, the network of a project represents", "opta": "activity of an excavation of a footing", "optb": "activity of an excavation which starts at event No. 1 and ends at even No. 2", "optc": "activity of excavation which takes 8 units of time", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the PERT event from the following:", "opta": "Digging of foundation started", "optb": "Digging of foundation completed", "optc": "Laying of concrete started", "optd": "Laying of concrete completed", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is the duration, ES and EF are the earliest start and finish, LS and LF are latest start and latest finish time, then the following relation holds good", "opta": "EF = ES + D", "optb": "LS = LF - D", "optc": "LF = LS + D", "optd": "D = EF - ES", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Final technical authority of a project lies with", "opta": "Assistant Engineer", "optb": "Executive Engineer", "optc": "Superintending Engineer", "optd": "Chief Engineer.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The performance of a specific task in CPM, is known", "opta": "Dummy", "optb": "Event", "optc": "Activity", "optd": "Contract.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The float may be positive, zero or negative", "optb": "If the float is positive and the activity is delayed by a period equal to its total float, the completion of project is not delayed", "optc": "If the float of an activity is negative, delay in its performance is bound to delay the completion of project", "optd": "If the float of an activity is zero, the activity is critical and any delay in its performance will delay the whole project", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Milestone chart", "opta": "shows the interdependencies of various jobs", "optb": "depicts the delay of jobs, if any", "optc": "points outgoing ahead of schedule of jobs, if any", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Completion of an activity on CPM network diagram, is generally known", "opta": "Event", "optb": "Node", "optc": "Connector", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A dummy activity", "opta": "is artificially introduced", "optb": "is represented by a dotted line", "optc": "does not consume time", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Military organisation is known as", "opta": "line organisation", "optb": "line and staff organisation", "optc": "functional organisation", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "The activity is the time consuming part of a project", "optb": "The beginning and end of a job, are called events", "optc": "The activity which consumes maximum time, is called a node", "optd": "Logically and sequentially connected activities and events form a network", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Various activities of a project, are shown on bar charts by", "opta": "vertical lines", "optb": "horizontal lines", "optc": "dots", "optd": "crosses.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Time and progress chart of a construction, is also known as", "opta": "Bar chart", "optb": "Gantt chart", "optc": "Modified Mile stone chart", "optd": "Critical path method chart", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Critical Path Net Work helps an engineer", "opta": "to concentrate his attention on critical activities", "optb": "to divert the resources from non-critical advanced activities to critical activities", "optc": "to be cautious for avoiding any delay in the critical activities to avoid delay of the whole project", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a is the optimistic time, b is the pessimistic time and m is most likely time of an activity, the expected time of the activity, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time by which activity completion time can be delayed without affecting the start of succeeding activities, is known as", "opta": "duration", "optb": "total flat", "optc": "free float", "optd": "interfering float.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The artificial activity which indicates that an activity following it, cannot be started unless the preceding activity is complete, is known as", "opta": "event", "optb": "free float", "optc": "dummy", "optd": "constant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Henry Gantt developed Bar charts for planning and scheduling of projects in", "opta": "1880", "optb": "1900", "optc": "1920", "optd": "1940", "opte": "1950", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most popular type of organisation used for Civil Engineering Constructions, is", "opta": "line organisation", "optb": "line and staff organisation", "optc": "functional organisation", "optd": "effective organisation.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference between the time avail-to do a job and the time required to do the job, is known as", "opta": "event", "optb": "float", "optc": "duration", "optd": "constraint.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The object of technical planning, is", "opta": "preparation of specifications", "optb": "preparation of estimates", "optc": "initiating the procurement action of resources", "optd": "taking remedial action for likely bottleneck in the execution", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The salient feature of functional organisation is", "opta": "strict adherence to specifications", "optb": "separation of planning and design part", "optc": "each individual maintains functional efficiency", "optd": "work is properly planned and distributed", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Critical path method", "opta": "is an improvement upon bar chart method", "optb": "provides a realistic approach to daily problems", "optc": "avoids delays which are very common in bar charts", "optd": "was invented by Morgan R. Walker of Dupot and James E. Kalley or Remington U.S.A. in 1957", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CPM is", "opta": "synthesising in concepts", "optb": "is built of activities oriented programme", "optc": "is based on time estimate", "optd": "is used for repetitive works", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Critical path lies along the activities having total float", "opta": "positive", "optb": "negative", "optc": "zero", "optd": "same.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Construction team means", "opta": "an engineer", "optb": "an architect", "optc": "an owner", "optd": "a contractor", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct network for the activities of pouring concrete, erection of form work, removal of form work and curing of concrete from the following:", "opta": "1. Pouring of Concrete  2. Erection of form work 3. Curing of concrete 4. Removal of form work", "optb": "1. Erection of form work 2. Pouring of concrete 3. Curing of concrete 4. Removal of form work", "optc": "1. Removal of form work  2. Erection of form work 3. Pouring of concrete 4. Curing of concrete", "optd": "1. Pouring of concrete 2. Curing of concrete 3. Erection of form work 4. Removal of form work", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A construction schedule is prepared after collecting", "opta": "number of operations", "optb": "output of labour", "optc": "output of machinery", "optd": "quantity of various items", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Site order book is used for recording", "opta": "instructions by the executive engineers", "optb": "construction measurements", "optc": "issue of store equipments", "optd": "names of the casual labour.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An Executive Engineer may have powers upto", "opta": "Rs. 25,000", "optb": "Rs. 50,000", "optc": "Rs. 100,000", "optd": "Rs. 200,000", "opte": "Rs. 500,000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main principle of an organisation, is", "opta": "unity of command", "optb": "cohegency", "optc": "effective control at all levels", "optd": "delegation of authority", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The estimated time required to perform an activity, is known as", "opta": "event", "optb": "dummy", "optc": "duration", "optd": "float.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A CPM family includes", "opta": "CPA (Critical Path Analysis)", "optb": "CPP (Critical Path Plotted)", "optc": "MCE (Minimum Cost Expenditure)", "optd": "CPS (Critical Path Scheduling)", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time which results in the leasi, possible construction cost of an activity, is known", "opta": "normal time", "optb": "slow time", "optc": "crash time", "optd": "standard time.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the total float and duration of an activity are 5 and 10 days respectively, the particular activity can be", "opta": "started 5 days later", "optb": "completed 5 days later", "optc": "performed at slower rate in 15 days", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Works costing less than Rs. 20,000 are treated as", "opta": "projects", "optb": "major projects", "optc": "minor projects", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A critical ratio scheduling", "opta": "establishes the relative priorities among various activities on a common basis", "optb": "determines the status of each activity", "optc": "adjusts automatically changes in activity progress", "optd": "is a dynamic system", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bar charts are suitable for", "opta": "minor works", "optb": "major works", "optc": "large projects", "optd": "all the Above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The first method invented for planning projects, was", "opta": "Bar chart method", "optb": "Milestone chart", "optc": "Critical path method (CPM)", "optd": "Programme Evaluation and Review Technique (PERT)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If TL is the latest allowable event occurrence time, total activity slack(s), is equal to", "opta": "LST-EST", "optb": "LFT-EFT", "optc": "TL-EFT", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Overall in-charge of an organisation at the site responsible for the execution of the works, is", "opta": "Executive Engineer", "optb": "Engineer", "optc": "Junior Engineer", "optd": "Sub overseer", "opte": "Assistant Engineer.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Modular co-ordination of construction means proper", "opta": "planning", "optb": "designing", "optc": "execution", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "CPM analysis is activity oriented", "optb": "PERT analysis is event oriented", "optc": "CPM does not make any allowance for the uncertainties in the duration of time", "optd": "In CPM, the time is related to cost", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to the recommendations of International Navigational Congress in 1912, the ratio of length to width at the entrance for cargo vessels is", "opta": "5.5 and 6.0 to 1", "optb": "6.2 and 6.8 to 1", "optc": "7.4 and 7.8 to 1", "optd": "8.2 and 8.5 to 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "An artificial barrier which makes the enclosed area safe for anchorage of ships, is known as break water", "optb": "The break water whose inside is used as a plateform for loading and unloading is called a mole", "optc": "The length of the quay wall is governed by the length of the largest vessel likely to be berthed", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Buoys which support the cables to which vessels are attached are of", "opta": "cylindrical shape", "optb": "drum", "optc": "pear shaped", "optd": "spherical shape", "opte": "all of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The beach is built:", "opta": "with largest material locally available to the waves", "optb": "with large material locally available to the waves", "optc": "with fine material locally available to the waves", "optd": "with finest material locally available to the waves.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flow of air from one place to the other is caused due to", "opta": "the sum of elevation", "optb": "pressure head", "optc": "velocity head", "optd": "all of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "For nautical purposes, low water level is generally referred to by the navigators", "optb": "The depth of the bed of the sea from the surface of water is called sounding", "optc": "The contour lines on the bed of a water body are called fathoms", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The direction of the littoral drift depends upon the direction of the wave with respect to the coastline", "optb": "The direction of a river opening to the sea determines the direction of no littoral drift", "optc": "Harbour in the path of littoral drift is not constructed to avoid a build up of sand on one side and erosion on the other", "optd": "all of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A low wall built out into the sea more or less perpendicular to the coast line, to resist the travel of sand and shingle along a beach, is called", "opta": "break water", "optb": "break wall", "optc": "groins", "optd": "shore wall.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At a place the shore line is along North West-South East. The wind is blowing from the north. The littoral drift will be along", "opta": "south east", "optb": "south", "optc": "south west", "optd": "west", "opte": "north west", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If F is the fetch, the straight line distance of open water available in kilometres, the height of the wave in metres is", "opta": "0.15 F", "optb": "0.20 F", "optc": "0.28 F", "optd": "0.34 F", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to the recommendations of International Navigational Congress in 1912, the ratio of length to width at the entrance for passenger vessels is :", "opta": "7.25 to 1", "optb": "7.80 to 1", "optc": "8.11 to 1", "optd": "8.44 to 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The operation of removing material from the sea or river bed is known as", "optb": "Dredging", "optc": "Digging", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Littoral drift", "opta": "is the raised line of sand, parallel to the sea coast", "optb": "is the slow movement of surface water at sea caused by the wind", "optc": "is a current parallel to the shore, caused due to tangential component of the wind", "optd": "is a current perpendicular to the shore line caused due to wind.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heaviest line is used to democrate", "opta": "the low water line", "optb": "the high water line", "optc": "the limit of swamps", "optd": "the direction of current.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "The soundings are made with respect to the mean low water", "optb": "The soundings which are below the datum are written in black on the map", "optc": "The spot heights of the features above datum are written in red on the map", "optd": "The decimal point of the sounding value is at the exact position of the sounding", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement function following:", "opta": "The coarse material which has a smaller angle of repose, causes a steeper beach slope", "optb": "The coarse material which has a greater angle of repose, causes a steeper beach slope", "optc": "The flattening out of the beach is caused due to the movement of small and uniform particles leeward.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wavelength is computed by Bertin's formula (where T is the period in seconds).", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The regular periodic rise and fall of the surface of the sea, is called tide.", "optb": "The average difference in water level between high tide and low tide at a place, is called tidal range", "optc": "The movement of water caused by the action of tide, is called a tidal current", "optd": "all of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Depth of borings for soil investigation, is generally kept below low water level", "opta": "30 m", "optb": "35 m", "optc": "45 m", "optd": "40 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following land marks on the coast line must be depicted on hydrographic maps ?", "opta": "shore line", "optb": "light houses", "optc": "church spires", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A lead line or sounding line", "opta": "is stretched thoroughly when wet before it is graduated", "optb": "should be soaked in water for about one hour prior to taking soundings", "optc": "is adjusted at regular interval", "optd": "is generally used for depths exceeding 6 m", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The smoothened surface of the front face of the guay walls, is known as fending which is made of", "opta": "granite stone", "optb": "timber", "optc": "steel", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shore line survey includes :", "opta": "depicting the shore line", "optb": "depicting the prominent details on shore line", "optc": "depicting the high water line", "optd": "depicting the low water line", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is not relevant to hydrographic survey :", "opta": "establishment of a chain of bench marks near the shore line", "optb": "establishment of horizontal control points on the shore", "optc": "determination of the sea bed profile", "optd": "depicting the irregularities in the shore line, islands and projecting rocks", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The important component of a sea port is", "opta": "terminal buildings", "optb": "the docks", "optc": "the harbour", "optd": "all of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cretans :", "opta": "are the harbours established on the island south east of Greek mainland", "optb": "are the natives of crete, an island south of Greek mainland", "optc": "are the plants, grown in the neighbourhood of harbours", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fixed mooring does not require", "opta": "mooring post", "optb": "bollard", "optc": "anchors", "optd": "capstan.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The low water datum for a lake is defined as the surface of the lake when it is at elevation", "opta": "180.5 m above M.S.L.", "optb": "190.5 m above M.S.L.", "optc": "170.5 m above M.S.L.", "optd": "200.0 m above M.S.L.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P and Q are two stations on the shore line at distance d. If the angle between Q and the boat O and P is a and the angle between P and Q at boat O is \u03b2, the x and y. Coordinate along PQ and perpendicular to PQ from O are :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A harbour is a place where", "opta": "ships get shelter and protection against destructive forces due to sea waves", "optb": "facilities are provided for receiving cargo and passengers", "optc": "port buildings are constructed for commercial purposes", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following: In a dry dock block made of hard wood,", "opta": "spacing of the blocks is 1.35 m", "optb": "the lowest block is 1.8 m long 40 cm x 40 cm in cross-section", "optc": "the middle block is 1.6 m long 40 cm x 40 cm in crosss-section", "optd": "the top block is 1.2 m long 40 cm x 40 cm in cross-section", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On a hydrographic map, the following feature is shown :", "opta": "datum", "optb": "high and low water lines", "optc": "depth contours", "optd": "land and water areas", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to the impact of water wave on a sea shore structure", "opta": "hydrostatic pressure coupled with a strong momentary impact is caused", "optb": "vibrations are subjected", "optc": "internal pressure is developed", "optd": "weakens the foundation", "opte": "all of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The horizontal angles from the boat between A and B and B and C, the stations on the shore are respectively \u03b81 and \u03b82. The distances AB = L1 and BC = L2. For calculating the angle \u03b12 at C between the boat and station B is obtained by using the following formula: where (\u03b2 is horizontal angle between A and C at B).", "opta": "", "optb": "\u03b1t tan \u03b12 = 360\u00b0 - (\u03b81 + \u03b82 + \u03b2) = \u03c6", "optc": "", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The breakwater which can be used as a platform for loading and unloading of cargo is called a mole", "optb": "The brick masonry retaining wall which is used for loading and unloading of cargo is called guay wall", "optc": "Three types of break waters are generally provided in harbours", "optd": "All of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dock wall is designed as a gravity retaining wall and is tested for", "opta": "back fill pressure when the dock is empty", "optb": "maximum water pressure from the dock without any back fill", "optc": "the load charge transmitted to the dock by the movement of loaded vehicles or trains on the way", "optd": "all of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shape of docks and basins is generally kept", "opta": "rectangular ways", "optb": "diamond shape guays", "optc": "inclined gauys", "optd": "all of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Surf zone is :", "opta": "the fathom line of 10 m depth", "optb": "the fathom line of 5 m depth", "optc": "the swell of the sea breaking on the shore or reefs", "optd": "the coast line attacked by the waves.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following lines is used for tying a ship with a dock", "opta": "bow line", "optb": "stern line", "optc": "spring line", "optd": "break line", "opte": "all of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Soundings are required for", "opta": "making nautical charts for navigation", "optb": "ascertaining the areas subject to scour or silting", "optc": "obtaining detailed information for construction", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If h and h1 are the heights of a light house and the observer in a ship in metres above M S L then the horizontal distance from the ship to the light house in kilometres is", "opta": "3.86 (h + h1)", "optb": "3.86 (h - h1)", "optc": "3.86 (h x h1)", "optd": "3.86 \u03c0 (h + h1)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The artificial barrier constructed to enclose \"n area for safe anchorage, is called break water", "optb": "The smoothened surface at the top end of the vertical face of a guay wall, is called fending", "optc": "The effective berthing lengths of inclined guays can be adjusted", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For location of soundings a range and one angle from the shore involves the following operations. Which one is correct ?", "opta": "A range line is established", "optb": "The first and the last soundings and every tenth soundings are fixed by angular observations", "optc": "The intermediate soundings are fixed by the time intervals", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "the Mediterranean sea is considered to be a huge harbour", "optb": "the Caspean sea is considered to be a big harbour", "optc": "the Red sea is considered to be harbour", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "a harbour without any port complex, is called a refuge harbour", "optb": "a harbour used for fishery, is called fishery harbour", "optc": "the terminal building of a commercial harbour consists of an administrative block, customs clearance and ware-houses.", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "As a wave of sea water approaches the coast line, it is generally accompanied by a drift of water in the direction of wave advance", "optb": "The on-shore wind helps to produce wave action as well as rise of M.S.L.", "optc": "A falling hydraulic gradient occurs in the direction of the wave", "optd": "The wave while receding carries finer particles out to deep water.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a wet dock system,", "opta": "minimum required depth of water for the vessels is maintained", "optb": "entrance locks are provided with massive gates", "optc": "the locks of dock gate are operated by means of heavy bascule bridges and connected machinery", "optd": "the cost of construction is quite heavy", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A roadstead :", "opta": "is a protected area of water where boats can move safely", "optb": "is the end of the road at the harbour", "optc": "may be protected by break water walls", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The width of the entrances of the harbours is restricted to", "opta": "100 m", "optb": "125 m", "optc": "150 m", "optd": "180 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The tides at any place occur a little less than 1 hour later, each succeeding day", "optb": "The difference in time in solar hours and minutes from any lunar transit to the succeeding transit, is called high water level", "optc": "The influence of the earth's gravity alone produces level-tidal less sea", "optd": "The spinning force is maximum at the equator and zero at the poles", "opte": "All of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct ?", "opta": "Snow albedo falls at all wave length with the increase of grain size", "optb": "The effect of grain size on reflection is maximum in the near-IR region", "optc": "The effect of grain size on reflection is low in the visible region of the spectrum", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The refractive index of the ocean water:", "opta": "increases with salinity", "optb": "increases with temperature", "optc": "decreases with salinity", "optd": "decreases with temperature", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The arrangement of terrain features which provides attributes: the shape, size and texture of objects, is called :", "opta": "spectral variation", "optb": "spatial variation", "optc": "temporal variation", "optd": "None of these .", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electromagnetic radiation :", "opta": "produces a time varying magnetic field and vice versa", "optb": "once generated, remains self-propagat-ing.", "optc": "is capable to travel across space", "optd": "consists of magnetic and electric fields", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the important characteristic of a target which facilitates its identification from the following:", "opta": "spectral variation", "optb": "spatial variation", "optc": "temporal variation", "optd": "polarisation variation", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following frequency regions is a part of sun's radiation?", "opta": "Ultraviolet frequency region", "optb": "Visible frequency region", "optc": "Infrared frequency region", "optd": "Radio frequency region", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The instruments which provide electromagnetic radiation of specified wave length or a band of wave lengths to illuminate the earth surface, are called :", "opta": "sensonrs", "optb": "passive sensors", "optc": "active sensors", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to pertubation of the orbit, satellite orbit parameters are frequently updated on measurements carried out by its", "opta": "six ground stations", "optb": "five ground stations", "optc": "four ground stations", "optd": "three ground stations", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coherence of two electromagnetic waves takes place if their phase difference is :", "opta": "constant in time", "optb": "constant in space", "optc": "constant in time and space", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The part radiation due to scattered/diffused radiation entering the field of view of a remote sensor other than that from the required target,", "opta": "reduces the contrast of the image and also its sharpness", "optb": "increases the contrast of the image but reduces the sharpness", "optc": "increases both the contrast and sharpness", "optd": "reduces the contrast but increases the sharpness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following residual biases involves the GPS accuracy ?", "opta": "Satellite dependent baises due to uncertainty in the orbital parameters of the satellite.", "optb": "Receiver-depandent biases due to clock stability with line", "optc": "Signal propagation baises due to the sphere and troposphere propogation.", "optd": "All the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct definition from the following with response to GIS.", "opta": "Common boundry between two areas of a locality is known as adjacency.", "optb": "The area features which are wholly contained within another area feature, is known so containment.", "optc": "The geometric property which describes the linkage between line features is defined as connectivity.", "optd": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following errors is produced by platform characteristics of the sensor ?", "opta": "altitude variation", "optb": "altitude", "optc": "orbit drift", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coherence length over which there is a strong relationship between amplitudes is;", "opta": "directly proportional to the bandwidth", "optb": "inversely proportional to the bandwidth", "optc": "the square of the bandwidth", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the given figure the phase of", "opta": "crest A is \u03c0/2", "optb": "B crossing is \u03c0", "optc": "trough C is 3 \u03c0/2", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If 0 is the angle of scan measured from the nadir, the ground distance swept by the sensor IFOV is proportional to :", "opta": "sin2\u03b8", "optb": "cos2\u03b8", "optc": "sec2\u03b8", "optd": "tan2\u03b8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the GPS satellites ?", "opta": "The nominal altitude is about 20, 200 km", "optb": "The inclination of axis satellite is 55\u00b0", "optc": "The satellite transmits two L band signals (L1 with 1575.42 MHz and L2 with 1276.6 MHz)", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Indian space effort started in 1962 with the establishment of a rocket.", "optb": "Development of space (DOS) was established by the Government of India in 1972", "optc": "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) is responsible for the space technology and its application to various activities.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rayleigh's criteria for a rough surface is: (where letters carry their usual meanings).", "opta": "h > \u03bb/\u0394 cos \u03b8", "optb": "h = \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "optc": "h > \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "optd": "h < \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "The distance between two successive crests or troughs of a wave, is called, the wave length", "optb": "The wave length is measured in metres and a fraction of a metre", "optc": "The wave length is generally denoted by \u03bb", "optd": "The length of the crest from the mid point, is called amplitude", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The basic requirement of any sensor system, is :", "opta": "radiometric resolution", "optb": "spatial resolution", "optc": "spectral resolution", "optd": "temporal resolution", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following helps to identify the objects on the earth surface ?", "opta": "atmospheric window", "optb": "signature", "optc": "radiometric error", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The spectral region of the electromagnetic radiation which passes through the atmosphere without much attenuation is known as:", "opta": "ozone hole", "optb": "atmospheric window", "optc": "ozone window", "optd": "black hole", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "During the day, earth reflects solar radiation", "optb": "During the day earth reflects both solar radiation the emission from its surface", "optc": "During the night, earth emits radiation from its surface", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The remote sensing techniques applied for the earth's surface features, is generally confined to the following wave lengths :", "opta": "0.4 to 1.3, 1.5 to 1.8, 2.2 to 2.6 \u03bcm", "optb": "2.2 to 2.6, 3.0 to 3.6, 4.2 to 5.0 \u03bcm", "optc": "4.2 to 5.0, 7.0 to 15.0 \u03bcm and 1 cm to 30 cm", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of energy quantum for radiation of any frequency is proportional to :", "opta": "the frequency", "optb": "the reciprocal of the energy", "optc": "the square of the frequency", "optd": "the square root of the frequency", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phase difference of the waves 1 and 2 at A in the given figure is :", "opta": "\u03c0/4", "optb": "\u03c0/2", "optc": "\u03c0", "optd": "3\u03c0/2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A perfectly black body :", "opta": "is a diffuse emitter", "optb": "absorbs all the radiations of every wave lengths", "optc": "emits power of every wave length", "optd": "All the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "When the electric field oscillates in the direction of the electric vector, a plane polarised wave is formed.", "optb": "When the electric vector is in the plane of incidence, vertical polarisation is formed.", "optc": "When the electric vector is at right angles to the plane of incidence, horizontal polarization wave is formed.", "optd": "The plane containing the incident ray and normal to the reflecting surface at the point of incidence is called the plane of incidence.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Phase of a wave is expressed as a fraction of a period with respect to a refrence", "optb": "Phase is usually specified by angular measure with one period being 360\u00b0", "optc": "The reference for finding the phase of a wave is taken from the previous passage through zero from the negative to the positive direction.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A and B are two towers of equal height diametrically opposite on either side of the nadir point, at 3 km and 5 km distances. Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "Height displacement of A will be less than that of B", "optb": "Height displacement of B will be less than that of A", "optc": "Height displacement of A and B is equal", "optd": "Height displacement of A and B will be towards each other", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Remote sensing techniques makes use of the properties of-----emitted, reflected or diffracted by the sensed objects:", "opta": "electric waves", "optb": "soundwaves", "optc": "electromagnetic waves", "optd": "wind waves", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following parameters is accurate for DGPS.", "opta": "Positional accuracies ~ 1 - 2 m if rover is less than 1-2 km from the reference station", "optb": "Positional accuracies ~ 2 - 5m if rover is less than 2-5 fm from the reference station", "optc": "Positional accuracies ~ 5 - 10 m if rover is less than 5-10 km from reference station", "optd": "Positional accuracies ~ 5 - 10 m if rover is less than 25 km", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most widely used antenna in GPS is", "opta": "Parabolid antenna", "optb": "Microstrip antenna", "optc": "Horn antenna", "optd": "Slotted antenna", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding remote sensing is correct.", "opta": "The interaction of the electromagnetic radiation with the target", "optb": "The emission of electromagnetic radiation from the target", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"An Electromagnetic wave falls on to a boundary between two loss less homogeneous media with different refractive indices, a part of the wave is reflected back to the incident medium and the rest is transmitted on to the second media\". This phenomenon is known as :", "opta": "Fresnel reflection", "optb": "Fresnel refraction", "optc": "Snell's law", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following relationship between the wave length (\u03bb), and frequency and the speed (C) of the electromagnetic wave is correct ?", "opta": "C = v + \u03bb", "optb": "", "optc": "C = v\u03bb", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The various stages occuring in GPS system are described below :1. Generation of an output to the user2. Detection of the GPS signal3. Processing the data in the built-in-computer4. Decoding the GPS signal.The correct sequence of the stages is :", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "2, 3, 4, 1", "optc": "2, 4, 3, 1", "optd": "3, 1, 2 , 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reflection of solar energy is characterised by the water content in the leaf, in the reflective optical infrared:", "opta": "visible (0.4 - 0.7 \u03bcm) region", "optb": "near-IR (0.7 - 1.3 \u03bcm) region", "optc": "short wave-IR (1.3 - 2.7 \u03bcm) region", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one the following is a correct statement?", "opta": "The vertical section of the soil extending into the parent material, is called profile", "optb": "The layers of the soil parallel to the earth surface, are called horizons.", "optc": "The transitional layer between two adjoining horizons, is called boundary.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The entire range of the electromagnetic spectrum spans a large spectrum of wave lengths varying from:", "opta": "10-10 to 106 m", "optb": "10-8 to 106 m", "optc": "10-10 to 1010 m", "optd": "10-8 to 108 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Topology describes the geometric characteristic of objects which do not change under transformations and are independent of any coordinate system", "optb": "Topological characteristics of an object are independent of scale measurement", "optc": "The three elements of topology are adjacency, containment, and connectivity", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following parameters is considered to determine the reflectance of a vegetation canopy", "opta": "Solar zenith angle", "optb": "Azimuth angle", "optc": "Look angle", "optd": "Number and arrangement of leaves", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reduction of nitrogen nutrient in plants :", "opta": "affects leaf colour", "optb": "reduces pigment concentration", "optc": "increase the visible reflectivity", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The surface defined by the locus of points having same phase, is called a wave front.", "optb": "The wave whose surface of constant phase are parallel planes, is known as a plane wave.", "optc": "The relative phase difference between the waves is important and not the absolute phase of a point on the wave", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Leaf reflactance depends primarily on :", "opta": "the pigments", "optb": "internal cell structure", "optc": "equivalent water content", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "The ratio of the up flux and down flux just above the snow surface, is called albedo", "optb": "Spectral albedo of snow is calculated for the semi-infinite snow thickness", "optc": "Water equivalent height of snow is the height of water column obtained by melting snow.", "optd": "A homogeneous snow pack is one whose average grain size does not vary with depth.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Permeability is a measure of conducting the magnetic lines of force in the material.", "optb": "Permeability is a measure of the extent to which magnetic lines of force can penetrate a medium.", "optc": "Permeability is expressed as the ratio of the magnetic flux density (B) to the field strength of the magnetizing field.", "optd": "The force between the magnetic poles is inversely proportional to the permeability of the medium.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In remote sensing technique, the observation place, is called a platform", "optb": "Platforms may be either stationary or mobile", "optc": "Spatial resolution of the imaging system becomes poorer with increase of platform height.", "optd": "Area coverage of the imaging system increases with the increase of the platform altitude.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following questions is relevant to the construction estimates :", "opta": "Did the estimators precisely evaluate site conditions ?", "optb": "Did the estimators use short cut methods which may be un realistic in their situation ?", "optc": "How much money will the contractor's risk, loosing if he Were to submit bid on the raw estimate of cost.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio obtained by dividing 'quick assests' by current liabilities is called", "opta": "Turnover ratio", "optb": "Acid test ratio", "optc": "Solvency ratio", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following definitions, is correct ?", "opta": "The ratio of total debt to share holder's equity is called 'debt ratio'.", "optb": "The ratio debt-to-total assests is called Debt-to-total assest ratio.", "optc": "The ratio of earnings before interest and taxes for a particular reporting period to the amount of interest charges for the period, is called interest coverage ratio.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the element of the cost from the following:", "opta": "direct material", "optb": "direct labour", "optc": "Over head", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The estimator for definitive estimates must be able :", "opta": "and an all-around construction expert.", "optb": "to read the plans and specifications to determine accurate quantities of permanent materials and installed Equipment.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The change in the amount of money over a given time period is called 'time value' of money, a most important concept in engineering economy.", "optb": "The manifestation of the time value of money is termed as interest.", "optc": "Interest on borrowing = present amount owed - original loan", "optd": "The original investment (or loan) is referred to as principal.", "opte": "All of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is included in financial ratios of the firm ?", "opta": "Profitability ratio", "optb": "Liquidity ratio", "optc": "Turnover ratio", "optd": "Ratio of overall performances", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The financial ratio summarises some aspect of the firm's financial condition at the time of preparing a balance sheet.", "optb": "Both the numerator and denominator of financial ratios come directly from the balance sheet.", "optc": "Income statement ratios compare one 'flow' item from the income statement to another flow item from the income statement.", "optd": "Income statement ratios compare a flow item from the income statement to another flow item form the income statement", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refer to the cash flow diagram of uniform gradient in a cash flow (in the given figure), the gradient is :", "opta": "Rs 10000 per year", "optb": "Rs 15000 per year", "optc": "Rs 20000 per year", "optd": "Rs 25000 per year", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the cash-flow diagram shown in the given figure", "opta": "Equal deposits of Rs 3000 per year (A) are made, starting now.", "optb": "The rate of interest is 10% per yearaccount", "optc": "The amount accumulated after the seventh deposit is to be computed", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The estimate based on a detailed quantity survey and furnishes the most accurate and reliable estimate possible is known as", "opta": "Conceptual estimate", "optb": "Definitive estimate", "optc": "Probabilistic estimate", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sunk costs include :", "opta": "a past expenditure", "optb": "an unrecovered balance", "optc": "an invested capital that cannot be retreived", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Current assests less inventories divided by current liabilities is known as", "opta": "Liquidity ratio", "optb": "Current ratio", "optc": "Acid-Test (or Quick) ratio", "optd": "Debts ratio", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "The number of years required to recover the initial cash investment in a project, is called Pay Back period (PBP).", "optb": "The discount rate that equates the present value of the expected Net Cash Flows (CFs) with the Initial Cash Outflow (ICO) is known as internal rate of return.", "optc": "The present value of the proposal's net cash flows, less the proposal's initial cash outflow is known as the Net Present Value (NPV)", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The alternatives which are standalone solutions for given situations in engineering involve :", "opta": "a purchase cost (first cost)", "optb": "the anticipated life of the assest", "optc": "the yearly costs of maintaining the assest (annual maintenance and operating cost)", "optd": "the anticipated resaleable value (salvage value) and the interest return (rate of return)", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of current assests to current liabilities is known as", "opta": "Liquidity ratio", "optb": "Current ratio", "optc": "Acid-Test (or Quick) ratio", "optd": "Debts ratio", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "An annuity is a series of equal payments occurring at equal period of time.", "optb": "Annuity is called an equal payment or uniform payment series.", "optc": "An annuity may have periods of time of any length but should always be of equal length.", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The construction estimate of a project is used by :", "opta": "the owner of the facility", "optb": "the consulting architect/engineer", "optc": "the contractor of the project", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Both architect and engineer make use of the cost estimate of the project:", "opta": "for site selection", "optb": "for designing of the project", "optc": "for choosing alternatives", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a is the base amount expenditure, b is the increase in the operation cost each year over a period of n years, the total cost of maintenance is :", "opta": "a + (n + 1) b", "optb": "a + (n - 1) b", "optc": "a x (n - 1) b", "optd": "a - (n - 1) b", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The more critical (or severe) test of the firm's liquidity can be judged by :", "opta": "Liquidity ratio", "optb": "Current ratio", "optc": "Acid-Test (or Quick) ratio", "optd": "Debts ratio", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ratio analysis of a construction firm is used for analysis by :", "opta": "share holders", "optb": "firm's management", "optc": "Banks of the firm", "optd": "financial analysts", "opte": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "", "optb": "Over head cost per unit = Overhead ratio x direct labour cost/unit", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (6)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Probabilistic estimating of a construction project includes:", "opta": "Labour", "optb": "Productivity", "optc": "wage scale", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A construction estimate is used", "opta": "to judge tentatively or approximate value of the project", "optb": "to produce a statement of the approximate cost", "optc": "to decide an approximation of the value of the project and not the exact cost.", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The capital required to get a project started, is called first cost.", "optb": "The costs associated with a new or existing project that remain unaffected by the changes in activity level over the normal range of operation of the project, are called fixed costs.", "optc": "The group of costs that vary proportionately to the changes in the activity level of a new or existing project are called variable costs.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Present worth Annuity (PWA) is generally known as", "opta": "Premium annuities", "optb": "Income annuities", "optc": "Future annuities", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the ratio which gives us sufficient information by which to judge the financial condition and performance of the firm, from the following:", "opta": "Liquidity ratio", "optb": "Financial leverage ratio", "optc": "Activity ratio", "optd": "Portability", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The ratios which show profitability in relation to sales and those which show profitability in relation to investment, are called profitability ratios.", "optb": "The ratio of gross profit and net sales, is called profitability in relation to sales ratio.", "optc": "The ratio of net profit after taxes to total assests is known as profitability in relation to investment ratio", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The financial analysis helps to judge:", "opta": "The operational efficiency of the firm", "optb": "The financial position of the firm.", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If interest is paid more than once in a year, i is the rate of interest per year, n is the number of periods in years and m is a number of periods per years, compound amount factor (CAF) is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a cash flow series :", "opta": "uniform gradient signifies that an income or disbursement changes by the same amount in each interest period.", "optb": "Either an increase or a decrease in the amount of a cash flow is called the gradient.", "optc": "The gradient in the cash flow may be positive or negative.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If P is principal amount, i is the rate of interest and n is the number of periods in years, then the interest factor is :", "opta": "(1 + ni)", "optb": "(ni - 1)", "optc": "ni", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Ratio analysis is the procedure of determining and interpreting numerical relationship of various items of the financial statement.", "optb": "All financial ratios are obtained by relating two sets of information contained in a Single financial statement.", "optc": "The relationship between two accounting figures expressed mathematically, is known as a financial ratio.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The ability of a company to meet obligations which are likely to mature in short term, is called liquidity.", "optb": "The liquidity ratio may be defined as a relationship of current liabilities and current assests and advances.", "optc": "The liquidity ratios are used to indicate the financial position of the firm.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capital Recovery Factor (equal payments) of Capital Recovery Annuity is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Current ratio is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The interest calculated on the basis of 365 days a year, is known as :", "opta": "interest", "optb": "ordinary simple interest", "optc": "exact simple interest", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If S is the future capital accumulated in n years at the rate of interest i per annum, then present worth is :", "opta": "", "optb": "S(1 + i)n", "optc": "S(1 + i)1/n", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a cash-flow diagram :", "opta": "Time 0 is considered to be the present", "optb": "Time 1 is considered to be the end of time period 1", "optc": "A vertical arrow pointing up indicates a positive cash flow", "optd": "An arrow pointing downward indicates a negative cash flow", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Each financial ratio is generally compared by", "opta": "a past ratio calculated from the past financial standard of the firm.", "optb": "a ratio developed by using the projected financial statement of the firm.", "optc": "a ratio of some selected firms most progressive and successful at the point of consideration.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The key to profitable operation for project cost control, is :", "opta": "To keep the project cost equal to original cost estimate.", "optb": "To keep the project cost equal to subsequent construction budget.", "optc": "To keep the project cost within the cost budget and knowing when and where job costs are deviating.", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The annuity which refers to a debt payment for recovering the initial amount or capital in equal periodical payments, is known as;", "opta": "Present Worth Annuity", "optb": "Sinking fund annuity", "optc": "Compound annuity", "optd": "Capital recovery annuity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The product of CAF (S P) and PWF (S P) is:", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1", "optc": "1/3", "optd": "1/4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct reason for making conceptual (or preliminary) estimate from the following:", "opta": "To have a check on a definitive cost estimate.", "optb": "To check qoutations from contractors and/or sub contractors.", "optc": "To compute target estimate for the owner while drawings and specifications are in initial stage.", "optd": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "A NPV profile graph shows the curvilinear relationship between the net present value of the project and discount rate employed.", "optb": "In a NPV profile, if discount rate is zero, then net present value is simply total cash inflows less the total cash outflows of the project.", "optc": "As the discount rate increases, the net present value profile slopes downward to the right.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The project contractor relies on the cost of the estimate :", "opta": "for submission of a competitive bid for a lumpsum contract", "optb": "for a unit price contract", "optc": "for preparation of a definitive estimate to help negotiate contract.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wages of supervisors and material handlers are charged as :", "opta": "Over head", "optb": "direct labour cost", "optc": "indirect labour cost", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The CRF (ep) is also known as: [CRF(EP) - 8% - 7], where", "opta": "8% is the rate of interest per year", "optb": "money is borrowed for n = 7 years", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Annuities involve:", "opta": "a series of payments", "optb": "all payments of equal amount", "optc": "payment at equal time intervals", "optd": "payments at the end of periods.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the excavation where measurements are made in square metres for payment.", "opta": "Ordinary cuttings up to 1 m", "optb": "surface dressing up to 15 cm depths", "optc": "Surface excavation up to 30 cm depths", "optd": "Both (b) and (c)", "opte": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expected out turn of 2.5 cm cement concrete floor per manson per day", "opta": "2.5 sqm", "optb": "5.0 sqm", "optc": "7.5 sqm", "optd": "10 sqm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A portion of an embankment having a uniform up-gradient 1 in 500 is circular with radius 1000 m of the centre line. It subtends 180\u00b0 at the centre. If the height of the bank is 1 m at the lower end, and side slopes 2:1, the earth work involved.", "opta": "26, 000 m3", "optb": "26, 500 m3", "optc": "27, 000 m3", "optd": "27, 500 m3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The correct prismoidal formula for volume is", "opta": "D [first area + last area + \u2211 Even area + 2 \u2211 odd areas]", "optb": "[first area + last area + 4 \u2211 Even area + 2 \u2211 odd areas]", "optc": "[first area + last area + 2 \u2211 Even area + 4 \u2211 odd areas]", "optd": "[first area + last area + 2 \u2211 Even area + 4 \u2211 odd areas].", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The order of booking dimensions is", "opta": "Length, breadth, height", "optb": "Breadth, length, height", "optc": "Height, breadth, length", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As per Indian Standard Specifications, the peak discharge for domestic purposes per capita per minute, is taken", "opta": "1.80 litres for 5 to 10 users", "optb": "1.20 litres for 15 users", "optc": "1.35 for 20 users", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the item of work not included in the plinth area estimate", "opta": "Wall thickness", "optb": "Room area", "optc": "Verandah area", "optd": "W.C. area", "opte": "Courtyard area.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The bent up bars at a support resist the negative bending moment", "optb": "The bent up bars at a support resist the sharing force", "optc": "The bending of bars near supports is generally at 45\u00b0", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The brick work is measured in sq metre, in case of", "opta": "Honey comb brick work", "optb": "Brick flat soling", "optc": "Half brick walls or the partition", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brick walls are measured in sq. m if the thickness of the wall is", "opta": "10 cm", "optb": "15 cm", "optc": "20 cm", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement in case of water supply.", "opta": "Pipes laid in trenches and pipes fixed to walls are measured separately", "optb": "Cutting through walls and floors are included with the item", "optc": "Pipes are classified according to their sizes and quality", "optd": "In laying pipes, the method of jointing and fixing is specifically specified", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of laying gullies, siphons, intercepting traps, the cost includes", "opta": "Setting and laying", "optb": "Bed concreting", "optc": "Connection to drains", "optd": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In long and short wall method of estimation, the length of long wall is the centre to centre distance between the walls and", "opta": "breadth of the wall", "optb": "half breadth of wall on each side", "optc": "one fourth breadth of wall on each side", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The height of the sink of wash basin above floor level is kept", "opta": "60 cm", "optb": "70 cm", "optc": "75 cm to 80 cm", "optd": "80 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While preparing a detailed estimate", "opta": "Dimension should be measured correct to 0.01 m", "optb": "Area should be measured correct to 0.01 sqm", "optc": "Volume should be measured correct to O.Olcum", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement regarding a master trap from the following :", "opta": "It is provided in between the lower end of the house drain and the street sewer", "optb": "It is provided a cleaning eye at the top of the trap", "optc": "The height of fresh air inlet pipe fixed vertically with wall is 3 m", "optd": "The mica flap valve which opens inwards only, is fitted at the top of the inlet pipe", "opte": "The water seal is less than that of ordinary traps.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concrete work for the following part of the building of specified thickness is measured in square metres", "opta": "Root slabs", "optb": "Floors", "optc": "D.P.C.", "optd": "Wall panels", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The estimated value of the work excluding the amount for contigencies, work charged establishment, tool and plants, is called work value", "optb": "The actual expenditure involved to complete a work including incidental, establishment and travelling charges, is called actual cost", "optc": "The formal acceptance by the administrative department for incurring an expenditure on the work, is called administrative approval", "optd": "The order of a competent authority sanctioning a properly detailed estimate of the cost of a work of construction or repair is called technical sanction", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expected out turn of cement concrete 1 : 2 : 4 per mason per day is", "opta": "1.5 m3", "optb": "2.5 m3", "optc": "3.5 m3", "optd": "5.0 m3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The area of the cross-section of a road fully in banking shown in the given figure, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The plinth area of a building not includes", "opta": "area of the walls at the floor level", "optb": "area of stair cover", "optc": "internal shaft for sanitary installations up to 2 sq m. in area", "optd": "lift and wall including landing", "opte": "area of cantilevered porch.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For 12 mm thick cement plastering 1 : 6 on 100 sq.m new brick work, the quantity of cement required, is", "opta": "0.200 m3", "optb": "0.247 m3", "optc": "0.274 m3", "optd": "0.295 m3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum width of a septic tank is taken", "opta": "70 cm", "optb": "75 cm", "optc": "80 cm", "optd": "90 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The item of the brick structure measured in sq.m, is", "opta": "Reinforced brick work", "optb": "Broken glass coping", "optc": "Brick edging", "optd": "Brick work in arches.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The inspection pit or chamber is a manhole provided in a base drainage system", "opta": "at every change of direction", "optb": "at every change of gradient", "optc": "at every 30 m intervals", "optd": "at the point where vertical soil pipe joins the house drain", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the mid-section formula", "opta": "The mean depth is the average of depths of two consecutive sections", "optb": "The area of mid-sections is calculated by using mean depth", "optc": "The volume of the earth work is calculated by multiplying the mid-section area by the distance between the two sections", "optd": "The volume of the earth work is calculated by multiplying the mid-section area by the distance between the two original sections", "opte": "(a), (b) and (c) of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The item of steel work which is measured in sq.m, is", "opta": "Collapsible gates", "optb": "Rolling shutters", "optc": "Steel doors", "optd": "Ventilators and glazing.", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of 'C' of Indian type W.C. shown in the given figure is :", "opta": "400 mm", "optb": "450 mm", "optc": "500 mm", "optd": "550 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The area of a sloping surface of a protective embankment of mean height d, side slopes S : 1 and length L is", "opta": "d x d x s", "optb": "d2 x (ds)2", "optc": "L.D 1 + s2", "optd": "2 LD 1 + s2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the formation level of a highway has a uniform gradient for a particular length, and the ground is also having a longitudinal slope, the earthwork may be calculated by", "opta": "Mid-section formula", "optb": "Trapezoidal formula", "optc": "Prismoidal formula", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most reliable estiamte is", "opta": "Detailed estimate", "optb": "Preliminary estimate", "optc": "Plinth area estimate", "optd": "Cube rate estimate", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expected out turn of 12 mm plastering with cement mortar is", "opta": "2.5 sq m", "optb": "4.0 sq m", "optc": "6.0 sq m", "optd": "8.0 sq m", "opte": "10 sq m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main factor to be considered while preparing a detailed estimate, is", "opta": "Quantity of the materials", "optb": "Availability of materials", "optc": "Transportation of materials", "optd": "Location of site and local labour charges", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The damp proof course (D.P.C.) is measured in", "opta": "Cub.m", "optb": "Sq m", "optc": "Metres", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reduced levels of points, 30 metres apart along the longitudinal section of a road portion between chainages 5 and 9 are shown in the given figure. If there is a uniform up-gradient of the road 120 in 1, the chainage of the point with no filling or cutting is", "opta": "(6 + 15) chains", "optb": "(6 + 12) chains", "optc": "(6 + 18) chains", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The area is measured correct to the nearest", "opta": "0.01 sqm", "optb": "0.02 sqm", "optc": "0.03 sqm", "optd": "0.04 sqm", "opte": "0.05 sqm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cost of fittings and their fixing is specified for the following sanitary fittings", "opta": "Water closets", "optb": "Flushing pipes", "optc": "Lavatary basins", "optd": "Sinks", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The volume is measured correct to the nearest", "opta": "0.01 cum", "optb": "0.02 cum", "optc": "0.03 cum", "optd": "0.04 cum", "opte": "0.05 sum", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The earth work of cutting in trenches or borrow pits in fairly uniform ground is measured with the help of average depths of the dead men", "optb": "The earth work in trenches or borrow pits in irregular ground is measured by taking the difference in levels before and after completion of work", "optc": "The earth work in trenches or borrow pits, where neither a nor b is feasible, are measured from the fillings after deduction of voids", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the item whose weight is added to the weight of respective item, is", "opta": "Cleats", "optb": "Brackets", "optc": "Bolts", "optd": "Distance separators", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total length of a cranked bar through a distance (d) at 45\u00b0 in case of a beam of effective length L, is", "opta": "L + 0.42 d", "optb": "L + 2 x 0.42 d", "optc": "L - 0.42 d", "optd": "L - 2 x 0.4 d", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While estimating a reinforced cement structure, the omitted cover of concrete is assumed", "opta": "at the end of reminforcing bar, not less than 25 mm or twice the diameter of the bar", "optb": "in thin slabs, 12 mm minimum or diameter of the bar whichever is more", "optc": "for reinforcing longitudinal bar in a beam 25 mm minimum or diameter of the largest bar which is more", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The excavation exceeding 1.5 m in width and 10 sq.m in plan area with a depth not exceeding 30 cm, is termed as", "opta": "Excavation", "optb": "Surface dressing", "optc": "Cutting", "optd": "Surface excavation.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "Dimensions are measured to the nearest 0.01 m", "optb": "Areas are measured to the nearest 0.01 sq.m", "optc": "Cubic contents are measured to the nearest 0.1 cm m", "optd": "Weights are measured to the nearest 0.001 tonnes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If tensile stress of a steel rod of diameter D is 1400 kg/cm2 and bond stress is 6 kg/cm2, the required bond length of the rod is", "opta": "30 D", "optb": "40 D", "optc": "50 D", "optd": "53 D", "opte": "59 D", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The measurement is not made in square metres in case of", "opta": "D.P.C. (Damp proof course)", "optb": "Form works", "optc": "Concrete Jaffries", "optd": "R.C. Chhajja.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to ISI method of measurement, the order of the sequence is", "opta": "Length, breadth, height", "optb": "Breadth, length, height", "optc": "Height, length, breadth", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The assumption on which the trapezoidal formula for volumes is based, is", "opta": "The end sections are parallel planes", "optb": "The mid-area of a pyramid is half the average area of the ends", "optc": "The volume of the prismoidal is over-es-timted and hence a prismoidal correction is applied", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cross-sections for a highway is taken at", "opta": "right angle to the centre line", "optb": "30 metres apart", "optc": "intermediate points having abrupt change in gradient", "optd": "the starting end points of the curves", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The detention period in a septic tank is assumed", "opta": "20 minutes", "optb": "25 minutes", "optc": "30 minutes", "optd": "40 minutes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of simultaneous equations to be solved in the slope deflection method, is equal to :", "opta": "the degree of statical indeterminacy", "optb": "the degree of kinematic indeterminacy", "optc": "the number of joints in the structure", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum size of a fillet weld for a plate of square edge is", "opta": "1.5 mm less than the thickness of the plate", "optb": "one half of the thickness of the plate", "optc": "thickness of the plate itself", "optd": "1.5 mm more than the thickness of the plate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The treatment that should be given to the water from a deep tube well is :", "opta": "pre-settling only", "optb": "coagulation and flocculation only", "optc": "filtration only", "optd": "disinfection only", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On sag (or valley) curves the available sight distance is determined based on :", "opta": "design speed", "optb": "height of obstacle", "optc": "height of driver eye", "optd": "night-time driving conditions", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a steady radial flow into an intake, the velocity is found to vary as (1/r2), where r is the radial distance. The acceleration of the flow is proportional to", "opta": "1/r5", "optb": "1/r3", "optc": "1/r4", "optd": "1/r", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wall shown in the below figure has failed. The cause of failure or the error made in the design of the failded wall is :", "opta": "deep slip surface failure", "optb": "overturning", "optc": "no proper drainage in the clay backfill", "optd": "translational failure", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The span to depth ratio limit is specified in IS : 456-1978 for the reinforced concrete beams, in order to ensure that the", "opta": "tensile crack width is below a limit", "optb": "shear failure is avoided", "optc": "stress in the tension reinforcement is less than the allowable value", "optd": "deflection of the beam is below a limiting value", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A two span beam with an internal hinge is shown below.  The conjugate beam corresponding to this beam is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some of the structural strength of a clayey material that is lost by remoulding is slowly recovered with time. This property of soils to undergo an isothermal gel-to-soil-to-gel transformation upon agitation and subsequent rest is termed :", "opta": "Isotropy", "optb": "Anisotropy", "optc": "Thixotropy", "optd": "Allotropy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacities of \"One-way 1.5 m wide sidewalk (persons per hour)\" and \"One-way 2-lane urban road (PCU per hour, with no frontage access, no standing vehicles and very little cross traffic)\" are respectively.", "opta": "1200 and 2400", "optb": "1800 and 2000", "optc": "1200 and 1500", "optd": "2000 and 1200", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Is 459-1978 recommends to provide certain minimum steel in a RCC beam", "opta": "to ensure compression failure", "optb": "to avoid rupture of steel in case a flexural failure occurs", "optc": "to hold the stirrup steel in position", "optd": "to provide enough ductility to the beam", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shear stress develops on a fluid element, if :", "opta": "the fluid is at least", "optb": "the fluid-container is subject to uniform linear acceleration", "optc": "the fluid is inviscid", "optd": "the fluid is viscous and the flow is nonuniform", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic turbine has a discharge of 5 m3/s, when operating under a head of 20 m with a speed of 500 rpm. If it is to operate under a head of 15 m, for the same discharge, the rotational speed in rpm will approximately be", "opta": "433", "optb": "403", "optc": "627", "optd": "388", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A nozzle discharging water under head H has an outlet area \"a\" and discharge coefficient cd = 1.0. A vertical plate is acted upon by the fluid force Fj when held across the free jet and by the fluid force Fn when held against the nozzle to stop the flow, the ratio Fj/Fn is", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic turbine develops a power of 104 metric horse power while running at a speed of 100 revolutions per minute, under a head of 40 m. Its specific speed is nearest to one of the following :", "opta": "100", "optb": "628", "optc": "523", "optd": "314", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Prandtl mixing length for turbulent flow through pipes is", "opta": "independent of shear stress", "optb": "a universal constant", "optc": "zero at the pipe wall", "optd": "independent of radial distance from pipe axis", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A 40\u00b0 slope is excavated to a depth of 10 m in a deep layer of saturated clay of unit weight 20 kN.m3; the relevant shear strength parameters are cu = 70 kN/m2 and \u03c6u = 0. The rock ledge is at a great depth. The Taylor's stability coefficient for \u03c6u = 0 and 40\u00b0 slope angle is 0.18. The factor of safety of the slope is :", "opta": "2.0", "optb": "2.1", "optc": "2.2", "optd": "2.3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lysimeter and Tensiometer are used to measure respectively, one of the following groups of quantities :", "opta": "Capillary potential and permeability", "optb": "Evapotranspiration and capillary potential", "optc": "Velocity in channels and vapour pressure", "optd": "Velocity in pipes and pressure head", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ruling minimum radius of horizontal curve of a national highway in plain terrain for ruling design speed of 100 km/hour with e = 0.07 and f = 0.15 is close to", "opta": "250 m", "optb": "360 m", "optc": "36 m", "optd": "300 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Principle involved in the relationship between submerged unit weight and saturated weight of a soil is based on", "opta": "Equilibrium of floating bodies", "optb": "Archimedes' principle", "optc": "Stokes' law", "optd": "Darcy's law", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The kinetic energy correction factor for a full developed laminar flow through a circular pipe is", "opta": "1.00", "optb": "1.33", "optc": "2.00", "optd": "1.50", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The slope of the e-log p curve for a soil mass gives :", "opta": "coefficient of permeability, k", "optb": "coefficient of consolidation Cv", "optc": "compression index, Cc", "optd": "coefficient of volume compressibility, mv", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The modulus of subgrade reaction is obtained from the plate bearing test in the form of load-deformation curve. The pressure corresponding to the following settlement value should be used for computing modulus of subgrade reaction", "opta": "0.375 cm", "optb": "0.175 cm", "optc": "0.125 cm", "optd": "0.250 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "X-component of velocity in a 2-D incompressible flow is given by u = y2 + 4 xy. If Y-com-ponent of velocity 'v' equals zero at y = 0, the expression for 'v' is given by", "opta": "4y", "optb": "2y2", "optc": "-2y2", "optd": "2xy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consolidation in soils", "opta": "is a function of the effective stress", "optb": "does not depend on the present stress", "optc": "is a function of the pore water pressure", "optd": "is a function of the total stress", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cantilever beam of length L and a cross section with shape factor f supports a concentrated load P as shown below  The length LP of the plastic zone, when the maximum bending moment equals the plastic moment MP, given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum area of tension reinforcement in a beam shall be greater than", "opta": "0.85 bd/fy", "optb": "0.87 fy/bd", "optc": "0.04 bd", "optd": "0.4 bd/y", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an iceberg, 15% of the volume projects above the sea surface. If the specific weight of sea water is 10.5 kN/m3 , the specific weight of iceberg ir kN/m3 is", "opta": "12.52", "optb": "9.81", "optc": "8.93", "optd": "7.83", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reinforced concrete column contains longitudinal steel equal to 1 percent of net cross-sectional area of the column. Assume modular ratio as 10. The loads carried (using the elastic theory) by the longitudinal steel and the net area of concrete, are Ps and Pc respectively. The ratio Ps/Pc expressed as percent is", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.1", "optd": "10", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steady discharge of 1 cumec flows uniformly in a rectangular channel 1 m wide at a depth of 250 mm. The slope of the channel bed is :", "opta": "adverse", "optb": "steep", "optc": "critical", "optd": "mild", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In reinforced concrete, pedestal is defined as compression member, whose effective length does not exceed its least dimension by", "opta": "12 times", "optb": "3 times", "optc": "16 times", "optd": "8 times", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flexible pavements derive stability primarily from :", "opta": "aggregate interlock, particle friction and cohesion", "optb": "cohesion alone", "optc": "the binding power of bituminous materials", "optd": "the flexural strength of the surface course", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The permissible bending tensile stress in concrete for the vertical wall of an R.C. water tank made of M 25 concrete is :", "opta": "8.5 N/mm2", "optb": "6.0 N/mm3", "optc": "2.5 N/mm2", "optd": "1.8 N/mm2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cylinder strength of the concrete is less than the cube strength because of", "opta": "the difference in the shape of the cross section of the specimens", "optb": "the difference in the slendeness ratio of the specimens", "optc": "the friction between the concrete specimens and the steel plate of the testing machine", "optd": "the cubes are tested without capping but the cylinders are tested with capping", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A water treatment plant is required to process 28800 m3/d of raw water (density = 1000 kg/m3, kinematic viscosity = 10-6 m2/s). The rapid mixing tank imparts tank a velocity gradient of 900s-1 to blend 35 mg/l of alum with the flow for a detention time of 2 minutes. The power input (W) required for rapid mixing is", "opta": "32.4", "optb": "36", "optc": "324", "optd": "32400", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth of tension crack in a soft clay (\u03c6u = 0) is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A single rapid test to determine the pollu-tional status of river water is :", "opta": "biochemical oxygen demand", "optb": "chemical oxygen demand", "optc": "total organic solids", "optd": "dissolved oxygen", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The vertical stress at depth z, directly below the point load p is (k is a constant)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vane tester is normally used for determining in situ shear strength of :", "opta": "soft clays", "optb": "sand", "optc": "stiff clays", "optd": "gravel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the frame shown in the below figure, the maximum bending moment in the column is,", "opta": "zero", "optb": "400 kNm", "optc": "100 kNm", "optd": "200 kNm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a compaction test, as the compaction effort is increased, the optimum moisture content", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "remains same", "optc": "increases", "optd": "increases first and thereafter decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The peak discharge of the instantaneous unit hydrograph of a basin, when compared to the peak discharge of a 4-hour unit hydrograph of that basin, would be", "opta": "greater", "optb": "equal", "optc": "equal or lesser", "optd": "lesser", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The drop manholes are provided in a sewerage system when there is", "opta": "change in alignment of sewer line", "optb": "change in size of sewers", "optc": "change in the elevation of ground level", "optd": "change from gravity system to pressure system", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reaction time for calculation of stopping distance may be assumed as", "opta": "5 secs", "optb": "2.5 secs", "optc": "0.5 secs", "optd": "10.0 secs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The percentage error in the computed discharge over a triangular notch corresponding to an error of 1% in the measurement of the head over the notch, would be", "opta": "1.0", "optb": "1.5", "optc": "2.0", "optd": "2.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The characteristic strength of concrete is defined as that compressive strength below which not more than", "opta": "10% of results fall", "optb": "5% of results fall", "optc": "2% of results fall", "optd": "None of the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Un-factored maximum bending moments at a section of a reinforced concrete beam resulting from a frame analysis are 50, 80, 120 and 180 kNm under dead, live, wind and earthquake loads respectively. The design moment (kNm) as per IS: 456-2000 for the limit state of collapse (flexure) is", "opta": "195", "optb": "250", "optc": "345", "optd": "372", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The microbial quality of treated piped water supplies is monitored by", "opta": "Microscopic examination", "optb": "Plate count of heterotrophic bacteria", "optc": "Coliform MPN test", "optd": "Identification of all pathogens", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The 5-day BOD of a wastewater sample is obtained as 190 mg/l (with k = 0.01 h-1). The ultimate oxygen demand (mg/l) of the sample will be", "opta": "3800", "optb": "475", "optc": "271", "optd": "190", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A tube well having a capacity of 4 m3/hour operates for 20 hours each day during the irrigation season. How much area can be commanded if the irrigation interval is 20 days and depth of irrigation is 7 cm ?", "opta": "1.71 x 104 m2", "optb": "1.14 x 104 m2", "optc": "22.9 x 104 m2", "optd": "2.29 x 104 m2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A district road with a bituminous pavement has a horizontal curve of 1000 m for a design speed of 75 km ph. The super-elevation is", "opta": "1 in 40", "optb": "1 in 50", "optc": "1 in 60", "optd": "1 in 70", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum value of camber provided for thin bituminous surface hill roads, is", "opta": "2.2%", "optb": "2.5%", "optc": "3.0%", "optd": "3.5%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Design of horizontal and vertical alignments, super-elevation, sight distance and grades, is worst affected by", "opta": "width of the vehicle", "optb": "length of the vehicle", "optc": "height of the vehicle", "optd": "speed of the vehicle", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thickness of a pavement may be reduced considerably by", "opta": "compaction of soil", "optb": "stabilisation of soil", "optc": "drainage of soil", "optd": "combination of all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total length of a valley formed by two gradients - 3% and + 2% curve between the two tangent points to provide a rate of change of centrifugal acceleration 0.6 m/sec2, for a design speed 100 km ph, is", "opta": "16.0 m", "optb": "42.3 m", "optc": "84.6 m", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Traffic engineering only includes", "opta": "planning of regulatory measures", "optb": "design and application of control devices", "optc": "analysis of traffic characteristics", "optd": "traffic opeation", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the movement of vehicles at an intersection of two roads, without any interference, the type of grade separator generally preferred to, is", "opta": "delta", "optb": "trumpet", "optc": "diamond interchange", "optd": "clover leaf.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the ruling gradient on any highway is 3%, the gradient provided on the curve of 300 metre radius, is", "opta": "2.00%", "optb": "2.25%", "optc": "2.50%", "optd": "2.75%", "opte": "3.00%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As per recommendations of I.R.C., traffic volume study is carried out for rural roads for 7 days continuously during", "opta": "harvesing", "optb": "lean season", "optc": "harvesting and lean season", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum ratio of the radii of two circular curves of a compound curve, is kept", "opta": "1.25", "optb": "1.5", "optc": "1.75", "optd": "2.0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Border Roads Organisation for hilly regions, was formed in", "opta": "1947", "optb": "1954", "optc": "1958", "optd": "1960", "opte": "1962", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The Border Roads Organization (BRO) was conceived and raised in the year 1960 by Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru, the great visionary and the first Prime Ministry of India. This was done with the aim of coordinating the speedy development of network of roads in the North and the North Eastern border regions of the country. BRO is regarded as a symbol of nation-building, national integration and an inseparable component in maintaining the security and integrity of the country."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following. The super-elevation on roads is", "opta": "directly proportional to width of pavement", "optb": "directly proportional to velocity of vehicles", "optc": "inversely proportional to acceleration due to gravity", "optd": "inversely proportional to the radius of curvature.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weaving length of a roadway is the distance", "opta": "between the channelising islands", "optb": "equal to half circumference", "optc": "equal to total width of adjoining radial roads", "optd": "equal to diameter of rotary.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Road makers along roads from the edge of a kerb should not be less than", "opta": "40 cm", "optb": "45 cm", "optc": "50 cm", "optd": "55 cm", "opte": "60 cm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Traffic surveys are carried out", "opta": "to know the type of traffic", "optb": "to determine the facilities to traffic regulations", "optc": "to design proper drainage system", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The formula for calculating the depth of concrete pavements suggested by Goldbeck, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If A is the projected area of a vehicle in square metres, V is speed of the vehicles in kilometres per hour and C is a constant, then the wind resistance R to the moving vehicles, is given by", "opta": "R = CAV", "optb": "R = CAV2", "optc": "R = CAV3", "optd": "", "opte": "R = C2AV", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The usual width of parapet walls along Highways in hilly region, is", "opta": "50 cm", "optb": "60 cm", "optc": "70 cm", "optd": "80 cm", "opte": "100 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The road foundation for modern highways construction, was developed by", "opta": "Tresguet", "optb": "Telford", "optc": "Macadam", "optd": "Tresguet and Telford simultaneously", "opte": "Telford and Macadam simultaneously.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If N is deviation angle the length L of a parabolic vetical curve for overtaking sight distance S, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "Both (A) and (C)", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If C is basic capacity per lane, V is velocity in km/hour, S is stopping distance pluslength of the vehicles in metres, the formula  is applicable to", "opta": "district roads", "optb": "two lane roads", "optc": "two lane roads in one direction", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Width of vehicles affects the width of", "opta": "lanes", "optb": "shoulders", "optc": "parking spaces", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "First operation during the detailed survey of a hill road, is", "opta": "hydrological and soil surveys", "optb": "adjustment of alignment along with curves", "optc": "derivation of longitudinal and cross-sections", "optd": "fixation of Bench Marks", "opte": "staking the ground.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The period of long term plan for the development of roads in India, known as Bombay Plan (Aug. 1958), is", "opta": "5 years", "optb": "10 years", "optc": "15 years", "optd": "20 years", "opte": "25 years", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In water bound macadam roads, binding material, is", "opta": "sand", "optb": "stone dust", "optc": "cement", "optd": "brick dust.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Highway Research Board of U.S.A. practical land width, is", "opta": "2.7 m", "optb": "3.0 m", "optc": "3.3 m", "optd": "3.6 m", "opte": "4.5 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Design of flexible pavements is based on", "opta": "mathematical analysis", "optb": "empirical formulae", "optc": "a compromise of pure theory and pure empirical formula", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of the brakes of a vehicle depends upon", "opta": "condition of road surface", "optb": "condition of the tyres", "optc": "presence of the show moisture", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum super-elevation on hill roads should not exceed", "opta": "5%", "optb": "7%", "optc": "8%", "optd": "10%", "opte": "15%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of transition curves generally provided on hill roads, is", "opta": "circular", "optb": "cubic parabola", "optc": "Lemniscate", "optd": "spiral.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum safe speed on roads, depends on the", "opta": "type of the highway", "optb": "type of road surface", "optc": "type of curves", "optd": "sight distance", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The basic formula for determination of pavement thickness was first suggested by", "opta": "Spanglar", "optb": "Picket", "optc": "Kelly", "optd": "Goldbeck", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Increase in traffic volume, due to increase in transport vehicles, is known as", "opta": "development traffic", "optb": "normal traffic growth", "optc": "generated traffic growth", "optd": "current traffic", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If R is the radius of a main curve and L is the length of the transition curve, the shift of the curve, is", "opta": "L/24 R", "optb": "L2/24 R", "optc": "L3/24 R", "optd": "L4/24 R", "opte": "L/12 R", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight of vehicles affects", "opta": "pavement thickness", "optb": "ruling gradient", "optc": "limiting gradient", "optd": "design of bridges", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "During reconnaissance, the general route of the alignment is selected", "optb": "After reconnaissance, a trace is cut for the alignment", "optc": "Last stage is the detailed surveys for desired geometries'of the highway", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Deviation of the alignment of a trace cut may be permitted in areas involving", "opta": "land slides", "optb": "sand dunes", "optc": "dens", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If cross slope of a country is 10% to 25%, the terrain is classified as", "opta": "rolling", "optb": "mountainous", "optc": "steep", "optd": "plain.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shoulders for high traffic volume roads, should", "opta": "be stable throughout the year to be used by vehicles in the case of emergency", "optb": "support and protect the ends of carriage ways", "optc": "not allow entrance of water to sub-grade", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to the recommendations of Nagpur Conference, the width formation of an ideal National Highway in hard rock cutting, is", "opta": "8.9 m", "optb": "7.9 m", "optc": "6.9 m", "optd": "6.5 m", "opte": "7.5 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The absolute minimum radius of horizontal curve for a design speed 60 km ph is", "opta": "131 m", "optb": "210 m", "optc": "360 m", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Volume of traffic which would immediately use a new road or an improved one when opened to traffic, is known", "opta": "development traffic", "optb": "current traffic", "optc": "general traffic", "optd": "normal traffic growth.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Safety fences are provided on either side of a roadway if embankments are in excess of 6 metres", "optb": "Safety fences are provided on outside of the curves of radii less than 750 m if the embankments are between 3 metres and 6 metres", "optc": "Guard stones are provided at 2.5 metres intervals if embankments are between 1.6 metres to 3 metres", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India the modes of transportation, in the order of their importance, are", "opta": "air transport, shipping, roads, railways", "optb": "shipping, roads, railways, air transport", "optc": "roads, railways, air transport, shipping", "optd": "railways, roads, shipping, air transport", "opte": "shipping, railways, roads, air transport.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On the recommendations of Indian Road Congress, the ruling gradient in plains, is", "opta": "1 in 15", "optb": "1 in 20", "optc": "1 in 30", "optd": "1 in 45", "opte": "1 in 100", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The head light of vehicles should be such that its lower beam illuminates objects at", "opta": "10 m", "optb": "20 m", "optc": "30 m", "optd": "40 m", "opte": "50 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of the side of warning sign boards of roads is", "opta": "30 cm", "optb": "40 cm", "optc": "45 cm", "optd": "50 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A single lane carriage way whenever changes to two-lane carriage way, is affected through a taper of", "opta": "1 in 10", "optb": "1 in 15", "optc": "1 in 20", "optd": "1 in 15 to 1 in 20", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wall constructed for the stability of an excavated portion of a road on the hill side, is known as", "opta": "retaining wall", "optb": "breast wall", "optc": "parapet wall", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum number of passenger cars that can pass a given point on a road during one hour under the most ideal road way and traffic conditions, is known as", "opta": "traffic density", "optb": "basic capacity of traffic lane", "optc": "possible capacity of traffic lane", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pitot tube is used to measure", "opta": "pressure", "optb": "difference in pressure", "optc": "velocity of flow", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness of a sharp crested weir is kept less than", "opta": "one-third of the height of water on the sill", "optb": "one-half of the height of water on the sill", "optc": "one-fourth of the height of water on the sill", "optd": "two-third of the height of water on the sill", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The property of steam function \u03c8 is :", "opta": "\u03c8 is constant everwhere on any stream line", "optb": "the flow around any path in the fluid is zero for continuous flow", "optc": "the rate of change of \u03c8 with distance in an arbitrary direction, is proportional to the component of velocity normal to that direction", "optd": "the velocity vector may be found by differentiating the stream function", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum vacuum created at the summit of a syphon is", "opta": "2.7 m of water", "optb": "7.4 m of water", "optc": "5.5 m of water", "optd": "none.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the atmospheric pressure on the surface of an oil tank (sp. gr. 0.8) is 0.1 kg/cm2, the pressure at a depth of 2.5 m, is", "opta": "1 metre of water", "optb": "2 metres of water", "optc": "3 metres of water", "optd": "3.5 metres of water", "opte": "4.0 metres of water.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total pressure force on a plane area is equal to the area multiplied by the intensity of pressure at its centroid, if", "opta": "area is horizontal", "optb": "area is vertical", "optc": "area is inclined", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the volume of a liquid weighing 3000 kg is 4 cubic metres, 0.75 is its", "opta": "specific weight", "optb": "specific mass", "optc": "specific gravity", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bernoulli's equation assumes that", "opta": "fluid is non-viscous", "optb": "fluid is homogeneous", "optc": "flow is steady", "optd": "flow is along the stream line", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time required to close a valve gradually is (where L is the length of pipe and C = velocity of pressure wave)", "opta": "", "optb": "\u2264", "optc": ">", "optd": "<", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A syphon is used", "opta": "to connect water reservoirs at different levels intervened by a hill", "optb": "to supply water to a town from higher level to lower level", "optc": "to fill up a tank with water at higher level from a lower level", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most economical section of a circular channel for maximum discharge", "opta": "depth of water = 0.95 diameter of circular section", "optb": "hydraulic mean depth = 0.286 diameter of circular section", "optc": "wetted perimeter = 2.6 diameter of circular section", "optd": "wetted perimeter = 2.83 depth of water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Unit of kinematic viscosity is", "opta": "m2/sec", "optb": "Newton sec/m2", "optc": "Newton sec/m3", "optd": "Kg sec/m2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The moment of inertia of a floating body along its longitudinal axis and the volume of water displaced by it are I and V respectively. The height of the metacentre above centre of buoyancy of the body, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Time of emptying liquid from a hemispherical vessel through an orifice at its bottom, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Critical depth (h) of a channel, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of maximum velocity to average velocity of viscous fluid through a circular pipe is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "0.75", "optc": "1.25", "optd": "2.00", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shear stress distribution in viscous fluid through a circular pipe is :", "opta": "maximum at the centre", "optb": "maximum at the inside of surface", "optc": "same throughout the section", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Product of Renold number, Froud's number and Mach number is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "For tranquil flow h > 2g or v <", "optb": "For critical flow", "optc": "For torrential flow h >  or v < gh", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The side slope of Cipolletti weir is generally kept", "opta": "1 to 4", "optb": "1 to 3", "optc": "1 to 2", "optd": "1 : 5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cylinder 3 m in diameter and 4 m long retains water one side as shown in the below figure. If the weight of the cylinder is 2000 kgf, the horizontal reaction at B is", "opta": "10,000 kgf", "optb": "15,000 kgf", "optc": "20,000 kgf", "optd": "18,000 kgf.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inside pressure in a hollow soap bubble in the air is : (where d is the diameter of the bubble)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The momentum correction factor (\u03b2) for the viscous flow through a circular pipe is", "opta": "1.25", "optb": "1.33", "optc": "1.50", "optd": "1.66", "opte": "2.00", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A piezometer opening in pipes measures", "opta": "velocity head", "optb": "static pressure", "optc": "total pressure", "optd": "negative static pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An independent mass of a fluid does not posses", "opta": "elevation energy", "optb": "kinetic energy", "optc": "pressure energy", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While applying the Bernoulli's equation  = total head, the work any section done on the flow system, if any", "opta": "is added on the right side of the equation", "optb": "is added on the left side of the equation", "optc": "is ignored", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge Q over a rectangular weir of length L and height H, is given by the equation", "opta": "Q = 2/3 Cd2g LH3/2", "optb": "Q = 2/3 CdL H2gH", "optc": "", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A short tube mouthpiece will not run full at its outlet if the head under which the orifice works, is", "opta": "less than 12.2 m of the water", "optb": "more than 12.2 m of the water", "optc": "equal of 12.2 m of water", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrostatic pressure on a dam depends upon its", "opta": "length", "optb": "depth", "optc": "shape", "optd": "material", "opte": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When two layers of a fluid separated by dy move over the other with a difference of velocity dv, causes a shearing stress , where \u03bc is known as", "opta": "coefficient of viscosity", "optb": "absolute viscosity", "optc": "dynamic viscosity", "optd": "viscosity", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pipe of 0.1 m2 cross sectional area suddenly enlarges to 0.3 m2 cross-sectional area. If the discharge of the pipe is 0.3 m3 /sec, the head loss is", "opta": "2/g m of water", "optb": "g/2 m of water", "optc": "1g m of water", "optd": "g m of water.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum efficiency of transmission of power through a pipe, is", "opta": "25%", "optb": "33.3%", "optc": "50%", "optd": "66.67%.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal flow of a liquid obeys", "opta": "Continuity equation", "optb": "Newton's law of viscosity", "optc": "Newton's second law of motion", "optd": "dynamic viscosity law,", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Euler's equation for motion of liquids, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "\u03c1dp + gdz + vdv = 0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reynold number is the ratio of initial force and", "opta": "viscosity", "optb": "elasticity", "optc": "gravitational force", "optd": "surface tension.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body is totally or partially immersed in a fluid, it is buoyed up by a force equal to", "opta": "weight of the body", "optb": "weight of the fluid displaced by the body", "optc": "weight of the body and fluild displaced by the body", "optd": "difference of weights of the fluid displaced and that of the body", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is the diameter of a pipe of length L and f is the coefficient of friction of pipe then diameter of the nozzle d is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the total head of the nozzle of a pipe is 37.5 m and discharge is 1 cumec, the power generated is", "opta": "400 H.P.", "optb": "450 H.P.", "optc": "500 H.P.", "optd": "550 H.P.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phenomenon occuring in an open channel when a rapidly flowing stream abruptly changes to a slowly flowing stream causing a distinct rise of liquid surface, is", "opta": "water hammer", "optb": "hydraulic jump", "optc": "critical discharge", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a circular pipe of length L and diameter d, a viscous liquid is flowing with a velocity v. The loss in head, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The horizontal component of the force on a curved surface is equal to", "opta": "weight of liquid vertically below the curved surface", "optb": "force on a vetical projection of the curved surface", "optc": "product of pressure at its centroid and the area", "optd": "weight of liquid retained by the curved area.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radius of gyration of the water line of a floating ship is 4 m and its metacentric height is 72.5 cm. The period of oscillation of the ship, is", "opta": "\u03c0", "optb": "2\u03c0", "optc": "3\u03c0", "optd": "4\u03c0", "opte": "\u03c0/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pipe consisting of several pipes of varying diameters and lengths, may be replaced by an equivalent pipe of diameter D of length", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Empirical formula  for discharge over large rectangular weirs, is known as", "opta": "Francis formula", "optb": "Bazin formula", "optc": "Rehbook formula", "optd": "Kutter's formula.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter (d) of a nozzle fixed at the end of a pipe (diameter D, length L) for maximum energy, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement regarding Borda's mouth piece running full from the following :", "opta": "Actual velocity at the out let is gH", "optb": "Theoretical velocity at the outlet is 2gH", "optc": "Coefficient of velocity is 1/2", "optd": "Coefficient of contraction is 1", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Differential manometers are used to measure", "opta": "pressure in water channels, pipes, etc.", "optb": "difference in pressure at two points", "optc": "atmospheric pressure", "optd": "very low pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A tank 4m x 3m x 2m containing an oil of specific gravity 0.83 is moved with an acceleration g/2 m sec2. The ratio of the pressures at its bottom when it is moving vertically up and down, is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "1/3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most familiar form of Bernoulli's equation, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "= constant head", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Highest dam in India, is", "opta": "Bhakra dam", "optb": "Hirakund dam", "optc": "Nagarjuna Sagar dam", "optd": "Iddiki dam.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Borrow pits should preferably be located in", "opta": "field on the left side of the canal", "optb": "field on the right side of the canal", "optc": "fields on both sides of the canal", "optd": "central half width of the section of the canal.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Irrigation canals are generally aligned along", "opta": "ridge line", "optb": "contour line", "optc": "valley line", "optd": "straight line.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of a meander is the distance along the river between the tangent point of one curve to the tangent point of", "opta": "reverse curve", "optb": "next curve of the same order", "optc": "reverse curve plus the width of the river", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If B and d are the bed width and depth of a channel in metres, the combined losses due to evaporation and seepage in cumecs per kilometre length of the channel, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following", "opta": "Side walls of a venturi head flume are splayed out from the end of the throat at 1 : 10 for a length of 4.5 m", "optb": "Length of side walls should be such that the width of the flume is made equal to 2/3rd the bed width of the distributary", "optc": "Once the width of the flume becomes 2/3rd of the width of the distributary, the splayed walls are increased to 1 in 3 to get full bed width", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference in level between the top of a bank and supply level in a canal, is called", "opta": "berm", "optb": "free board", "optc": "height of bank", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "F.S.L. of a canal at its head with respect to parent channel is kept", "opta": "at the same level", "optb": "15 cm lower", "optc": "15 cm higher", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The measure to remove water logging of land, is", "opta": "to reduce percolation from canals and water courses", "optb": "to increase outflow from the ground water reservoir", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Attracting groynes are built", "opta": "perpendicular to the bank", "optb": "inclined down stream", "optc": "inclined up stream", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Retrogression of the bed level of a river downstream a weir, occurs due to", "opta": "heavy impact of water", "optb": "increase of the bed level", "optc": "less percentage of silt", "optd": "soft soil strata.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to G.W. Pickles the effect of confining the flood water of a river between levee, is to increase", "opta": "rate of flood wave", "optb": "water surface elevation during floods", "optc": "maximum discharge", "optd": "velocity and scouring action", "opte": "surface slope of streams above the leveed portion.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a canal syphon, the flow is", "opta": "under atmospheric pressure", "optb": "pipe flow", "optc": "with critical velocity", "optd": "under negative pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A water-logged land is found suitable for cultivation due to", "opta": "ease of tillage for preparation of the field for optimum condition of germination", "optb": "absence of aeration of soil from root zone of the plant", "optc": "regular supply of water to plants from the water table by capillary action", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal and a drainage approach each other at the same level, the structure so provided, is", "opta": "an aqueduct", "optb": "a syphon", "optc": "a level crossing", "optd": "inlet and outlet.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For smooth entry of water in a canal, the angle between head regulator and water is generally kept", "opta": "80\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "110\u00b0", "optd": "120\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If L is total length of a canal in kilometres, P is total perimeter of its lining in metres and C is the cost of lining per square metre, the additional expenditure involved on lining, is", "opta": "1000 PLC", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "In free flooding irrigation, water is admitted at one corner of a field and is allowed to spread over the entire area", "optb": "In check method of irrigation, the field is divided into smaller compartments and water is admitted to each in turn", "optc": "In furrow irrigation water is admitted between the rows of plants in the field", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fundamental momentum equation for a hydraulic jump, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a Sarda type fall, the rectangular crest, may be used for discharge upto", "opta": "6 cumecs", "optb": "10 cumecs", "optc": "14 cumecs", "optd": "20 cumecs", "opte": "25 cumecs.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal is carried over a natural drainage, the structure provided, is known as", "opta": "syphon", "optb": "aqueduct", "optc": "super passage", "optd": "syphon-aqueduct.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the stability of a structure against seepage pressure according to Khosla's creep theory, the critical gradient is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "0.25", "optc": "0.50", "optd": "0.75", "opte": "1.00", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "Approach of the water line in a flumed channel section should not be steeper than", "optb": "Departure of the water line from a flumed channel section should not be steeper than 30\u00b0", "optc": "Approach of the water line should not be steeper than 30\u00b0 and departure line not steeper than  in a flumed channel section", "optd": "Approach and departure of the water line in a flumed channel section, should not be steeper than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Groynes are generally built", "opta": "perpendicular to the bank", "optb": "inclined up stream up to 30\u00b0", "optc": "inclined down stream upto 30\u00b0", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The top of the capillary zone", "opta": "lies below the water table at every point", "optb": "lies above the water table at every point", "optc": "coincides the water table at every point", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following. Culturable commanded area is the gross area of an irrigation canal system less", "opta": "populated area", "optb": "alkaline area", "optc": "forest area", "optd": "fallow land.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "In a level crossing, a crest with its top at the canal F.S.L. is provided across the drainage at its up-stream junction with canal", "optb": "In a level crossing a regulator is provided across the drainage at its down-stream", "optc": "In a level crossing, a cross regulator is provided on the canal below the crossing", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the design of major hydraulic structures on the canals, the method generally preferred to, is based on", "opta": "Bligh's theory", "optb": "Electrical analogy method", "optc": "The relaxation method", "optd": "Khosla's method of independent variables.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For designing the venturi head,", "opta": "width of the throat should not be less than one-third of the bed width of main canal", "optb": "width of the throat should not be less than the width obtained from the formula B = Q / 1.2d3/2, where d is the difference in levels of F.S.L. and sill", "optc": "minimum throat width should not be less than 60 cm", "optd": "length of the throat should be 2.5 times the depth measured to F.S.L. in the main canal", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sinuosity of a meander is the ratio of", "opta": "meander length and the width of meander", "optb": "meander length and half width of the river", "optc": "curved length and the straight distance", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The top soil of a water logged field becomes more alkaline and infertile if its pH value is", "opta": "6", "optb": "8", "optc": "9", "optd": "10", "opte": "11", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main function of a diversion head works of a canal from a river, is", "opta": "to remove silt", "optb": "to control floods", "optc": "to store water", "optd": "to raise water level", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Side slopes generally kept for canals in loam soil, are :", "opta": "1 : 1 in cutting and  : 1 in filling", "optb": ": 1 in cutting and 2 : 1 in filling", "optc": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a canal flowing under pressure is carried below a natural drainage such that its F.S.L. does not touch the underside of the supporting structure, the structure so provided, is called", "opta": "syphon", "optb": "aqueduct", "optc": "super passage", "optd": "syphon-aqueduct.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the conditions enumerated to provide a crossing at C1 You will probably provide", "opta": "an aqueduct", "optb": "a super-passage", "optc": "a syphon aqueduct", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the straight sides of a triangular section of a lined canal with circular bottom of radius R, make an angle \u03b8 with horizontal, the perimeter of the canal is", "opta": "R(\u03b8 + tan \u03b8)", "optb": "2R(\u03b8 + tan \u03b8)", "optc": "R(\u03b8 + cos \u03b8)", "optd": "2R(\u03b8 + cos \u03b8)", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The crest level of a canal diversion head work, depends upon", "opta": "F.S.L. of the canal", "optb": "discharge perimeters", "optc": "pond level", "optd": "all the above", "opte": "none these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth of rice root zone, is", "opta": "50 cm", "optb": "60 cm", "optc": "70 cm", "optd": "80 cm", "opte": "90 cm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The intensity of irrigation means", "opta": "percentage of culturable commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optb": "percentage of gross commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optc": "percentage of the mean of culturable commanded area and the gross commanded area to be irrigated annually", "optd": "total depth of water supplied by the number of waterings.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The saturation line is the line up to which banks get saturated after the canal runs for some time. The saturation gradient in ordinary loam soil, is generally", "opta": "2 : 1", "optb": "3 : 1", "optc": "4 : 1", "optd": "5 : 1", "opte": "6 : 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth of the crest of a scouring sluice below the crest of a head regulator, is generally kept", "opta": "0.20 m", "optb": "1.20 m", "optc": "2.20 m", "optd": "3.20 m", "opte": "4.90 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge over a trapezoidal crest of a Sarda fall with free over fall conditions, is", "opta": "0.45 2g . LH3/2 (H/B)1/3", "optb": "0.45 2g . LH2/3 (H/B)2/3", "optc": "0.45 2g . LH3/2 (H/B)1/6", "optd": "0.45 2g . LH1/6 (H/B)3/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If q is the discharge per unit width of a channel and D1 D2 are the depths of water before and after hydraulic jump, the following relationship is true", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A river training work is generally required when the river is", "opta": "meandering", "optb": "aggrading", "optc": "degrading", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For loss of head in a canal inverted syphon barrel, the factor in the Unwin formula  is a coefficient for loss of head due to", "opta": "friction", "optb": "exit", "optc": "entry", "optd": "gradient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "If the flexibility is more than one, the outlet is hyper-proportional", "optb": "If the setting of an outlet is higher than that required for proportionality, the outlet is hyper-proportional", "optc": "If the setting of an outlet is lower than that required for proportionality, the outlet is sub-proportional", "optd": "If the flexibility is zero, it is a rigid module", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Duty of canal water is defined as the total area irrigated by the discharge averaging one unit during the base period of the duty", "optb": "Duty of canal water is usually calculated at the head discharge of a channel", "optc": "Duty of canal water at the head of a channel and at the outlet of a distributary, differ considerably due to progressive losses of water", "optd": "Duty of canal water at the outlet of a distributary, is generally known as outlet factor or outlet discharge factor", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water-shed line is abondened for aligning an irrigation canal if", "opta": "water shed forms a sharp loop", "optb": "canal has to take off from a river", "optc": "towns and villages are located on the water shed line", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following", "opta": "A bank in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the right", "optb": "A bank in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the left", "optc": "A 'dowla' in the cross-section of a canal is provided on the left", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a given discharge in a channel, Blench curves give the relationship between the loss of head (HL) and", "opta": "specific energy up-stream", "optb": "specific energy down-stream", "optc": "critical depth of water down-stream", "optd": "depth of water down-stream", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mr. W. Simms, the consulting Engineer to the Government of India recommended the gauge for Indian railways", "opta": "1.435 m as adopted in England", "optb": "1.800 m as per Indian conditions", "optc": "1.676 m as a compromise gauge", "optd": "1.000 m as a standard gauge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If absolute levels of rails at the consecutive axles A, B, and C separated by 1.8 metres are 100.505 m, 100.530 m, and 100.525 m respectively, the unevenness of rails, is", "opta": "0.065 m", "optb": "0.055 m", "optc": "0.045 m", "optd": "0.035 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A CST-9 sleeper consists of", "opta": "two inverted triangular pots on either side of rail seat", "optb": "a central plate with a projected key and box on the top of plate", "optc": "a tie bar and 4 cotters to connect two cast iron plates", "optd": "a single two way key provided on the gauge side to hold the rail to sleeper", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Charles Vignoles invented the flat footed rails in", "opta": "1814", "optb": "1836", "optc": "1846", "optd": "1856", "opte": "1873", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To design a cross-over between parallel tracks, the required components are :", "opta": "two switch, points, two acute angle crossings and two check rails", "optb": "two switch points, two acute angle crossings and four check rails", "optc": "two switch points, two acute angle crossings and six check rails", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The first Indian railway was laid in", "opta": "1775", "optb": "1804", "optc": "1825", "optd": "1853", "opte": "1876", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight of the rails depends upon", "opta": "gauge of the tracks", "optb": "speed of trains", "optc": "spacing of sleepers", "optd": "nature of traffic", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Rails are directly laid over hard wooden sleepers and fixed with spikes", "optb": "Adzing is done on hard wooden sleepers", "optc": "Bearing plates are used on soft wooden sleepers", "optd": "Chairs are used for bull headed rails", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "Fish plates fit the underside of the rail head", "optb": "Fish plates fit the top of the rail foot", "optc": "Fish plates fit the web of the rail section", "optd": "Cross sectional area of fish plates, is normally the same as that of the rail section.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Minimum depth of ballast prescribed of B.G. trunk lines of Indian Railways, is", "opta": "20 cm", "optb": "15 cm", "optc": "25 cm", "optd": "30 cm", "opte": "35 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Boxing of ballast is done", "opta": "under rails", "optb": "at the rails", "optc": "in between two rails", "optd": "in between two sleepers.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Best ballast contains stones varying in size from", "opta": "1.5 cm to 3 cm", "optb": "2.0 cm to 4 cm", "optc": "2.0 cm to 5 cm", "optd": "2.5 cm to 6 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For holding a rail in position, no chairs are used for", "opta": "flat footed rails", "optb": "bull headed rails", "optc": "double headed rails", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Distance between the inner rail and check rail provided on sharp curve, is", "opta": "40 mm", "optb": "42 mm", "optc": "44 mm", "optd": "46 mm", "opte": "50 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coal ash (or cinder) is used in initial stages of a new construction of railway for", "opta": "wooden sleepers", "optb": "steel sleepers", "optc": "cast iron sleepers", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pot sleepers are in the form of", "opta": "a number of bowls connected together with a tie bar", "optb": "two bowls placed under each rail and connected together with a tie bar", "optc": "two bowls placed under two rails and the one between the rails", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In railways a triangle is mainly provided for", "opta": "diverting trains from the main line to branch line", "optb": "crossing over between parallel tracks", "optc": "changing direction of engines through 180\u00b0", "optd": "shunting wagons in yards.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A kink is made in stock rails, ahead of the toe of switch at a distance of", "opta": "10 cm", "optb": "15 cm", "optc": "20 cm", "optd": "30 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If L is length of a rail and R is the radius of a curve, the versine h for the curve, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rails are bent to correct curvature if the degree of curve, is more than", "opta": "1\u00b0", "optb": "2\u00b0", "optc": "3\u00b0", "optd": "4\u00b0", "opte": "6\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India the rails are manufactured by", "opta": "open hearth process", "optb": "duplex process", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rail section first designed on Indian railways, was", "opta": "double headed", "optb": "bull headed", "optc": "flat footed", "optd": "(a) and (b) simultaneously", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A scissors cross-over consists of", "opta": "two pairs of points, four acute angle crossings and two obtuse angle crossings", "optb": "four pairs of points, four acute angle crossings and four obtuse angle crossings", "optc": "four pairs of points, six acute angle crossings and two obtuse angle crossings", "optd": "two pairs of points, six acute angle crossings and four obtuse angle crossings.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To prevent percolation of water into formation, moorum is used as a blanket for", "opta": "black cotton soil", "optb": "sandy soil", "optc": "clayey soil", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Distance between inner faces of the flanges, is kept", "opta": "equal to the gauge distance", "optb": "slightly less than the gauge distance", "optc": "slightly more than the gauge distance", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wooden sleepers used on the girders of bridges, are generally made of", "opta": "sal", "optb": "chir", "optc": "teak", "optd": "deodar.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If L1 and L2 are actual and theoretical lengths of a tongue rail, d is heel divergence and t is thickness of tongue rail at toe, the switch angle \u03b1 is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is distance between centres of two parallel track of gauge G, then, total length of cross-over (from the point of commencement to the point of termination) with an intermediate straight portion and N crossing, is given by", "opta": "DN + G (N + 1 + N2)", "optb": "DN + G (2N + 1 + N2)", "optc": "DN + G (3N + 1 + N2)", "optd": "DN + G (4N + l +N2)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a 0.7% upgrade meets a 0.65% downgrade at a summit and the permissible rate of change of grade per chain length is 0.10%, the length of the vertical curve, is", "opta": "10 chains", "optb": "12 chains", "optc": "14 chains", "optd": "16 chains", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Overall depth of a dog spike, is", "opta": "120.6 mm", "optb": "155.90 mm", "optc": "135 mm", "optd": "150 mm", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Best wood for wooden sleepers is", "opta": "chir", "optb": "deodar", "optc": "sal", "optd": "teak", "opte": "shesham.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rail section which is not used on Indian metre gauge tracks, is", "opta": "25 R", "optb": "30 R", "optc": "35 R", "optd": "40 R", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimensions of a plate girder, are :", "opta": "851 mm x 851 mm", "optb": "255 mm x 254 mm", "optc": "851 mm x 254 mm", "optd": "551 mm x 254 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rail joint supported on a single sleeper, is known", "opta": "suspended rail joint", "optb": "bridge rail joint", "optc": "supported rail joint", "optd": "square rail joint.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum wheel base distance provided on Indian B.G. tracks, is", "opta": "4.096 m", "optb": "5.096 m", "optc": "6.096 m", "optd": "7.096 m", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tread of wheels is provided an outward slope of", "opta": "1 in 10", "optb": "1 in 15", "optc": "1 in 20", "optd": "1 in 25", "opte": "1 in 30", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On a straight railway track, absolute levels at point A on two rails are 100.550 m and 100.530 m and the absolute levels at point B 100 m apart are 100.585 m and 100.515 m respectively, the value of twist of rails per metre run, is", "opta": "0.4 mm", "optb": "0.5 mm", "optc": "0.7 mm", "optd": "0.8 mm", "opte": "1.0 mm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bearing plates are used to fix", "opta": "flat footed rails to the wooden sleepers", "optb": "double headed rails to the wooden sleepers", "optc": "bull headed rails to the wooden sleepers", "optd": "flat footed rails to the cast iron sleepers", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A welded rail joint is generally", "opta": "supported on a sleeper", "optb": "supported on a metal plate", "optc": "suspended", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Safe speed (V) on a curve of radius 970 metres provided with two transition curves on Board Gauge track, is", "opta": "112 km/hour", "optb": "122 km/hour", "optc": "132 km/hour", "optd": "142 km/hour", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "Sleepers hold the rails at proper gauge on straights", "optb": "Sleepers provide stability to the permanent way", "optc": "Sleepers act as an elastic cushion between rails and ballast", "optd": "Sleepers transfer load of moving trains to ballast", "opte": "None of the these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b1 is switch angle and R is radius of the turnout, the length of the tongue rail, is", "opta": "R sin \u03b1", "optb": "R tan \u03b1", "optc": "R sin \u03b1/2", "optd": "R tan \u03b1/2", "opte": "R cos \u03b1/2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quantity of stone ballast required per metre tangent length, is", "opta": "1.15 m3", "optb": "1.14 m3", "optc": "1.13 m3", "optd": "1.12 m3", "opte": "1.11 m3", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of switch generally used for B.G. and M.G. tracks, is", "opta": "articulated", "optb": "undercut", "optc": "over riding", "optd": "straight cut.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference in the lengths of two diagonals of a rail diamond is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For flat bottom sleepers, maximum size of ballast, is", "opta": "50 mm", "optb": "40 mm", "optc": "33 mm", "optd": "25 mm", "opte": "20 mm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coning of wheels", "opta": "prevent lateral movement of wheels", "optb": "provide smooth running of trains", "optc": "avoid excessive wear of inner faces of rail", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sleepers which satisfy the requirements of an ideal sleeper, are", "opta": "cast iron sleepers", "optb": "R.C.C. sleepers", "optc": "steel sleepers", "optd": "wooden sleepers.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Arrangement made to divert the trains from one track to another, is known as", "opta": "railway point", "optb": "railway crossing", "optc": "turnout", "optd": "railway junction", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At a rail joint, the ends of adjoining rails, are connected with a pair of fish plates and", "opta": "2 fish bolts", "optb": "4 fish bolts", "optc": "6 fish bolts", "optd": "8 fish bolts", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a combined footing if shear stress exceeds 5 kg/cm2, the nominal stirrups provided are:", "opta": "6 legged", "optb": "8 legged", "optc": "10 legged", "optd": "12 legged", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum area of tension reinforcement in beams shall not exceed", "opta": "0.15%", "optb": "1.5%", "optc": "4%", "optd": "1%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As per I.S. 456 - 1978, the pH value of water shall be", "opta": "less than 6", "optb": "equal to 6", "optc": "not less than 6", "optd": "equal to 7", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum number of main steel bars provided in R.C.C.", "opta": "rectangular columns is 4", "optb": "circular columns is 6", "optc": "octagonal columns is 8", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Post tensioning system", "opta": "was widely used in earlier days", "optb": "is not economical and hence not generally used", "optc": "is economical for large spans and is adopted now a days", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An R.C.C. column is treated as long if its slenderness ratio is greater than", "opta": "30", "optb": "35", "optc": "40", "optd": "50", "opte": "60", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The width of the flange of a T-beam should be less than", "opta": "one-third of the effective span of the T-beam", "optb": "distance between the centres of T-beam", "optc": "breadth of the rib plus twelve times the thickness of the slab", "optd": "least of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A prestressed rectangular beam which carries two concentrated loads W at L/3 from either end, is provided with a bent tendon with tension P such that central one-third portion of the tendon remains parallel to the longitudinal axis, the maximum dip h is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "A pile is a slender member which transfers the load through its lower end on a strong strata", "optb": "A pile is a slender member which transfers its load to the surrounding soil", "optc": "A pile is a slender member which transfers its load by friction", "optd": "A pile is a cylindrical body of concrete which transfers the load at a depth greater than its width.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cantilever retaining walls can safely be used for a height not more than", "opta": "3 m", "optb": "4 m", "optc": "5 m", "optd": "6 m", "opte": "8 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If W is the load on a circular slab of radius R, the maximum circumferential moment at the centre of the slab, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "zero", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a bent tendon is required to balance a concentrated load W at the centre of the span L, the central dip h must be at least", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For M 150 mix concrete, according to I.S. specifications, local bond stress, is", "opta": "5 kg/cm2", "optb": "10 kg/cm2", "optc": "15 kg/cm2", "optd": "20 kg/cm2", "opte": "25 kg/cm2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the average bending stress is 6 kg/cm2 for M 150 grade concrete, the length of embedment of a bar of diameter d according to I.S. 456 specifications, is", "opta": "28 d", "optb": "38 d", "optc": "48 d", "optd": "58 d", "opte": "95 d", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bottom bars under the columns are extended into the interior of the footing slab to a distance greater than", "opta": "42 diameters from the centre of the column", "optb": "42 diameters from the inner edge of the column", "optc": "42 diameters from the outer edge of the column", "optd": "24 diameter from the centre of the column", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter of longitudinal bars of a column should never be less than", "opta": "6 mm", "optb": "8 mm", "optc": "10 mm", "optd": "12 mm", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The design of a retaining wall assumes that the retained earth", "opta": "is dry", "optb": "is free from moisture", "optc": "is not cohesives", "optd": "consists of granular particles", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimensions of a beam need be changed if the shear stress is more than", "opta": "10 kg/cm2", "optb": "15 kg/cm2", "optc": "20 kg/cm2", "optd": "25 kg/cm2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness of base slab of a retaining wall generally provided, is", "opta": "one half of the width of the stem at the bottom", "optb": "one-third of the width of the stem at the bottom", "optc": "one fourth of the width of the steam at the bottom", "optd": "width of the stem at the bottom", "opte": "twice the width of the steam at the bottom.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a circular slab carrying a uniformly distributed load, the ratio of the maximum negative to maximum positive radial moment, is", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thickened part of a flat slab over its supporting column, is technically known as", "opta": "drop panel", "optb": "capital", "optc": "column head", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An R.C.C. beam not provided with shear reinforcement may develop cracks in its bottom inclined roughly to the horizontal at", "opta": "25\u00b0", "optb": "35\u00b0", "optc": "45\u00b0", "optd": "55\u00b0", "opte": "60\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective span of a simply supported slab, is", "opta": "distance between the centres of the bearings", "optb": "clear distance between the inner faces of the walls plus twice the thickness of the wall", "optc": "clear span plus effective depth of the slab", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "In the stem of a retaining wall, reinforcement is provided near the earth side", "optb": "In the toe slab of a retaining wall, rein forcement is provided at the bottom of the slab", "optc": "In the heel slab of a retaining wall, rein forcement is provided at the top of the slab", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum cube strength of concrete used for a prestressed member, is", "opta": "50 kg/cm2", "optb": "150 kg/cm2", "optc": "250 kg/cm2", "optd": "350 kg/cm2", "opte": "400 kg/cm2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of treads in a flight is equal to", "opta": "risers in the flight", "optb": "risers plus one", "optc": "risers minus one", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A short column 20 cm x 20 cm in section is reinforced with 4 bars whose area of cross section is 20 sq. cm. If permissible compressive stresses in concrete and steel are 40 kg/cm2 and 300 kg/cm2, the Safe load on the column, should not exceed", "opta": "4120 kg", "optb": "41, 200 kg", "optc": "412, 000 kg", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reinforced concrete beam which has width 25 cm, lever arm 40 cm, shear force 6t/cm2, safe shear stress 5 kg/cm2 and B.M. 24 mt,", "opta": "is safe in shear", "optb": "is unsafe in shear", "optc": "is over safe in shear", "optd": "needs redesigning.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a beam the local bond stress Sb, is equal to", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.S. : 456 specifications, the safe diagonal tensile stress for M 150 grade concrete, is", "opta": "5 kg/cm2", "optb": "10 kg/cm2", "optc": "15 kg/cm2", "optd": "20 kg/cm2", "opte": "25 kg/cm2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A foundation rests on", "opta": "base of the foundation", "optb": "subgrade", "optc": "foundation soil", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For initial estimate for a beam design, the width is assumed", "opta": "1/15th of span", "optb": "1/20th of span", "optc": "1/25th of span", "optd": "1/30th of span", "opte": "1/40th of span.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If R and T are rise and tread of a stair spanning horizontally, the steps are supported by a wall on one side and by a stringer beam on the other side, the steps are designed as beams of width", "opta": "R + T", "optb": "T-R", "optc": "R2 + T2", "optd": "R-T", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The advantage of a concrete pile over a timber pile, is", "opta": "no decay due to termites", "optb": "no restriction on length", "optc": "higher bearing capacity", "optd": "not necessary to cut below the water mark", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the permissible compressive stress for a concrete in bending is C kg/m2, the modular ratio is", "opta": "2800/C", "optb": "2300/2C", "optc": "2800/3C", "optd": "2800/C2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If d and n are the effective depth and depth of the neutral axis respectively of a singly reinforced beam, the lever arm of the beam, is", "opta": "d", "optb": "n", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To have pressure wholly compressive under the base of a retaining wall of width b, the resultant of the weight of the wall and the pressure exerted by the retained, earth should have eccentricity not more than", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The width of the flange of a T-beam, which may be considered to act effectively with the rib depends upon", "opta": "breadth of the rib", "optb": "overall thickness of the rib", "optc": "centre to centre distance between T-beams", "optd": "span of the T-beam", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Design of a two way slab simply supported on edges and having no provision to prevent the corners from lifting, is made by", "opta": "Rankine formula", "optb": "Marcus formula", "optc": "Rankine Grashoff formula", "optd": "Grashoff formula", "opte": "Rankine-Marcus formula.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Design of R.C.C. simply supported beams carrying U.D.L. is based on the resultant B.M. at", "opta": "supports", "optb": "mid span", "optc": "every section", "optd": "quarter span.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transverse reinforcements provided at right angles to the main reinforcement", "opta": "distribute the load", "optb": "resist the temperature stresses", "optc": "resist the shrinkage stress", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of reinformcement for main bars in a slab, is based upon", "opta": "minimum bending moment", "optb": "maximum bending moment", "optc": "maximum shear force", "optd": "minimum shear force.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the effective length of a 32 cm diameter R.C.C. column is 4.40 m, its slenderness ratio, is", "opta": "40", "optb": "45", "optc": "50", "optd": "55", "opte": "60", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The percentage of minimum reinforcement of the gross sectional area in slabs, is", "opta": "0.10%", "optb": "0.12%", "optc": "0.15%", "optd": "0.18%", "opte": "0.20%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A continuous beam shall be deemed to be a deep beam if the ratio of effective span to overall depth, is", "opta": "2.5", "optb": "2.0", "optc": "less than 2", "optd": "less than 2.5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If T and R are tread and rise respectively of a stair, then", "opta": "2R + T = 60", "optb": "R + 2T = 60", "optc": "2R + T = 30", "optd": "R + 2T= 30", "opte": "3R + 27 = 30", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If k is wobble correction factor, \u03bc is coefficient of friction between the duct surface and the curve of tendon of radius R, the tension ratio at a distance x from either end, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a prestressed beam carrying an external load W with a bent tendon is having angle of inclination \u03b8 and prestressed load P. The net downward load at the centre is", "opta": "W - 2P cos \u03b8", "optb": "W - P cos \u03b8", "optc": "W - P sin \u03b8", "optd": "W - 2P sin \u03b8", "opte": "W + 2P sin \u03b8", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective width of a column strip of a flat slab, is", "opta": "one-fourth the width of the panel", "optb": "half the width of the panel", "optc": "radius of the column", "optd": "diameter of the column", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High strength concrete is used in prestressed member", "opta": "to overcome high bearing stresses developed at the ends", "optb": "to ovecome bursting stresses at the ends", "optc": "to provide high bond stresses", "optd": "to overcome cracks due to shrinkage", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "1 kg wt in gravitational unit equals", "opta": "8.9 N in SI system", "optb": "9.8 N in SI system", "optc": "4.5 N in SI system", "optd": "5.4 N in SI system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To convert the units of M.K.S. to units of S.I., a factor 9.80665 is used for", "opta": "mass", "optb": "force", "optc": "work energy", "optd": "power", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SI unit for the surface tension, is", "opta": "kg/m3", "optb": "kg/m2", "optc": "kg/m", "optd": "N/m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The basic quantity in the International system of units, is", "opta": "length and mass", "optb": "time and temperature", "optc": "mole and light intensity", "optd": "electric current", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intensity of electric current is expressed in", "opta": "volts", "optb": "watts", "optc": "amperes", "optd": "joules.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Netwon force equals", "opta": "105 dynes", "optb": "104 dynes", "optc": "103 dynes", "optd": "102 dynes", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In S.I. system, the symbol for density is", "opta": "N/m3", "optb": "kg/m3", "optc": "m3/s", "optd": "kg", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "1 N force = 0.10197 kgf", "optb": "1 kgf = 9.80665 N", "optc": "1 kgf/cm2 = 98.0665 kN/m2", "optd": "1 atm = 101.325 kN/m2", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness of a micron, is", "opta": "10-3 m", "optb": "10-6 m", "optc": "10-9 m", "optd": "10-12 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fundamental units in S.I. system, are the same as that of", "opta": "C.G.S. units", "optb": "F.P.S. units", "optc": "M.K.S. units", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In S.I. system, pressure is expressed in N/m2", "optb": "In S.I. system, surface tension is expressed in Newton per metre", "optc": "In S.I. system, force is expressed in Newtons", "optd": "In S.I. system, power is expressed in watts", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "100 kN/m2 pressure is equal to", "opta": "1 atm", "optb": "1 bar", "optc": "1 m bar", "optd": "1 mm Hg", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The solid angles are measured in", "opta": "degrees", "optb": "grades", "optc": "radians", "optd": "steradians.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "10-12, is called", "opta": "Terra", "optb": "pico", "optc": "Giga", "optd": "Mega", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The units of moment of inertia of a plane area, depends upon the units of the area and the length", "optb": "The moment of inertia is expressed in m4 if the area is in square metres and the length is also in metres", "optc": "The moment of inertia is expressed in cm4 if the area is in square centimetres and the length in centimetres", "optd": "The moment of inertia is expressed in mm4 if the area is in square millimetres and the length in millimetres", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The intensity of pressure at a certain place is 1 kg (f)/m2, the intensity of pressur e in SI units will be", "opta": "47.88 N/m2", "optb": "9.81 N/m2", "optc": "4.882 N/m2", "optd": "0.07013 N/m2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b1 is the angular acceleration of a body of moment of inertia I, the torque is", "opta": "I2 \u03b1", "optb": "I \u03b1", "optc": "I/\u03b1", "optd": "I2/\u03b1", "opte": "I \u03b11/2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In SI units, moment is expressed as", "opta": "kg-m", "optb": "kg-cm", "optc": "kg-mm", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Angular acceleration is expressed as", "opta": "m/s2", "optb": "w/s2", "optc": "rad/s2", "optd": "rad/s", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Newton force produces an acceleration of", "opta": "1 cm/sec2 while acting on a body of 1 gm mass", "optb": "1 cm/sec2 while acting on a body of 1 kg mass", "optc": "1 m/sec2 while acting on a body of 1 kg mass", "optd": "1 m/sec2 while acting on a body of 1 gm mass.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hertz (Hz) is used to express", "opta": "Luminous intensity", "optb": "electric current intensity", "optc": "power", "optd": "frequency.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Candela (Cd) is used to express", "opta": "luminous intensity", "optb": "electric current intensity", "optc": "power", "optd": "frequency.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit kg/m3 is used for", "opta": "force", "optb": "density", "optc": "volume", "optd": "pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fundamental units in S.I. System are :", "opta": "Centimetre, gram, second", "optb": "Foot, pound, second", "optc": "Metre, kilogram, second", "optd": "Kilometre, kilogram, minute", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bar used for defining the standard metre at the International office of weights and measures at Sevres near Paris, is composed of", "opta": "50% platinum and 50% iridium", "optb": "60% platinum and 40% iridium", "optc": "70% platinum and 30% iridium", "optd": "80% platinum and 20% iridium", "opte": "90% platinum and 10% iridium", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "m2/s is used in S.I. system for", "opta": "Surface tension", "optb": "Kinematic viscosity", "optc": "Pressure", "optd": "Power.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The S.I. unit of Modulus of elasticity is", "opta": "Newton/m2", "optb": "Newton/cm2", "optc": "Newton/mm2", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Newton is equivalent to", "opta": "0.10197 kgf", "optb": "0.20197 kgf", "optc": "9.80665 kgf", "optd": "0.97125 kgf", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Joule or Newton metric is used for", "opta": "Work", "optb": "Torque", "optc": "Energy", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stress in SI units is expressed in", "opta": "kg per sq cm", "optb": "kg per sq mm", "optc": "Newton per sq mm", "optd": "Newton per sq cm", "opte": "Newton per sq m", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In S.I. system, symbol for the specific weight is", "opta": "kg/m3", "optb": "N/m3", "optc": "N/m2", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The SI unit of the force is", "opta": "Newton", "optb": "Kilogrames", "optc": "Joule", "optd": "Erg", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In SI system, the unit of temperature, is", "opta": "Degree centigrade", "optb": "Degree Celsius", "optc": "Kelvin", "optd": "Degree Fahrenheit.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "N-s/m2 is used in S.I. system for", "opta": "Kinematic viscosity", "optb": "Dynamic viscosity", "optc": "Mass density", "optd": "Weight density.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Basic unit of thermodynamic temperature, is", "opta": "degree fahrenheit", "optb": "degree centigrade", "optc": "degree kelvin", "optd": "degree absolute.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a liquid limit test, the moisture content at 10 blows was 70% and that at 100 blows was 20%. The liquid limit of the soil, is", "opta": "35%", "optb": "50%", "optc": "65%", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The active earth pressure of a soil is proportional to (where \u03c6 is the angle of friction of the soil)", "opta": "tan (45\u00b0 - \u03c6)", "optb": "tan2 (45\u00b0 + \u03c6/2)", "optc": "tan2 (45\u00b0 - \u03c6/2)", "optd": "tan (45\u00b0 + \u03c6)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum water content at which the soil just begins to crumble when rolled into threads 3 mm in diameter, is known", "opta": "liquid limit", "optb": "plastic limit", "optc": "shrinkage limit", "optd": "permeability limit.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The rise of the ground surface due to frost action is called frost heave.", "optb": "The freezing of water is accompained by a volume increase of 9%.", "optc": "Below freezing point, higher soil suction develops.", "optd": "The magnitude of frost heave decreases as the degree of saturation of soil decreases", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is true ?", "opta": "Clays are more porous than sands", "optb": "Pressure of organic matter in a soil decreases the bearing capacity of the soil", "optc": "Aluminous cement is used for foundations in soils with chemical deposits", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lateral earth pressure on a retaining wall", "opta": "is equal to mass of the soil retained", "optb": "proportional to the depth of the soil", "optc": "proportional to the square of the depth of the soil", "optd": "proportional to the internal friction of the soil", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The internal molecular attraction of a soil, the cohesion", "opta": "decreases as the moisture content increases", "optb": "increases as the moisture content decreases", "optc": "is more in well compacted clays", "optd": "depends upon the external applied load.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quantity of seepage of water through soils is proportional to", "opta": "coefficient of permeability of soil", "optb": "total head loss through the soil", "optc": "neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "both (a) and (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When drainage is permitted under initially applied normal stress only and full primarily consolidation is allowed to take place, the test is known as", "opta": "quick test", "optb": "drained test", "optc": "consolidated undrained test", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum water content at which the soil retains its liquid state and also possesses a small shearing strength against flowing, is known", "opta": "liquid limit", "optb": "plastic limit", "optc": "shrinkage limit", "optd": "permeability limit.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Minimum size of the particles of silt soil, is", "opta": "0.002 mm", "optb": "0.04 mm", "optc": "0.06 mm.", "optd": "0.08 mm", "opte": "1 mm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum value of effective stress in the past divided by the present value, is defined as over consolidation ratio (OCR). The O.C.R. of an over consolidated clay is", "opta": "less than 1", "optb": "1", "optc": "more than 1", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If Nf, Nd and H are total number flow channels, total number of potential drops and total hydraulic head differences respectively, the discharge q through the complete flow is given by (where K is a constant)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A flow line makes angles \u03b81 and \u03b82 with the normal to the interface of the soils having permeabilities k1, k2 before and after deflection. According to the law of deflection of the flow lines at the interface of the dissimilar soils", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Under-reamed piles are generally", "opta": "driven piles", "optb": "bored piles", "optc": "precast piles", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the clay soil group which does not swell when wet from the following :", "opta": "Kaolinite group", "optb": "Mite group", "optc": "Vermiculite group", "optd": "Montrorillonite group.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Factor of safety against sliding of a slope, is the ratio of", "opta": "actual cohesion to that required to maintain stability of slope", "optb": "shear strength to shear stress along the surface", "optc": "neither (a) nor (b)", "optd": "both (a) and (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the volume of voids to the volume of soil solids in a given soil mass, is known", "opta": "porosity", "optb": "specific gravity", "optc": "void ratio", "optd": "water content.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A compacted soil sample using 10% moisture content has a weight of 200 g and mass unit weight of 2.0 g/cm3. If the specific gravity of soil particles and water are 2.7 and 1.0, the degree of saturation of the soil is", "opta": "11.1%", "optb": "55.6%", "optc": "69.6%", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A partially saturated sample of soil has a unit weight of 2.0 g/cm3 and specific gravity of soil particles is 2.6. If the moisture content in the soil is 20%, the degree of saturation is", "opta": "20%", "optb": "77%", "optc": "92%", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Minimum depth of a footing carrying a heavy load, is calculated by the formula", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Coulomb's wedge theory, the active earth pressure slides the wedge", "opta": "down and outwards on a slip surface", "optb": "up and inwards on a slip surface", "optc": "horizontal upward and parallel to base", "optd": "horizontal inward and parallel to base.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of curvature is defined", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective size of particles of soil is denoted by", "opta": "D10", "optb": "D20", "optc": "D30", "optd": "D60", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Degree of saturation of a natural soil deposit having water content 15%, specific gravity 2.50 and void ratio 0.5, is", "opta": "50%", "optb": "60%", "optc": "75%", "optd": "80%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of compressibility of soil, is the ratio of", "opta": "stress to strain", "optb": "strain to stress", "optc": "stress to settlement", "optd": "rate of loading to that of settlement.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the failure of a finite slope occurs through the toe, it is known as", "opta": "slope failure", "optb": "face failure", "optc": "base failure", "optd": "toe failure.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rankine's theory of active earth pressure assumes", "opta": "soil mass is homogeneous, dry and cohesionless", "optb": "ground surface is a plane which may be horizontal or inclined", "optc": "back of the wall is vertical and smooth", "optd": "wall yields about the base", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The water content of soil is defined as the ratio of", "opta": "volume of water to volume of given soil", "optb": "volume of water to volume of voids in soil", "optc": "weight of water to weight of air in voids", "optd": "weight of water to weight of solids of given mass of soil.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Accurate determination of water content, is made by", "opta": "calcium carbide method", "optb": "sand bath method", "optc": "alcohol method", "optd": "oven-drying method.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stoke's law sates that the velocity at which a grain settles out of suspension, the other factors remaining constant, is dependent upon", "opta": "shape of grain", "optb": "weight of grain", "optc": "size of grain", "optd": "shape and size of grain", "opte": "shape, size and weight of grain.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "When water table is above the base of a footing, the dry weight m should be used for soil below water table", "optb": "When water table is located somewhat below the base of a footing, the elastic wedge is partly of moist soil and partly of submerged soil, and a suitable reduction factor is used", "optc": "When water table is just at the base of the footing, no reduction factor is used", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "In soils, the flow index indicates variation in shear strength with water content", "optb": "Liquid limit minus plastic limit, is known as plasticity index of the soil", "optc": "Plastic limit minus shrinkage limit, is known as shrinkage index of the soil", "optd": "The ratio of the plasticity index to the flow limit, is known as toughness index of the soil", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If S, L and R are the arc length, long chord and radius of the sliding circle then the perpendicular distance of the line of the resultant cohesive force, is given  by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The liquid limit and plastic limit exist in", "opta": "sandy soils", "optb": "silty soils", "optc": "gravel soils", "optd": "clay soils.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Back fill with a sloping surface exerts a total active pressure Pa on the wall of height H and acts at", "opta": "H/4 above the base parallel to base", "optb": "H/2 above the base parallel to base", "optc": "H/3 above the base parallel to base", "optd": "H/5 above the base parallel to base.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the weight of given volume of soil solids to the weight of an equal volume of distilled water at the given temperature, is known", "opta": "porosity", "optb": "specific gravity", "optc": "void ratio", "optd": "water content.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ultimate Settlement of a soil is directly proportional to:", "opta": "depth of the compressible soil strata", "optb": "compressive index", "optc": "void ratio", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The seepage force in a soil, is", "opta": "perpendicular to the equipotential lines", "optb": "proportional to the exit graident", "optc": "proportional to the head loss", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A soil has bulk density 2.30 g/cm3 and water content 15 per cent, the dry density of the sample, is", "opta": "1.0 g/cm2", "optb": "1.5 g/cm3", "optc": "2.0 g/cm3", "optd": "2.5 g/cm3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Sandy clayloam contains highest percentage of sand", "optb": "Silty clayloam contains highest percentage of silt", "optc": "Stiff boulder clay offers maximum shear strength", "optd": "Soft chalk carries least safe load", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The clay soil mainly consists of", "opta": "Kaolinites .", "optb": "Montomorillonite", "optc": "Illites", "optd": "Vermiculite", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The liquidity index is defined as a ratio expressed as percentage of", "opta": "plastic limit minus the natural water content, to its plasticity index", "optb": "natural water content minus its plastic limit to its plasticity index", "optc": "natural water content plus its plastic limit to its plasticity index", "optd": "liquid limit minus the natural water content to the plasticity index.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fluid generally used for grouting is", "opta": "cement and water mix", "optb": "clay suspension", "optc": "sodium silicate", "optd": "bitumen emulsion", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A coarse-grained soil has a voids ratio 0.75, and specific gravity as 2.75. The critical gradient at which quick sand condition occurs, is", "opta": "0.25", "optb": "0.50", "optc": "0.75", "optd": "1.00", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The relationship between void ratio (e) and porosity ratio (n) is :", "opta": "n =", "optb": "e =", "optc": "n =", "optd": "e = n/(1 - n)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Failure of the stability of slopes, generally occurs along", "opta": "slip plane", "optb": "a horizontal surface", "optc": "a curved surface", "optd": "all the surfaces.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Failure plane carries maximum shear stress", "optb": "Failure plane does not carry maximum shear stress", "optc": "Failure plane carries shear stress equal to maximum shear stress", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Geologic cycle for the formation of soil, is", "opta": "Upheavel \u2192 transportation \u2192 deposition \u2192 weathering", "optb": "Weathering \u2192 upheaval \u2192 transportation \u2192 deposition", "optc": "Transportation \u2192 upheaval \u2192 weathering \u2192 deposition", "optd": "Weathering \u2192 transportation \u2192 deposition \u2192 upheaval", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight of a pycnometer containing 400 g sand and water full to the top is 2150 g. The weight of pycnometer full of clean water is 1950 g. If specific gravity of the soil is 2.5, the water content is", "opta": "5%", "optb": "10%", "optc": "15%", "optd": "20%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective length of a compression member of length L held in position and restrained in direction at one end and effectively restrained in direction but not held in position at the other end, is", "opta": "L", "optb": "0.67 L", "optc": "0.85 L", "optd": "1.5 L", "opte": "2 L", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of shearing stress to shearing strain within elastic limit, is known as", "opta": "modulus of elasticity", "optb": "shear modulus of elasticity", "optc": "bulk modulus of elasticity", "optd": "tangent modulus of elasticity", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determination of allowable stress in axial compression, Indian Standard Institution has adopted", "opta": "Euler's formula", "optb": "Rankine formula", "optc": "Engesser formula", "optd": "Secant formula", "opte": "Perry Robertson formula.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The method of design of steel framework for greatest rigidity and economy in weight, is known as", "opta": "simply design", "optb": "semi-rigid design", "optc": "fully rigid design", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the pitch is 6 cm and rivet value is 4 tonnes, the number of rivets required for a riveted connection carrying an eccentric load of 15 tonnes at a distance of 30 cm from the centre line, is", "opta": "6", "optb": "8", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "opte": "15", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In plastic analysis, the shape factor for circular sections, is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "1.6", "optc": "1.697", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical stress on a column for elastic buckling given by Euler's formula, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A beam is defined as a structural member subjected to", "opta": "axial loading", "optb": "transverse loading", "optc": "axial and transverse loading", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to IS : 800 - 71, the minimum thickness of a vertically stiffened web plate, shall not be less than", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fillet weld may be termed as", "opta": "mitre weld", "optb": "concave weld", "optc": "convex weld", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the moment of inertia of a section about its axis is I and its effective sectional area is A, its radius of gyration r about the axis, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical load for a column of length I hinged at both ends and having flexural rigidity El, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Slenderness ratio of a compression member is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Vertical stiffeners may be placed in pairs one on each side of the web", "optb": "Single vertical stiffeners may be placed alternately on opposite sides of the web", "optc": "Horizontal stiffeners may be placed in pairs one on each side of the web", "optd": "Horizontal stiffeners may be placed alternately on opposite sides of the web", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A structural member subjected to compressive stress in a direction parallel to its longitudinal axis, is generally known as", "opta": "column", "optb": "stanchion", "optc": "post", "optd": "strut", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equivalent axial tensile load Pe, which produces an average axial tensile stress in the section equivalent to the combined stress due to axial tension P and bending M, at the extreme fibre of the section, is given by (where Z is the section modulus of the section).", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Live load", "opta": "varies in magnitude", "optb": "varies in position", "optc": "is expressed as uniformly distributed load", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most economical section for a column, is", "opta": "rectangular", "optb": "solid round", "optc": "flat strip", "optd": "tubular section", "opte": "hexagonal.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the depth of two column sections are equal, then the column splice is provided", "opta": "with filler plates", "optb": "with bearing plates", "optc": "with filler and hearing plates", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance between e.g. of compression and e.g. of tension flanges of a plate girder, is known as", "opta": "overall depth", "optb": "clear depth", "optc": "effective depth", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Web crippling generally occurs at the point where", "opta": "bending moment is maximum", "optb": "shearing force is minimum", "optc": "concentrated loads act", "optd": "deflection is maximum", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "The nominal diameter of a rivet is its diameter before driving", "optb": "The gross diameter of a rivet is the diameter of rivet hole", "optc": "The gross area of a rivet is the cross-sectional area of the rivet hole", "optd": "The diameter of a rivet hole is equal to the nominal diameter of the rivet plus 1.5 mm", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The allowable stress in axial tension for rolled I-sections and channels, is taken as", "opta": "1420 kg/cm2", "optb": "1500 kg/cm2", "optc": "2125 kg/cm2", "optd": "1810 kg/cm2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a tension member is made of four angles with a plate as a web, the allowance for holes is made as", "opta": "two holes for each angle and one hole for the web", "optb": "one hole for each angle and one hole for the web", "optc": "one hole for each angle and two holes for the web", "optd": "two holes for each angle and two holes for the web", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The failure of a web plate takes place by yielding if the ratio of the clear depth to thickness of the web, is less than", "opta": "45", "optb": "55", "optc": "60", "optd": "75", "opte": "82", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum edge distance of a rivet line connecting two or more plates, is kept equal to 37 mm plus (where t is the thickness in mm of the thinner outside plate).", "opta": "2 t", "optb": "4 t", "optc": "6 t", "optd": "8 t", "opte": "10 t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Dead load includes self-weight of the structure and super-imposed loads permanently attached to the structure", "optb": "Dead loads change their positions and vary in magnitude", "optc": "Dead loads are known in the beginning of the design", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum permissible slenderness ratio of a member carrying loads resulting from wind, is", "opta": "180", "optb": "200", "optc": "250", "optd": "300", "opte": "350", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If d is the distance between the flange angles, the vertical stiffeners in plate girders are spaced not greater than", "opta": "d", "optb": "1.25 d", "optc": "1.5 d", "optd": "1.75 d", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the unsupported length of a stanchion is 4 metres and least radius of gyration of its cross-section is 5, the slenderness ratio of the stanchion, is", "opta": "60", "optb": "70", "optc": "80", "optd": "90", "opte": "100", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The area Ap of cover plates in one flange of a built up beam, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The average shear stress for rolled steel beam section, is", "opta": "845 kg/cm2", "optb": "945 kg/cm2", "optc": "1025 kg/cm2", "optd": "1500 kg/cm2", "opte": "1875 kg/cm2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a rectangular section, the ratio of the maximum and average shear stresses, is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "2.0", "optc": "2.5", "optd": "3.0", "opte": "4.0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To keep the intensity of bearing pressure between the column base and concrete compressive and to vary from zero to , the ratio of the moment M to the axial load P should be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cross-section of a standard fillet is a triangle whose base angles are", "opta": "45\u00b0 and 45\u00b0", "optb": "30\u00b0 and 60\u00b0", "optc": "40\u00b0 and 50\u00b0", "optd": "20\u00b0 and 70\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Secant formula for direct stress in compression, is applicable only for slenderness ratio upto", "opta": "120", "optb": "130", "optc": "140", "optd": "150", "opte": "160", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A second horizontal stiffener is always placed at the neutral axis of the girder if the thickness of the web is less than", "opta": "d/250 for structural steel", "optb": "d/225 for high tensile steel", "optc": "both (c) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rolled steel I-sections are most commonly used as beams because these provide", "opta": "large moment of inertia with less cross-sectional area", "optb": "large moment of resistance as compared to other section", "optc": "greater lateral stability", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness t of a single flat lacing should not be less than", "opta": "1/30 th length between inner end rivets", "optb": "1/40 th length between inner end rivets", "optc": "1/50 th length between inner end rivets", "optd": "1/60 th length between inner end rivets", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the steel member exposed to weather and accessible for repainting, the thickness of steel should not be less than (excepting the webs of Indian Standard rolled steel joists and channels).", "opta": "4 mm", "optb": "6 mm", "optc": "8 mm", "optd": "10 mm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The permissible stress in bending for rolled steel I-beams and channels, is", "opta": "1500 kg/cm2", "optb": "1575 kg/cm2", "optc": "945 kg/cm2", "optd": "1650 kg/cm2", "opte": "1875 kg/cm2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Column footing is provided", "opta": "to spread the column load over a larger area", "optb": "to ensure that intensity of bearing pressure between the column footing and soil does not exceed permissible bearing capacity of the soil", "optc": "to distribute the column load over soil through the column footing", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "When the gauge distance is larger than the pitch, the failure of the section may occur in a zig-zag line", "optb": "When the gauge distance is smaller than the pitch, the failure of the section may occur in a straight right angle section through the centre of rivet holes", "optc": "When the gauge distance and pitch are both equal, the failure to the section becomes more likely as the diameter of the holes increases", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of longitudinal stress to strain within eiastic limit, is known as", "opta": "modulus of elasticity", "optb": "shear modulus of elasticity", "optc": "bulk modulus of elasticity", "optd": "tangent modulus of elasticity", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If flexural rigidity of a column whose length is L and the loaded end is free, is El, the critical load will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a column of height L fixed in position and direction both at its top and bottom, its effective length, is", "opta": "L", "optb": "L", "optc": "(1/2)*L", "optd": "2L", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a tension member if b is width of plate, t is thickness of plate, p is staggered pitch, g is gauge distance, n is number of rivet holes in zig-zag line, n is number of gauge spaces, d is gross diameter of rivets, then the net sectional area Anet of the plate, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Net sectional area of a tension member, is equal to its gross section area", "opta": "plus the area of the rivet holes", "optb": "divided by the area of rivet holes", "optc": "multiplied by the area of the rivet holes", "optd": "minus the area of the rivet holes", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance measured along one rivet line from the centre of a rivet to the centre of adjoining rivet on an adjacent parallel rivet line, is called", "opta": "pitch of rivet", "optb": "gauge distance of rivet", "optc": "staggered pitch", "optd": "all the above", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tongue plates are provided in a steel girder at", "opta": "the upper flange", "optb": "the lower flange", "optc": "the upper end of the web", "optd": "the lower end of the web", "opte": "the upper and lower ends of the web.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rectangular bar of width b and height h is being used as a cantilever. The loading is in a plane parallel to the side b. The section modulus is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As compared to uniaxial tension or compression, the strain energy stored in bending is only", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of strengths of solid to hollow shafts, both having outside diameter D and hollow having inside diameter D/2, in torsion, is", "opta": "1/4", "optb": "1/2", "optc": "1/16", "optd": "15/16", "opte": "3/8", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weakest section of a diamond riveting, is the section which passes through", "opta": "first row", "optb": "second row", "optc": "central raw", "optd": "one rivet hole of end row.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a loaded beam, the point of con-traflexture occurs at a section where", "opta": "bending moment is minimum", "optb": "bending moment is zero or changes sign", "optc": "bending moment is maximum", "optd": "shearing force is maximum", "opte": "shearing force is minimum.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of elongations of a conical bar due to its own weight and that of a prismatic bar of the same length, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A three-hinged arch is said to be :", "opta": "statically determinate structure", "optb": "statically indeterminate structure", "optc": "a bent beam", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deflection due to couple M at the free end of a cantilever length L is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shape of the bending moment diagram over the length of a beam, having no external load, is always", "opta": "linear", "optb": "parabolic", "optc": "cubical", "optd": "circular.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement", "opta": "The cross-sectional area of the welded member is effective", "optb": "A welded joint develops strength of its parent metal", "optc": "Welded joints provide rigidity", "optd": "Welded joints have better finish", "opte": "Welding takes more time than riveting.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A uniform girder simply supported at its ends is subjected to a uniformly distributed load over its entire length and is propped at the centre so as to neutralise the deflection. The net B.M. at the centre will be", "opta": "WL", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A beam of length L is pinned at both ends and is subjected to a concentrated bending couple of moment M at its centre. The maximum bending moment in the beam is", "opta": "M", "optb": "M/2", "optc": "M/3", "optd": "ML/2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If two forces acting at a joint are not along the straight line, then for the equilibrium of the joint", "opta": "one of the forces must be zero", "optb": "each force must be zero", "optc": "forces must be equal and of the same sign", "optd": "forces must be equal in magnitude but opposite in sign.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A closely coiled helical spring of radius R, contains n turns and is subjected to an axial load W. If the radius of the coil wire is r and modulus of rigidity of the coil material is C, the stress developed in the helical spring is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the shear force along a section of a beam is zero, the bending moment at the section is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "maximum", "optc": "minimum", "optd": "average of maximum-minimum", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the cantilever truss as shown in below figure, the horizontal component of the reaction at A, is", "opta": "30 tonnes", "optb": "60 tonnes", "optc": "90 tonnes", "optd": "120 tonnes", "opte": "150 tonnes.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of an eccentric loading on a bracket subjected to moment M, the tangential force developed in any rivet, at right angles to its radius vector r is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A simply supported beam of span L carries a concentrated load W at its mid-span. The maximum bending moment M is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the maximum deflections of a beam simply supported at its ends with an isolated central load and that of with a uniformly distributed load over its entire length, is", "opta": "1", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shape of the bending moment diagram over the length of a beam, carrying a uniformly distributed load is always", "opta": "linear", "optb": "parabolic", "optc": "cubical", "optd": "circular.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum number of rivets for the connection of a gusset plate, is", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A triangular section having base b, height h, is placed with its base horizontal. If the shear stress at a depth y from top is q, the maximum shear stress is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The slenderness ratio of a vertical column of a square cross-section of 2.5 cm sides and 300 cm length, is", "opta": "200", "optb": "240", "optc": "360", "optd": "416", "opte": "500", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If n is the ratio of internal and external diameters of a hollow shaft, the ratio of the weight of the hollow shaft and that of solid shaft of same strength, will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rectangular beam 20 cm wide is subjected to a maximum shearing force of 10, 000 kg, the corresponding maximum shearing stress being 30 kg/cm2. The depth of the beam is", "opta": "15 cm", "optb": "20 cm", "optc": "25 cm", "optd": "30 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum twisting moment a shaft can resist, is the product of the permissible shear stress and", "opta": "moment of inertia", "optb": "polar moment of inertia", "optc": "polar modulus", "optd": "modulus of rigidly.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a simply supported beam with a central load, the bending moment is", "opta": "least at the centre", "optb": "least at the supports", "optc": "maximum at the supports", "optd": "maximum at the centre.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a given material Young's modulus is 200 GN/m2 and modulus of rigidity is 80 GN/m2. The value of Poisson's ratio is", "opta": "0.15", "optb": "0.20", "optc": "0.25", "optd": "0.30", "opte": "0.40", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the moment of inertia of a circular plate and that of a square plate for equal depth, is", "opta": "less than one", "optb": "equal to one", "optc": "more than one", "optd": "equal to 3\u03c0/16", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "For circular plate, MI = \u03c0*d^4/64.\nFor square plate, MI = d^4/12.\nSo, Ratio = MI of circular plate/MI of square plate.\n= 3*\u03c0/16."}, {"question": "The force in member U2L2 of the truss shown in below figure, is", "opta": "10 T tension", "optb": "10 T compression", "optc": "zero", "optd": "15 T compression.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a shaft is rotating N revolutions per minute with an applied torque T kg-m, the horse power being transmitted by the shaft, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the width of a simply supported beam carrying an isolated load at its centre is doubled, the deflection of the beam at the centre is changed by", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1/8", "optc": "2", "optd": "8", "opte": "4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a simply supported beam of length L, the bending moment M is described as M = a (x - x3/L2), 0 \u2264 x < L; where a is a constant. The shear force will be zero at", "opta": "the supports", "optb": "x = L/2", "optc": "x = L/3", "optd": "x = L/3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deflection of any rectangular beam simply supported, is", "opta": "directly proportional to its weight", "optb": "inversely proportional to its width", "optc": "inversely proportional to the cube of its depth", "optd": "directly proportional to the cube of its length", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a rectangular beam measuring 10 x 18 x 400 cm carries a unformly distributed load such that the bending stress developed is 100 kg/cm2. The intensity of the load per metre length, is", "opta": "240 kg", "optb": "250 kg", "optc": "260 kg", "optd": "270 kg", "opte": "280 kg.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Influence lines are drawn for structures", "opta": "of any type", "optb": "statically determinate", "optc": "pin-jointed truss", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A shaft turning 150 r.p.m. is subjected to a torque of 150 kgm. Horse power transmitted by the shaft is", "opta": "\u03c0", "optb": "10 \u03c0", "optc": "\u03c02", "optd": "1/\u03c0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A simply supported beam carrying a uniformly distributed load over its whole span, is propped at the centre of the span so that the beam is held to the level of the end supports. The reaction of the prop will be", "opta": "half the distributed load", "optb": "3/8th the distributed load", "optc": "5/8th the distributed load", "optd": "distributed load.", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The range within which a load can be applied on a rectangular column, to avoid any tensile stress, is", "opta": "one-half of the base", "optb": "one-fifth of the base", "optc": "one-fourth of the base", "optd": "one-fifth of the base", "opte": "one sixth of the base on either side of centroid.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a beam, the neutral plane", "opta": "may be its centre", "optb": "passes through the C.G. of the area of cross-section", "optc": "does not change during deformation", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When loads are applied proportionately to a frame structure containing its members in one plane, the structure is called", "opta": "grid frame", "optb": "plane frame", "optc": "space frame", "optd": "truss frame.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shear stress at any section of a shaft is maximum", "opta": "at the centre of the section", "optb": "at a distance r/2 from the centre", "optc": "at the top of the surface", "optd": "at a distance 3/4 r from the centre", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The region of the cross-section of a column in which compressive load may be applied without producing any tensile stress, is known as the core of the cross-section. In circular columns the radius of the core, is", "opta": "one-half of the radius", "optb": "one-third of the radius", "optc": "one-quarter of the radius", "optd": "one-fifth of the radius", "opte": "one-sixth of the radius.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A beam is said to be of uniform strength, if", "opta": "B.M. is same throughout the beam", "optb": "deflection is same throughout the beam", "optc": "bending stress is same throughout the beam", "optd": "shear stress is same throughout the beam", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a tension test, the yield stress is 300 kg/cm2, in the octa hedral shear stress at the point is:", "opta": "100 2 kg/cm2", "optb": "150 2 kg/cm2", "optc": "200 2 kg/cm", "optd": "250 2 kg/cm2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radius of gyration of a rectangular section is not proportional to", "opta": "square root of the moment of inertia", "optb": "square root of the inverse of the area", "optc": "square root of the moment of inertia divided by area of the section", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reinforced concrete beam is assumed to be made of", "opta": "homogeneous material", "optb": "heterogeneous material", "optc": "isotropic material", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the rivets in adjacent rows are staggered and outermost row has only one rivet, the arrangement of the rivets, is called", "opta": "chain riveting", "optb": "zig-zag riveting", "optc": "diamond riveting", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy stored in a beam of length L subjected to a constant B.M. is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force in DB of the truss shown in below figure is", "opta": "3 W compression", "optb": "W tension", "optc": "2 W compression", "optd": "5 W tension", "opte": "4 W tension.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The area of the concrete in compression plus the area of reinforcement transferred on the basis of modular ratio, is called", "opta": "transferred section", "optb": "equivalent section", "optc": "cracked section", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is the overall thickness of the slab, the diameter of the reinforcing bars should not exceed", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The diameter of reinforcing bars shall not exceed one eighth of the total thickness of the slab."}, {"question": "The gap between web plates and flange plates for fillet welds should not be more than", "opta": "0.5 mm", "optb": "0.75 mm", "optc": "1.0 mm", "optd": "1.25 mm", "opte": "1.5 mm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A continuous beam shall be deemed to be a deep beam if the ratio of its effective span to overall depth, is", "opta": "2.0", "optb": "2.5", "optc": "less than 2", "optd": "less than 2.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depth 'd' of webs without horizontal stiffeners and consisting of tongue plates is taken lesser than the depth of the girder between the flanges less the sum of the depth of the tongue plates, and", "opta": "eight times the sum of the thickness of tongue plates", "optb": "six times the sum of the thickness of tongue plates", "optc": "four times the sum of the thickness of tongue plates", "optd": "None of the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For design of a column the eccentricity of loading shall be taken as the distance from the assumed point of application of the load to the centroid of the column, subject to a minimum of", "opta": "10 mm", "optb": "20 mm", "optc": "30 mm", "optd": "40 mm", "opte": "50 mm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If l is the effective span in metres and D is overall depth of the section in mm, the structure may be accepted after 24 hour load test, provided the maximum deflection in mm is less than", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The approximate value of torsion constant k for a box of depth d, width b, and having uniform thickness t, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the formula a + bk for the calculation of the net effective section of single angles in tension connected by one leg only, the value of k, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concrete is deemed not to comply with the strength requirements if the strength is less than the greater of", "opta": "characteristic strength minus 1.35 times the standard deviation", "optb": "0.8 times the characteristic strength", "optc": "the average strength of all the samples is less than the characteristic strength plus  times the standard deviation.", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum area of compression reinforcement in a beam of cross section B x D is limited to", "opta": "0.02 BD", "optb": "0.03 BD", "optc": "0.04 BD", "optd": "0.05 BD", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moist curing of the exposed surfaces of concrete is done at least for", "opta": "3 days", "optb": "5 days", "optc": "7 days", "optd": "14 days", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following:", "opta": "The gross section of the web of rolled I-beams is the depth of the beam multiplied by the web thickness", "optb": "The gross section of the web of channels is the depth of the web multiplied by its thickness", "optc": "The gross section of the web of plate girders is the depth of the web plate multiplied by its thinkness", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the ratio of effective span to overall depth of a simply supported beam is equal or greater than 1 but less than or equal to 2, the lever arm, is", "opta": "0.2 (l + 2D)", "optb": "0.3 (l + 3D)", "optc": "0.2 (l + 3D)", "optd": "0.3 (l + 2D)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the slenderness ratio of a column is more than 160, the compressive stress obtained by the secant formula is multiplied by a factor in which value of x is", "opta": "0.9", "optb": "1.1", "optc": "1.2", "optd": "1.5", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For battened struts, the effective length is increased by", "opta": "5%", "optb": "7.5%", "optc": "10%", "optd": "12.5%", "opte": "15%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum horizontal deflection of a column of actual length L, when subjected to lateral forces, may be upto", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The test strength of the sample is taken as the average of the strength of", "opta": "2 specimens", "optb": "3 specimens", "optc": "4 specimens", "optd": "5 specimens", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum deflection of a structure should not normally exceed lesser of the span/350 or", "opta": "10 mm", "optb": "15 mm", "optc": "20 mm", "optd": "25 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement regarding columns.", "opta": "The cross sectional area of longitudinal reinforcement, should not be less than 0.8% nor more than 4% of its gross sectional area", "optb": "The minimum of longitudinal bars provided in rectangular and circular columns are 4 and 6 respectively", "optc": "In helically reinforced column, the minimum number of longitudinal reinforcement should be six", "optd": "If the effective length of a column is less than three times its lateral dimension, it is generally called a pedestal", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For heavily reinforced concrete member, the nominal maximum size of the aggregates should be restricted to", "opta": "5 mm less than the minimum clear distance between the main bars", "optb": "5 mm less than the minimum cover to the reinforcement", "optc": "smaller of (a) and (b)", "optd": "greater of (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum pitch i.e.,  the distance between centres of rivet holes is not less than", "opta": "1.5 times the hole diameter", "optb": "2.0 times the hole diameter", "optc": "2.5 times the hole diameter", "optd": "3.0 times the hole diameter", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dispersion of load through the flange to web is considered as dispersed uniformly at an angle \u03b8\u00b0 is", "opta": "10\u00b0", "optb": "15\u00b0", "optc": "20\u00b0", "optd": "25\u00b0", "opte": "30\u00b0", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The grade of concrete generally not used in the reinforced concrete, is", "opta": "M 10", "optb": "M 15", "optc": "M 20", "optd": "M 40", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The outstand of stiffeners should be (where t is the thickness of flat).", "opta": "6 t", "optb": "8 t", "optc": "10 t", "optd": "12 t", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the plain reinforcing bars in compression, the permissible design bond stress in tension, is increased by", "opta": "10%", "optb": "15%", "optc": "20%", "optd": "25%", "opte": "30%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cover to the main reinforced may be reduced up to one third of the specified cover but not less than", "opta": "5 mm", "optb": "7 mm", "optc": "10 mm", "optd": "15 mm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum compressive strength on 15 cm cubes of M 20 grade concrete at 7 days, should be a minimum of", "opta": "7 N/mm2", "optb": "10 N/mm2", "optc": "15 N/mm2", "optd": "20 N/mm2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reduced level of third floor of a building near a column is 205.350 m. The reduced levels of the undersides of four beams supporting the fourth floor framing into the column mutually perpendicular are 208.350 m, 208.450 m, 208.500 m and 208.550 m. The supported length of the column is", "opta": "3.000 m", "optb": "3.100 m", "optc": "3.150 m", "optd": "3.200 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance between, rivet line and the nearest edge of a joint not exposed to weather, is taken (where t is thickness in mm of the thinner outside plate).", "opta": "6 t", "optb": "8 t", "optc": "10 t", "optd": "12 t", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct precaution while spilicing the reinforcing bars", "opta": "These are provided away from the sections of maximum stress", "optb": "These are staggered", "optc": "These are provided if the B.M. is more than 50% of M.R.", "optd": "Not more than half the bars are spliced at a section", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u0394 is the deviation of the individual test strength from the average of n samples, the standard deviation of concrete of the given grade is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The over all depth of a solid slab is 20 cm and effective depth is 15 cm. The horizontal distance between parallel main reinforcement should not be more than", "opta": "30 cm", "optb": "40 cm", "optc": "45 cm", "optd": "60 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of minimum compressive strength on 15 cm cubes prepared with the concrete of M 20 grade and M 40 grade, at 7 days should be at least", "opta": "1/3", "optb": "1/2", "optc": "3/2", "optd": "2.0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum compressive strength on 15 cm cubes of M 30 grade concrete at 7 days, should be a minimum of", "opta": "7 N/mm2", "optb": "10 N/mm2", "optc": "20 N/mm2", "optd": "30 N/mm2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The grade of plain concrete to be used in sea water or structures exposed to sea water, should be", "opta": "M lO", "optb": "M 15", "optc": "M 20", "optd": "M 30", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of continuous beams, the distance between the points of zero moment, may be obtained as (where l is the effective span).", "opta": "0.5 l", "optb": "0.6 l", "optc": "0.7 l", "optd": "0.8 l", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reinforcing bars in beams are not bundled in contact if the diameter of the bars, exceeds", "opta": "12 mm", "optb": "20 mm", "optc": "35 mm", "optd": "30 mm", "opte": "36 mm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the reinforced concrete member totally immersed in sea water, the normal cover provided for the reinforcing bars is further increased by", "opta": "10 mm", "optb": "20 mm", "optc": "30 mm", "optd": "40 mm", "opte": "50 mm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective and actual lengths of a cantilever are same if continuous at the support,", "opta": "unstrained against torsion at the support and free at the end", "optb": "with partial restraint against torsion of the support and free at the end", "optc": "restrained against torsion at the support and free at the end", "optd": "none of the these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of fbct in the formula  for calculating the thickness of a Rectangular base, according to IS : 800-1982, is", "opta": "1500 kg/cm2", "optb": "1650 kg/cm2", "optc": "1800kg/cm2", "optd": "1890 kg/cm2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The slenderness ratio of single angle discontinuous struts conmected by a single rivet or bolt, shall not exceed", "opta": "110", "optb": "130", "optc": "150", "optd": "180", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In adverse circumtances, the reinforced concrete member immersed in sea water or subjected to sea spray, the maximum permissible cover for the reinforcing bars, should not exceed", "opta": "40 mm", "optb": "50 mm", "optc": "60 mm", "optd": "70 mm", "opte": "75 mm", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a column is subjected to dead load and super imposed load only, the maximum ratio  should not be greater than", "opta": "180", "optb": "250", "optc": "350", "optd": "400", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the dimensions of a rectangular section of a short column are 15 cm x 20 cm, its unsupported length should be restricted to", "opta": "9.0 m", "optb": "10.0 m", "optc": "11.0 m", "optd": "12.0 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The designed transverse shear in lacing is assumed as", "opta": "2.5% of axial load", "optb": "3% of axial load", "optc": "3.5% of axial load", "optd": "4% of axial load.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the stability of a structural part, the weight or anchorage should be", "opta": "1.2 times the minimum overturning moment due to dead load", "optb": "1.4 times the minimum overturning moment due to dead load", "optc": "sum of (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The creep coefficient i.e. the ratio of ultimate creep and elastic strain after", "opta": "7 days is 2.2", "optb": "28 days is 1.6", "optc": "365 days is 1.1", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For rolled I-beams and channels, permissible tensile and compressive stresses does not exceed", "opta": "1400 kg/cm2", "optb": "1500 kg/cm2", "optc": "1650 kg/cm2", "optd": "1800 kg/cm2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In compression members, the lap length of a bar should not be less than", "opta": "12 \u03c6", "optb": "16 \u03c6", "optc": "20 \u03c6", "optd": "24 \u03c6", "opte": "30 \u03c6", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrographic surveys deal with the mapping of", "opta": "large water bodies", "optb": "heavenly bodies", "optc": "mountaineous region", "optd": "canal system", "opte": "movement of clouds.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If h is the difference in level between end points separated by l, then the slope correction is  . The second term may be neglected if the value of h in a 20 m distance is less than", "opta": "m", "optb": "1 m", "optc": "2 m", "optd": "3 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal vertical curve to join two gradients, is", "opta": "circular", "optb": "parabolic", "optc": "elliptical", "optd": "hyperbolic", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "the eyepiece plays no part in defining the line of sight", "optb": "the diaphragm plays no part in defining the line of sight", "optc": "the optical centre of the objective plays no part in defining the line of sight", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The intercept of a staff", "opta": "is maximum if the staff is held truly normal to the line of sight.", "optb": "is minimum if the staff is held truly normal to the line of sight.", "optc": "decreases if the staff is tilted away from normal", "optd": "increases if the staff is tilted towards normal.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radius of curvature of the arc of the bubble tube is generally kept", "opta": "10 m", "optb": "25 m", "optc": "50 m", "optd": "100 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If S is the length of a subchord and R is the radius of simple curve, the angle of deflection between its tangent and sub-chord, in minutes, is equal to", "opta": "573 S/R", "optb": "573 R/S", "optc": "171.9 S/R", "optd": "1718.9 R/S", "opte": "1718.9 S/R.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The real image of an object formed by the objective, must lie", "opta": "in the plane of cross hairs", "optb": "at the centre of the telescope", "optc": "at the optical centre of the eye-piece", "optd": "anywhere inside the telescope.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In chain surveying tie lines are primarily provided", "opta": "to check the accuracy of the survey", "optb": "to take offsets for detail survey", "optc": "to avoid long offsets from chain lines", "optd": "to increase the number of chain lines.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "the tangent screw enables to give small movement under conditions of smooth and positive control", "optb": "standing on the tripod is the levelling head or trib arch", "optc": "the levelling screws are used to tilt the instrument so that its rotation axis is truly vertical", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of the Lehmann's rules of plane tabling, is", "opta": "location of the instrument station is always distant from each of the three rays from the known points in proportion to their distances", "optb": "when looking in the direction of each of the given points, the instrument station will be on the right side of one and left side of the other ray", "optc": "when the instrument station is outside the circumscribing circle its location is always on the opposite side of the ray to the most distant point as the inter-section of the other two rays", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If f1 and f2 are the distances from the optical centre of a convex lens of focal length f to conjugate two points P1 and P2 respectively, the following relationship holds good", "opta": "f = f1 + f2", "optb": "f = (f1 + f2)", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The accuracy of measurement in chain surveying, does not depend upon", "opta": "length of the offset", "optb": "scale of the plotting", "optc": "importance of the features", "optd": "general layout of the chain lines.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If arithmetic sum of latitudes of a closed traverse is \u2211Lat and closing error in latitude is dx, the correction for a side whose latitude is l, as given by Transit Rule, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Closed contours of decreasing values towards their centre, represent", "opta": "a hill", "optb": "a depression", "optc": "a saddle or pass", "optd": "a river bed.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a 30 m chain diverges through a perpendicular distance d from its correct alignment, the error in length, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": ".", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diopter is the power of a lens having a focal length of", "opta": "25 cm", "optb": "50 cm", "optc": "75 cm", "optd": "100 cm", "opte": "125 cm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An imaginary line joining the points of equal elevation on the surface of the earth, represents", "opta": "contour surface", "optb": "contour gradient", "optc": "contour line", "optd": "level line", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The 'fix' of a plane table station with three known points, is bad if the plane table station lies", "opta": "in the great triangle", "optb": "outside the great triangle", "optc": "on the circumference of the circumscribing circle", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If R is the radius of the main curve, \u03b8 the angle of deflection, S the shift and L the length of the transition curve, then, total tangent length of the curve, is", "opta": "(R - S) tan \u03b8/2 - L/2", "optb": "(R + S) tan \u03b8/2 - L/2", "optc": "(R + S) tan \u03b8/2 + L/2", "optd": "(R - S) tan \u03b8/2 + L/2", "opte": "(R - S) cos \u03b8/2 + L/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In chain surveying field work is limited to", "opta": "linear measurements only", "optb": "angular measurements only", "optc": "both linear and angular measurements", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two concave lenses of 60 cm focal length are cemented on either side of a convex lens of 15 cm focal length. The focal length of the combination is", "opta": "10 cm", "optb": "20 cm", "optc": "30 cm", "optd": "40 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b8 is the vertical angle of an inclined sight, \u03b4 is the angle of tilt of the staff, the error", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of the tacheometric constants is additive, the other constant, is", "opta": "subtractive constant", "optb": "multiplying constant", "optc": "dividing constant", "optd": "indicative constant.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The limiting length of an offset does not depend upon", "opta": "accuracy of the work", "optb": "method of setting out perpendiculars", "optc": "scale of plotting", "optd": "indefinite features to be surveyed.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In quadrantal bearing system, back bearing of a line may be obtained from its forward bearing, by", "opta": "adding 180\u00b0, if the given bearing is less than 180\u00b0", "optb": "subtracting 180\u00b0, if the given bearing, is more than 180\u00b0", "optc": "changing the cardinal points, i.e. substituting N for S and E for W and vice-versa", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If L is the perimeter of a closed traverse, \u0394D is the closing error in departure, the correction for the departure of a traverse side of length l, according to Bowditch rule, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": ".", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "the theodolite in which telescope can be rotated in vertical plane is called a transmit", "optb": "when the vertical circle is to the left of the telescope during observation, it is called to be in left face", "optc": "when the vertical circle is to the right of the telescope during observation, it is called to be in right face", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the method of surveying in which field observations and plotting proceed simultaneously from the following", "opta": "chain surveying", "optb": "compass surveying", "optc": "plan table surveying", "optd": "tacheometric surveying.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While viewing through a level telescope and moving the eye slightly, a relative movement occurs between the image of the levelling staff and the cross hairs. The instrument is", "opta": "correctly focussed", "optb": "not correctly focussed", "optc": "said to have parallax", "optd": "free from parallax.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Accuracy of 'fix' by two point problem, is", "opta": "bad", "optb": "good", "optc": "not reliable", "optd": "unique.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A bearing of a line is also known as", "opta": "magnetic bearing", "optb": "true bearing", "optc": "azimuth", "optd": "reduced bearing", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "True meridians are generally preferred to magnetic meridians because", "opta": "these converge to a point", "optb": "these change due to change in time", "optc": "these remain constant.", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "the apparent error on reversal is twice the actual error", "optb": "the correction may be made equal to half the observed discrepancy.", "optc": "the good results may be obtained from a defective instrument by reversing and taking the mean of two erroneous results", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03b8 is the slope of the ground and l is the measured distance, the correction is", "opta": "2l sin2 \u03b8/2", "optb": "2l cos2 \u03b8/2", "optc": "2l tan2 \u03b8/2", "optd": "2l cot2 \u03b8/2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most reliable method of plotting a theodolite traverse, is", "opta": "by consecutive co-ordinates of each station", "optb": "by independent co-ordinates of each station", "optc": "by plotting included angles and scaling off each traverse leg", "optd": "by the tangent method of plotting.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of level between a point below the plane of sight and one above, is the sum of two staff readings and an error would be produced equal to", "opta": "the distance between the zero of gradient and the foot of the staff", "optb": "twice the distance between the zero of graduation and the foot of the staff", "optc": "thrice the distance between the zero of graduation and the foot of the staff", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Offsets are measured with an accuracy of 1 in 40. If the point on the paper from both sources of error (due to angular and measurement errors) is not to exceed 0.05 cm on a scale of 1 cm = 20 m, the maximum length of offset should be limited to", "opta": "14.14", "optb": "28.28 m", "optc": "200 m", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The probable error of the adjusted bearing at the middle is", "opta": "rn", "optb": "rn", "optc": "rn", "optd": "rn.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bearings of the lines AB and BC are 146\u00b0 30' and 68\u00b0 30'. The included angle ABC is", "opta": "102\u00b0", "optb": "78\u00b0", "optc": "45\u00b0", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a closed traverse the omitted measurements may be calculated", "opta": "length of one side only", "optb": "bearing of one side only", "optc": "both length and bearing of one side", "optd": "length or bearing of adjacent side", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The slope correction for a length of 30 m along a gradient of 1 in 20, is", "opta": "3.75 cm", "optb": "0.375 cm", "optc": "37.5 cm", "optd": "2.75 cm.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main principle of surveying is to work", "opta": "from part to the whole", "optb": "from whole to the part", "optc": "from higher level to the lower level", "optd": "from lower level to higher level.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the construction of highway (or railway)", "opta": "longitudinal sections are required", "optb": "cross sections are required", "optc": "both longitudinal and cross sections are required", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the radius of a simple curve is R, the length of the chord for calculating offsets by the method of chords produced, should not exceed.", "opta": "R/10", "optb": "R/15", "optc": "R/20", "optd": "R/25.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sensitiveness of a level tube decreases if", "opta": "radius of curvature of its inner surface is increased", "optb": "diameter of the tube is increased", "optc": "length of the vapour bubble is increased", "optd": "both viscosity and surface tension are increased.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For true difference in elevations between two points A and B, the level must be set up", "opta": "at any point between A and B", "optb": "at the exact mid point of A and B", "optc": "near the point A", "optd": "near the point B.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ABCD is a regular parallelogram plot of land whose angle BAD is 60\u00b0. If the bearing of the line AB is 30\u00b0, the bearing of CD, is", "opta": "90\u00b0", "optb": "120\u00b0", "optc": "210\u00b0", "optd": "270\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Keeping the instrument height as 1.5 m, length of staff 4 m, the slope of the ground as 1 in 10, the sight on the down-slope, must be less than", "opta": "30 m", "optb": "25 m", "optc": "20 m", "optd": "15 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Box sextant is used for the measurement of horizontal angles", "optb": "Cross staff is used for setting out right angles", "optc": "Gradiometer is used for setting out any required gradient", "optd": "Line ranger is used for locating intermediate stations on a survey line", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The assumption in the theory of bending of beams, is :", "opta": "material is homogeneous", "optb": "material is isotropic", "optc": "Young's modulus is same in tension as well as in compression", "optd": "each layer is independent to expand or to contract", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shape factor of standard rolled beam section varies from", "opta": "1.10 to 1.20", "optb": "1.20 to 1.30", "optc": "1.30 to 1.40", "optd": "1.40 to 1.50", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shear strain energy theory for the failure of a material at elastic limit, is due to", "opta": "Rankine", "optb": "Guest or Trecas", "optc": "St. Venant", "optd": "Haig", "opte": "Von Mises.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The point of contraflexure is the point where", "opta": "B.M. changes sign", "optb": "B.M. is maximum", "optc": "B.M. is minimum", "optd": "S.F. is zero.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The normal component of a force inclined through \u03b8\u00b0 is obtained by multiplying the force by", "opta": "sin \u03b8", "optb": "cos \u03b8", "optc": "tan \u03b8", "optd": "sin \u03b8 cos \u03b8", "opte": "sin2\u03b8", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material which obeys Hook's law, is subjected to direct stress \u03c30. At its elastic limit, the following statement is true,", "opta": "Strain is equal to", "optb": "Maximum shear stress =", "optc": "Strain energy =", "optd": "Shear strain energy =", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the truss shown in the given figure, the force in member BC is", "opta": "100 t compressive", "optb": "100 t tensile", "optc": "zero", "optd": "indeterminate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A concentrated load P is supported by the free end of a quadrantal ring AB whose end B is fixed. The ratio of the vertical to horizontal deflections of the end A, is", "opta": "\u03c0", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stress may be defined as", "opta": "force per unit length", "optb": "force per unit volume", "optc": "force per unit area", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Total strain energy theory for the failure of a material at elastic limit, is known", "opta": "Guest's or Trecas' theory", "optb": "St. Venant's theory", "optc": "Rankine's theory", "optd": "Haig's theory", "opte": "Von Mises's theory.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stress may be expressed in Newtons", "opta": "per millimetre square (N/mm2)", "optb": "per centimetre square (N/cm2)", "optc": "per metre square (N/m2)", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Principal planes are subjected to", "opta": "normal stresses only", "optb": "tangential stresses only", "optc": "normal stresses as well as tangential stresses", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In plastic analysis, the shape factor for a circular section, is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "1.6", "optc": "1.7", "optd": "1.75", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Keeping the depth d constant, the width of a cantilever of length l of uniform strength loaded with a uniformly distributed load w varies from zero at the free end and", "opta": "at the fixed end", "optb": "at the fixed end", "optc": "at the fixed end", "optd": "at the fixed end", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total strain energy of a beam of length L, having moment of inertia of its section I, when subjected to a bending moment M, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A load of 1960 N is raised at the end of a steel wire. The minimum diameter of the wire so that stress in the wire does not exceed 100 N/mm2 is :", "opta": "4.0 mm", "optb": "4.5 mm", "optc": "5.0 mm", "optd": "5.5 mm", "opte": "6.0 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force in BF of the truss shown in given figure, is", "opta": "4t tension", "optb": "4t compression", "optc": "4.5t tension", "optd": "4.5t compression", "opte": "zero.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radius of gyration of a section of area A and least moment of inertia I about the centroidal axis, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A simply supported beam carries varying load from zero at one end and w at the other end. If the length of the beam is a, the maximum bending moment will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In plastic analysis, the shape factor for rectangular section, is", "opta": "1.4", "optb": "1.5", "optc": "1.6", "optd": "1.7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a simply supported rectangular beam of span L and loaded with a central load W, the length of elasto-plastic zone of the plastic hinge, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Hoop strain of the walls of a cylinder due to liquid is", "optb": "Longitudinal strain in the walls of a cylinder due to liquid is", "optc": "Volumetric change in the cylinderdue to liquid is", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material may fail if", "opta": "maximum principal stress exceeds the direct stress \u03c30", "optb": "maximum strain exceeds", "optc": "maximum shear stress exceeds", "optd": "total strain energy exceeds", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A truss containing j joints and m members, will be a simple truss if", "opta": "m = 2j - 3", "optb": "j = 2m - 3", "optc": "m = 3j - 2", "optd": "j = 3m - 2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stiffness of the close coil helical spring is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If E, N, K and 1/m are modulus of elasticity, modulus of rigidity. Bulk modulus and Poisson ratio of the material, the following relationship holds good", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of maximum shear stress to average shear stress of a circular beam, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rolled steel joist is simply supported at its ends and carries a uniformly distributed load which causes a maximum deflection of 10 mm and slope at the ends of 0.002 radian. The length of the joist will be,", "opta": "10 m", "optb": "12 m", "optc": "14 m", "optd": "16 m", "opte": "18 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steel rod 1 metre long having square cross section is pulled under a tensile load of 8 tonnes. The extension in the rod was 1 mm only. If Esteel = 2 x 106 kg/cm2, the side of the rod, is", "opta": "1 cm", "optb": "1.5 cm", "optc": "2 cm", "optd": "2.5 cm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum deflection due to a uniformly distributed load w/unit length over entire span of a cantilever of length l and of flexural rigidly EI, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material is said to be perfectly elastic if", "opta": "it regains its original shape on removal of the load", "optb": "It regains its original shape partially on removal of the load", "optc": "it does not regain its original shape at all", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For calculating the allowable stress of long columns. The empirical formula , is known as", "opta": "Straight line formula", "optb": "Parabolic formula", "optc": "Perry's formula", "optd": "Rankine's formula.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Beams composed of more than one material, rigidly connected together so as to behave as one piece, are known as", "opta": "Compound beams", "optb": "Indeterminate beams", "optc": "Determinate beams", "optd": "Composite beams.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In a loaded beam, the moment at which the first yield occurs is called yield moment", "optb": "In a loaded beam, the moment at which the entire section of the beam becomes fully plastic, is called plastic moment", "optc": "In a fully plastic stage of the beam, the neutral axis divides the section in two sections of equal area", "optd": "The ratio of plastic moment to the yield moment, is called shape factor", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum magnitude of shear stress due to shear force F on a rectangular section of area A at the neutral axis, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two bars, one of steel and the other of copper having areas of cross-sections As and Ac, coefficient of expansion \u03b1s and \u03b1c and Young's Modulii Es and Es are rigidly connected together at the ends and subjected to temperature change of t\u00b0. If the length of the bars initially is L, the final extension \u03b4 of the two bars at t\u00b0 temperature is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tangential component of stress on an plane inclined \u03b8\u00b0 to the direction of the force, may be obtained by multiplying the normal stress by", "opta": "sin \u03b8", "optb": "cos \u03b8", "optc": "tan \u03b8", "optd": "sin \u03b8 cos \u03b8", "opte": "sin2\u03b8", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force in AD of the truss shown in given figure, is", "opta": "4.0t compression", "optb": "3.0t compression", "optc": "0.5t compression", "optd": "0.5t tension", "opte": "zero.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There are two hinged semicircular arches A, B and C of radii 5 m, 7.5 m and 10 m respectively and each carries a concentrated load W at their crowns. The horizontal thrust at their supports will be in the ratio of", "opta": "1 : 1 1/2 : 2", "optb": "2 : 1 1/2 : 1", "optc": "1 : 1 : 2", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A spring of mean radius 40 mm contains 8 action coils of steel (N = 80000 N/mm2), 4 mm in diameter. The clearance between the coils being 1 mm when unloaded, the minimum compressive load to remove the clearance, is", "opta": "25 N", "optb": "30 N", "optc": "35 N", "optd": "40 N", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A shaft is subjected to bending moment M and a torque T simultaneously. The ratio of the maximum bending stress to maximum shear stress developed in the shaft, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the deflections of the free end of a cantilever due to an isolated load at l/3rd and 2/3rd of the span, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If Q is load factor, S is shape factor and F is factor of safety in elastic design, the following:", "opta": "Q = S + F", "optb": "Q = S - F", "optc": "Q = F - S", "optd": "Q = S x F", "opte": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In plastic analysis, the shape factor for a triangular section, is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "1.34", "optc": "2.34", "optd": "2.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The point of intersection of the bending axis with the cross section of the beam, is called shear centre", "optb": "For I sections, the shear centre coincides with the centroid of the cross section of the beam", "optc": "For channels, the shear centre does not concide its centroid", "optd": "Bending loads should pass through the shear centre to avoid twisting", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The bending moment which when acting alone would produce the maximum stress equal to the major principal stress caused by combined bending and torsion, is called equivalent bending moment", "optb": "Mcg = (M M2 + r2) where letters carry their usual meanings", "optc": "Tcp = m2 + T2 where letters carry their usual meanings", "optd": "The torque which when acting alone would produce maximum shear stress equal to the maximum shear stress caused by the combined bending and torsion, is called equivalent torque", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03a3H and \u03a3V are the algebraic sums of the forces resolved horizontally and vertically respectively, and \u03a3M is the algebraic sum of the moments of forces about any point, for the equilibrium of the body acted upon", "opta": "\u03a3H = 0", "optb": "\u03a3V = 0", "optc": "\u03a3M = 0", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determining the support reactions at A and B of a three hinged arch, points B and C are joined and produced to intersect the load line at D and a line parallel to the load line through A at D'. Distances AD, DD' and AD' when measured were 4 cm, 3 cm and 5 cm respectively. The angle between the reactions at A and B is", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "45\u00b0", "optc": "60\u00b0", "optd": "90\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following : The torsional resistance of a shaft is directly proportional to", "opta": "modulus of rigidity", "optb": "angle of twist", "optc": "reciprocal of the length of the shaft", "optd": "moment of inertia of the shaft section.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct for heading and benching method of tunnelling ?", "opta": "Drilling and mucking can be done simultaneously", "optb": "Benching provides a plateform for working on heading", "optc": "Removal of muck from the heading is very easy", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of heights of the tunnels above rail tops of BG and MG tracks is kept", "opta": "0.30 m", "optb": "0.45 m", "optc": "0.60 m", "optd": "0.75 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of drift method of tunnelling, the drift may be excavated at", "opta": "the centre", "optb": "the bottom", "optc": "the top", "optd": "the side", "opte": "All of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A tunnel is found more advantageous as compared to the alternate routes because it:", "opta": "remains free from snow", "optb": "reduces the cost by reducing the route distance", "optc": "reduces the maintenance cost", "optd": "avoids interference with surface rights", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For B.G. single track railway, the height of the tunnel above top of rails should be", "opta": "5.5 m to 5.8 m", "optb": "5.8 m to 6.2 m", "optc": "6.7 m to 7.3 m", "optd": "7.3 m to 7.5 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement regarding drilling a tunnel from the following:", "opta": "Holes are drilled by pneumatically operated rock drills", "optb": "One drill is required for each 4 to 5 m2 force area", "optc": "The diameter of the bore hole at the deepest point should be 6 mm more than the diameter of the cartridge", "optd": "All of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For tunnels exceeding 300 m in length, the grade should be provided below", "opta": "50% of the ruling gradient", "optb": "60% of the ruling gradient", "optc": "75% of the ruling gradient", "optd": "80% of the ruling gradient.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The method of draining in the tunnels, is generally known as", "opta": "foredrainage", "optb": "dewatering", "optc": "permanent drainage", "optd": "All of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following during tunnel excavation,", "opta": "Oxygen should not be less than 19.5%", "optb": "Carbondioxide should not be more than 0.5%", "optc": "Hydrogen sulphide should not be more than 0.001%", "optd": "Carbon mono-oxide should not be more than 0.01%", "opte": "All of the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To attain the required shape of the tunnel section, we use :", "opta": "easers", "optb": "trimmers", "optc": "cut holes", "optd": "chisels.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most commonly adopted pattern of cut holes is :", "opta": "horizontal wedge cut", "optb": "pyramid cut", "optc": "fan cut", "optd": "V-cut", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following linings is suitable for shield driven tunnels particularly in the subaqueous regions :", "opta": "Brick lining", "optb": "stone lining", "optc": "timber line", "optd": "cast iron lining", "opte": "concrete lining.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of railways,", "opta": "a detour round the hill is preferred", "optb": "a open cut is preferred", "optc": "tunnelling is preferred", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following tunnels were constructed in different countries for different purposes : 1. Emperor Claudius built the first Roman tunnel2. The first highway tunnel was constructed in Hungary3. The first underground railway tunnel was constructed in Great Britain4. The first navigational tunnel was constructed in France.The correct chronological development of these tunnels is:", "opta": "4 1 3 2", "optb": "1 4 2 3", "optc": "2 3 1 4", "optd": "3 2 4 1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following operations are generally employed for tunnelling in hard rock. 1. Removing ground water, 2. Loading holes and firing the explosive3. Setting up and drilling4. Grouting and lining5. Removing muck6. Ventilation and removing explosion dustThe correct sequence is :", "opta": "3 2 6 5 1 4", "optb": "3 4 6 1 5 2", "optc": "4 1 2 3 6 5", "optd": "5 4 2 1 3 6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the mechanical ventilation method used for tunnels from the following:", "opta": "blowing fresh air by ducts to the face of tunnel", "optb": "exhausting foul air by ducts from the face of the tunnel and permitting fresh air through the tunnel", "optc": "blowing fresh air and exhausting foul air by ducts", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following methods of tunnelling does not require the use of time bearing :", "opta": "Linear plate method", "optb": "Shield method", "optc": "Compressed air method", "optd": "Mechanical tunneler i.e. mole method", "opte": "All the these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For highways, tunnelling is preferred to if the open cut exceeds :", "opta": "10 metres depth", "optb": "15 metres depth", "optc": "20 metres depth", "optd": "25 metres depth.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following operations are required for tunnelling in rocky terrain :1. Removing the foul gases2. Marking the tunnel profile3. Setting up and drilling4. Checking misfire5. MuckingThe correct sequence is :", "opta": "1 2 3 4 5", "optb": "2 3 5 4 1", "optc": "4 2 1 3 5", "optd": "2 3 1 4 5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The advantages of providing a pair of tunnels as compared to only one large highway tunnel is :", "opta": "economy in cost of construction", "optb": "avoidance of head on collisions", "optc": "provision of separate exit and entrance of two traffic streams", "optd": "facility in carrying out repairs", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct in respect of setting of an inclined tunnel:", "opta": "Reference points are constructed at every 300 m.", "optb": "The alignment is fixed from upper/lower apex point.", "optc": "The level of the invert at the heading is marked by a tape.", "optd": "Reference points are constructed on the roof of tunnels", "opte": "None the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Forepoling method is generally adopted for tunnelling in :", "opta": "soft ground", "optb": "firm ground", "optc": "running ground", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Concrete lining is provided concurrently with the driving operation in case of", "opta": "rock terrain", "optb": "soft rock", "optc": "running soil", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concentration of the dust particles of the size 0.5 to 5 microns adjacent to the working face should not be more than", "opta": "200 particles/cm3", "optb": "250 particles/cm3", "optc": "300 particles/cm3", "optd": "450 particles/cm3", "opte": "400 particles/cm3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct with regard to heading and hench-ing method of tunnelling.", "opta": "Driving of tunnel is done in two portions of its section", "optb": "Driving the top portion is done in advance of the bottom portion.", "optc": "After driving the top portion 3 m to 3.5 m holes are drilled into the head and bench.", "optd": "The holes in head and bench are loaded together with explosive for blasting.", "opte": "Firing of head holes is done just before the bench holes are fired.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following methods is generally used for the layout of the muck-car tracks", "opta": "the grass hopper method", "optb": "passing track method", "optc": "the cherry picker", "optd": "California crossing, Dixon conveyor", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For transferring the tunnel alignment through shafts, we adopt the following steps :1. Hanging two or more plumb lines in the shaft2. Determining the bearing of the plumb lines i.e. plumb plane3. Suspending a 35 kg weight by each plumb line4. Immersing the weights of both the plumb lines in the buckets containing water.The correct sequence of steps is :", "opta": "1 2 3 4", "optb": "4 3 2 1", "optc": "l 3 2 4", "optd": "2 1 4 3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For initial surveys of tunnels, the following activities are involved:1. Marking portal point with concrete pillars on the ground2. Marking tunnel obligatory points on the topographical maps3. Preliminary setting of the tunnel on the topographical Survey of India maps3. Driving lines between the fixed obligatory points.The correct sequence of the activities is :", "opta": "3 2 4 1", "optb": "1 2 3 4", "optc": "4 3 1 2", "optd": "2 4 3 1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For full face method, the excavation to be done is generally divided into", "opta": "two sections", "optb": "three sections", "optc": "four sections", "optd": "five sections.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tunnels, the artificial underground passages are constructed for :", "opta": "highways", "optb": "railways", "optc": "sewerage", "optd": "water supply project", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the wooded bulk-head, used for mucking in steep grade tunnels,", "opta": "one opening is provided", "optb": "two openings are provided", "optc": "three openings are provided", "optd": "no opening is provided.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Railway tunnels, are generally", "opta": "polycentric", "optb": "rectangular", "optc": "parabolic", "optd": "circular", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the explosive used for tunnelling in soft rocks from the following :", "opta": "blasting gelatine", "optb": "special gelatine", "optc": "ammonia dynamite", "optd": "semi-gelatine.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cut of a tunnel face is shown in given figure. This is called", "opta": "Michigan cut", "optb": "Burn cut", "optc": "Fan cut", "optd": "Horizontal cut.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For B.G. single track, the section of the tunnel must have a width", "opta": "4.2 m to 4.5 m", "optb": "4.5 m to 4.8 m", "optc": "4.9 m to 5.5 m", "optd": "5.5 m to 5.8 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following methods is generally adopted for tunnelling in firm ground", "opta": "Full face method", "optb": "Top heading and benching method", "optc": "Drift method", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An overhead track on a large truss frame is required in case of car changer by", "opta": "the grass hopper method", "optb": "the passing track method", "optc": "California crossing method", "optd": "Dixon conveyor method.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The topographical maps of the Survey of India are useful in the mountainous region for tunnelling.", "optb": "The height point on the ridge is fixed with the help of reciprocal ranging", "optc": "The accuracy of 1 in 10, 000 is required for planimetric control", "optd": "1 second theodolite is used for angular measurement to achieve an angular error of 15 N where N is number of angles", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the given figure drill holes, heading, mucking and benching are mumbered as 1, 2, 3, 4 The correct sequence is :", "opta": "4 1 2 3", "optb": "1 2 3 4", "optc": "4 1 3 2", "optd": "3 4 1 3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of the needle beam used in needle beam method of tunnelling is usually", "opta": "2 m to 4 m", "optb": "2.5 m to 6 m", "optc": "4 m to 7 m", "optd": "5 m to 6 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High pressure grouting is generally restored for concreting in the lining if the rock strata is:", "opta": "highly fissured", "optb": "poor", "optc": "likely to get seepage of water", "optd": "All of the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For hauling muck from the tunnel, the following type of muck-car is used :", "opta": "muck box", "optb": "balle-ship", "optc": "side dump car", "optd": "U-bottom", "opte": "All of these.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following methods is adopted for permanent drainage of tunnels :", "opta": "provision of longitudinal drains", "optb": "continuous open drains", "optc": "concrete lining", "optd": "grouting with cement or chemicals", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which type of light energy is effectively absorbed by CO2 in the lower boundary of the troposphere ?", "opta": "X - rays", "optb": "UV - rays", "optc": "Visible light", "optd": "Infra-red rays", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following steps are involved in laying a sewer in a trench :1. Transferring the center line of the sewer to the bottom trench.2. Setting sight rails over the trench.3. Driving pegs to the level of the invert line of the sewer.4. Placing the sewer of these steps is The correct sequence of these steps is", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "2, 3, 4, 1", "optc": "4, 2, 3, 1", "optd": "2, 3, 1, 4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A horizontal rod AB carries three loads of 3.0 kg, 7.0 kg and 10.0 kg at distances of 2.0 cm, 9.0 cm and 15 cm respectively from A where it is hinged. Neglecting the weight of the rod, which is the point at which the rod will be balance ?", "opta": "10.95 cm form A", "optb": "11.25 cm from A", "optc": "12.55 cm from A", "optd": "13.25 cm form A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Distemper is used to coat", "opta": "external concrete surfaces", "optb": "interior surfaces not exposed to weather", "optc": "woodwork", "optd": "compound walls", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two simply supported beams B1 and B2 have spans l and 2l respectively. Beam B1 has a cross-section of 1 x 1 units and beam B2 has a cross-section of 2 x 2 units. These beams are subjected to concentrated loads W each at the centre of their spans. The ratio of the maximum flexural stress in these beams is", "opta": "4", "optb": "2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A soil has a liquid limit of 45% and lies above the A-line when plotted on a plasticity chart. The group, symbol of the soil as per Soil Classification is", "opta": "CH", "optb": "CI", "optc": "CL", "optd": "MI", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A short column of external diameter D and internal diameter d, is subjected to a load W, with an eccentricity 'e', causing zero stress at an extreme fibre. Then the value of 'e' must be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A high efficiency pump is required for low discharge, high head and low maintenance cost. Delivery of water need not be continuous. The pump need not run at high speed. Which one of the following is the correct choice ?", "opta": "Centrifugal pump", "optb": "Reciprocating pump", "optc": "Air lift pump", "optd": "Hydraulic ram", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For total reaction time of 2.5 seconds, coefficient of friction 0.35, design speed 80 km/h, what is the stopping sight distance on a highway ?", "opta": "127 m", "optb": "132 m", "optc": "76 m", "optd": "56 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the use of a station pointer ?", "opta": "For making soundings in water bodies", "optb": "For plotting of soundings in harbour area", "optc": "For marking sunken shipping hazards", "optd": "For making tidal observations", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The plastic modulus of a section is 5 x 10-4m3. Its shape factor is 1.2 and the plastic moment capacity is 120 kNm. What is the value of the yield stress of the material ?", "opta": "100 N/mm2", "optb": "200 N/mm2", "optc": "240 N/mm2", "optd": "288 N/mm2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to ICAO recommendations, what is the rate of elevation correction for the runway above MSL ?", "opta": "1 % for every 100 m of elevation above MSL", "optb": "7 % for every 300 m of elevation above MSL", "optc": "2 % for every 500 m of elevation above MSL", "optd": "2 % for every 300 m of elevation above MSL", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The absolute maximum Bending Moment in a simply supported beam of span 20 m due to moving udl of 4 t/m spanning over 5 m is", "opta": "87.5 t-m at the support", "optb": "87.5 t-m near the midpoint", "optc": "3.5 t-m at the midpoint", "optd": "87.5 t-m at the midpoint", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following steps are involved in making a spigot and socket joint of cast iron pipes used in water supply systems :1. Tarred gasket or hemp yarn in wrapped around the spigot.2. The sipgot end is centered into the socket end of the preceding pipe.3. A joining ring end is placed around the barrel and against the face of the socket.4. The gasket or hemp yarn in caulked slightly.5. Molten pig lead is poured and then caulked.The correct sequence of these steps is", "opta": "2, 1, 4, 3, 5", "optb": "2, 1, 3, 4, 5", "optc": "1, 2, 4, 5, 3", "optd": "1, 2, 3, 5, 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements :A : In masonry, bricks are joined together by cement mortar.B : Cement mortar adheres more effectively to brick surface than any other material.", "opta": "both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A", "optb": "both A and R are true but R is not the correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the force system shown in the figure, the force CA should be", "opta": "5 t", "optb": "- 5 t", "optc": "4 t", "optd": "- 4 t", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cylindrical shell made of mild steel plate of 100 cm diameter is to be subjected to an internal pressure of 10 kg/cm2. If the material yields at 2000 kg/cm2, assuming factor of safety as four and using maximum principal stress theory, thickness of the plate will be", "opta": "5 mm", "optb": "10 mm", "optc": "15 mm", "optd": "20 mm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A plot of land 60\u00b0m x 20 m is measure steel tape. If the standard error of length width measurements is taken as \u00b1 1 cm, the standard error of the area of the plot be", "opta": "\u00b1 0.1414 m2", "optb": "\u00b1 0.566 m2", "optc": "\u00b1 0.632 m2", "optd": "\u00b1 0.8484 m2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The graphical condition for equilibrium of concurrent forces is that", "opta": "both the force polygon and the funicular polygon must be closed figures", "optb": "funicular polygon should be a closed figure", "optc": "force polygon need not be a closed figure", "optd": "force polygon should be a closed figure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a tilted aerial photograph, if the swing is 230\u00b0, then the rotation angle is equal to", "opta": "140\u00b0", "optb": "130\u00b0", "optc": "50\u00b0", "optd": "25\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cold drawn seamless steel tubing subject to internal pressure, has a diameter of 6 cm and wall thickness of 0.2 cm. The ultimate strength of steel is 3600 kg/cm2. The bursting pressure (in kg/cm2) is", "opta": "120", "optb": "240", "optc": "480", "optd": "960", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following factors are associated with the behaviour of sand mass during earthquake to cause liquefaction ?1. Number of stress cycles2. The frequency, and amplitude of vibration of waves generated by an earthquake3. Characteristics of sand4. Relative densitySelect the correct answer using the codes given below :", "opta": "1, 2 and 3", "optb": "1, 2, 3 and 4", "optc": "2 and 4", "optd": "3 and 4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of total elongation of a bar of uniform cross-section produced under its own weight to the elongation produced by an external load equal to the weight of the bar is", "opta": "2", "optb": "1", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "1/4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The figure refers to a channel section of uniform thickness of 1 cm used as a beam with the cross-sectional dimensions shown in cm units. If the Moment of Inertia of channel Ixx be equal to 246 cm4 and C be the shear centre, then the value of e in cm is equal to", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "2.5", "optc": "2.25", "optd": "1.67", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shear force diagram of a beam is shown in the given figure. The absolute maximum bending moment in the beam is", "opta": "(2P x a)", "optb": "(5P x a)", "optc": "(4P x a)", "optd": "(7P x a)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A locomotive has four pairs of driving wheels carrying an axle load of 24 x 104 N. The maximum load that can be pulled if the coefficient of friction is 1/6, is", "opta": "32 x 104 N", "optb": "16 x 104 N", "optc": "8 x 104 N", "optd": "4 x 104 N", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A bar of circular cross-section of diameter D is subjected to a torque T at B as shown in the figure given. What is the angle of twist at A?", "opta": "Same as that at B", "optb": "Zero", "optc": "Twice as that at B", "optd": "Half as that at B", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements regarding Plane Table surveying : 1. It is less accurate than chain surveying. 2. It is not necessary to do accurate centering of plane table for small scale survey.3. Compass rule may be made use for adjusting the plane table transverse.4. From the instrument station, resectors are drawn to plot the position of object in the field.  Of these statements :", "opta": "1, 2 and 4 are correct", "optb": "2, 3 and 4 are correct", "optc": "1, 2 and 3 are correct", "optd": "1, 3 and 4 are correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pin-jointed tower truss is loaded as shown in the given figure. The force induced in the member DF is", "opta": "1.5 kN (tension)", "optb": "4.5 kN (tension)", "optc": "1.5 kN (compression)", "optd": "4.5 kN (compression)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a PERT network, the activity durations are given as to (optimistic), tp (pessimistic) and tm (most likely time). What is the variance of is activity ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A particle of mass 3 kg moving in a straight line decelerates uniformly from a speed of 40 m/s to 20 m/s in a distance of 300 m. Before it comes to rest, it will travel a further distance pf", "opta": "10 m", "optb": "20 m", "optc": "50 m", "optd": "100 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For designing end bearing piles of square cross-section in clays having average unconfmed compressive strength of 6 t/m2, the net ultimate bearing capacity may be taken as", "opta": "15 t/m2", "optb": "18 t/m2", "optc": "20 t/m2", "optd": "27 t/m2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The side AD of the square block ABCD as shown in the given figure is fixed at the base and it is under a state of simple shear causing shear stress \u03c4 and shear strain \u03c0, where  The distorted shape is AB'C'D. The diagonal strain (linear) will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "\u03c62", "optd": "\u03c6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements :Collision diagram is used to1. study accident pattern2. eliminate accidents3. determine remedial measures4. make statistical analysis of accidentsOf these statements :", "opta": "1 and 2 are correct", "optb": "1 and 3 are correct", "optc": "3 and 4 are correct", "optd": "2 and 4 are correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements :1. An ascending gradient of 1 in 100 meets an ascending gradient of 1 in 120 to form a Valley curve.2. A falling gradient of 1 in 25 meets a falling gradient of 1 in 50 to form a summit curve.3. The length of summit curve is determined on the basis of head light sight distance.Which one of the statements given above is/are correct ?", "opta": "1 and 2", "optb": "2 and 3", "optc": "1 and 3", "optd": "2 only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rectangular block shown in the given figure is subjected to pure shear to intensity 'q'. If BE represents the i principal plane and the principal stresses are \u03c31, \u03c32 ; then the values of \u03b8, \u03c31 and \u03c32 will be respectively.", "opta": "\u03b8\u00b0, 90\u00b0; + q and - q", "optb": "30\u00b0, 120\u00b0; + q and - q", "optc": "45\u00b0, 135\u00b0; + and", "optd": "45\u00b0, 135\u00b0; + q and - q", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum energy stored at elastic limit of a material is called", "opta": "resilience", "optb": "proof resilience", "optc": "modulus of resilience", "optd": "bulk resilience", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the pressure carried by a CBR specimen at 2.5 mm penetration is 3.5 N/mm2, the CBR of the soil is", "opta": "10%", "optb": "35%", "optc": "50%", "optd": "70%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A close-coiled helical spring with n coils, mean radius R and diameter d is subjected to an axial load W. What is the compression in the spring ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Activated sludge is the", "opta": "resultant sludge removable from the aeration unit", "optb": "sludge settled in the humus tank", "optc": "sludge in the secondary tank post-aeration rich in microbial mass", "optd": "sludge.in the secondary tank post aeration, rich in nutrients.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which are the critical activities of the bar chart shown above ?", "opta": "Activities B and E", "optb": "Activities A, D and F", "optc": "Activities A, C and E", "optd": "Activities A and F", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the effective height of a free-standing masonry wall for the purpose of computing slenderness ratio ?", "opta": "0.5 L", "optb": "1.0 L", "optc": "2.0 L", "optd": "2.5 L", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To generate 10, 000 hp under a head of 81 m while working at a speed of 500 rpirt, the turbine of choice would be", "opta": "Pelton", "optb": "Kaplan", "optc": "Bulb", "optd": "Francis", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements :Sand in mortar is needed for1. decreasing the quantity of cement.2. reducing shrinkage.3. decreasing the surface area of the binding material.4. increasing the strength.Of these statements :", "opta": "2, 3 and 4 are correct", "optb": "1, 2 and 3 are correct", "optc": "1, 3 and 4 are correct", "optd": "1, 2 and 4 are correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The given figure shows gradually varied flow in an open channel with a beak in bed slope. Types of water surface profiles occurring from left to right are", "opta": "H2 , S3", "optb": "H2 , S2", "optc": "H2 , M2", "optd": "H3 , M2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following strengths of concrete :1. Cube strength2. Cylinder strength3. Split-tensile strength4. Modulus of ruptureThe correct sequence in decreasing order of these strengths is", "opta": "3, 4, 2, 1", "optb": "3, 4, 1, 2", "optc": "4, 3, 2, 1", "optd": "4, 3, 1, 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reinforced concrete slab is 75 mm thick. The maximum size of reinforcement bar that can be used is", "opta": "12 mm diameter", "optb": "10 mm diameter", "optc": "8 mm diameter", "optd": "6 mm diameter", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consider the following methods of preservation of timber :1. Dipping2. Brushing or spraying3. Pressure impregnationThe correct sequence in decreasing order of the effectiveness of these methods of preservation is", "opta": "1, 2, 3", "optb": "2, 1, 3", "optc": "3, 1, 2", "optd": "3, 2, 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Purlins are provided, in industrial buildings, over roof trusses to carry dead loads, live loads and wind loads. As per IS code, what are they assumed to be ?", "opta": "Simply supported", "optb": "Cantilever", "optc": "Continuous", "optd": "Fixed", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ratio of bearing capacity of double Under Reamed (U.R.) pile to that of single U.R. pile is nearly", "opta": "2", "optb": "1.5", "optc": "1.2", "optd": "1.7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The minimum recommended diameter of sewers, is", "opta": "5 cm", "optb": "10 cm", "optc": "15 cm", "optd": "20 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aerobic bacterias", "opta": "flourish in the presence of free oxygen", "optb": "consume organic matter as their food", "optc": "oxidise organic matter in sewage", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of accumulation of sludge in septic tanks is recommended as", "opta": "30 litres/person/year", "optb": "25 litres/person/year", "optc": "30 litres/person/month", "optd": "25 litres/person/month.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If 2% solution of a sewage sample is incubated for 5 days at 20\u00b0C and depletion of oxygen was found to be 5 ppm, B.O.D. of the sewage is", "opta": "200 ppm", "optb": "225 ppm", "optc": "250 ppm", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is the diameter of upper circular portion, the overall depth of a standard egg shaped section, is", "opta": "D", "optb": "1.25 D", "optc": "1.5 D", "optd": "1.75 D", "opte": "2 D.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the diameter of sewer is 225 mm, the gradient required for generating self cleansing velocity, is", "opta": "1 in 60", "optb": "1 in 100", "optc": "1 in 120", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "pH value indicates acidity and alkalinity of sewage", "optb": "In acidic sewage, the pH value is less than 7", "optc": "In alkaline sewage, the pH value is more than 7", "optd": "Fresh sewage is generally alkaline", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The non-clog pump which permits solid matter to pass out with the liquid sewage, is", "opta": "centrifugal pump", "optb": "reciprocating pump", "optc": "pneumatic ejector", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Assertion (A) : Discharging the effluents from the oxidation ponds just up stream of lakes or reservoirs is undesirable. Reason (R) : The discharged algae get settled in the reservoirs and cause anaerobic decomposition and other water qualities.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The width of a rectangular sewer is twice its depth while discharging 1.5 m/sec. The width of the sewer is", "opta": "0.68 m", "optb": "0.88 m", "optc": "1.36 m", "optd": "1.76 m.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "In treated sewage, 4 PPm of D.O. is essential", "optb": "Only very fresh sewage contains some dissolved oxygen", "optc": "The solubility of oxygen in sewage is 95% that is in distilled water", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In olden days the type of section adopted in trunk and out fall sewers was", "opta": "parabolic shaped", "optb": "horse shoe shaped", "optc": "egg shaped", "optd": "circular shaped.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the survival of fish in a river stream, the minimum dissolved oxygen is prescribed", "opta": "3 PPm", "optb": "4 PPm", "optc": "5 PPm", "optd": "10 ppm.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a fully mechanised composting plant, involves", "opta": "mechanized receipt", "optb": "mechanized segregation", "optc": "mechanized pulverising of refuse", "optd": "all of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Self-cleansing velocity is", "opta": "velocity at dry weather flow", "optb": "velocity of water at flushing", "optc": "velocity at which no accumulation remains in the drains", "optd": "velocity of water in a pressure filter.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the over land flow from the critical point to the drain is 8 km and the difference in level is 12.4 m, the inlet time is", "opta": "2 hours", "optb": "3 hours", "optc": "4 hours", "optd": "5 hours.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An inverted siphon is designed generally for", "opta": "one pipe", "optb": "two pipes", "optc": "three pipes", "optd": "four pipes.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rainfall may be classified as acidic if its pH value is less or equal to", "opta": "6", "optb": "7", "optc": "5", "optd": "6.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When drainage to sewage ratio is 20, the peak dry weather flow is", "opta": "20% of the design discharge", "optb": "slightly less than 5% of the design discharge", "optc": "slightly more than 5% of the design discharge", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For treating the sewage of a large city, you will recommend", "opta": "a sedimentation tank and an activated sludge treatment plant", "optb": "a plant consisting of Imhoff tanks with low rate trickling filters", "optc": "sedimentation tanks with high rate trickling filters", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The detention time of a circular tank of diameter d and water depth H, for receiving the sewage Q per hour, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dimensions of a rectangular settling tank are : length 24 m, width 6 m and depth 3 m. If 2 hour detention period for tanks is recommended, the rate of flow of sewage per hour, is", "opta": "204 cu m", "optb": "208 cu m", "optc": "212 cu m", "optd": "216 cu m", "opte": "220 cu m.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The screens are fixed", "opta": "perpendicular to the direction of flow", "optb": "parallel to the direction of flow", "optc": "at an angle 30\u00b0 to 60\u00b0 to the direction of flow", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In primary sedimentation, the 0.2 mm inorganic solids get separated if specific gravity is", "opta": "2.25", "optb": "2.50", "optc": "2.55", "optd": "2.65", "opte": "2.75", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the in-correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Manholes are provided in sewer pipes at suitable intervals", "optb": "Catch basins are generally provided in sewers for carrying drainage discharge", "optc": "Inlets are generally provided in all sewers", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Clogging of sewers, is caused due to", "opta": "silting", "optb": "low discharge", "optc": "greasy and oily matters", "optd": "domestic wastes thrown in manholes", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A sewer pipe contains 1 mm sand particles of specific gravity 2.65 and 5 mm organic particles of specific gravity 1.2, the minimum velocity required for removing the sewerage, is", "opta": "0.30 m/sec", "optb": "0.35 m/sec", "optc": "0.40 m/sec", "optd": "0.45 m/sec", "opte": "0.50 m/sec.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coagulant widely used for sewage treatment, is", "opta": "alum", "optb": "ferric chloride", "optc": "ferric sulphate", "optd": "chlorinated copperas.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "House connections to the laterals is generally made by", "opta": "R.C.C.", "optb": "P.C.C.", "optc": "Cast iron", "optd": "Glazed stonewares.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of maximum sewage flow to average sewage flow for mains up to 1 m in diameter, is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "2.0", "optc": "3.0", "optd": "4.0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dilution method of disposing off sewage, is not preferred to", "opta": "when sewage is fresh", "optb": "when diluting water has high dissolved oxygen content", "optc": "when diluting water is used for water supply near the point of sewage disposed", "optd": "when the diluting water is having flow currents", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For house drainage minimum gradient is", "opta": "1 in 60", "optb": "1 in 80", "optc": "1 in 10", "optd": "1 in 400", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the side of a square sewer is 1000 mm, the diameter of a hydraulically equivalent circular section, is", "opta": "1045 mm", "optb": "1065 mm", "optc": "1075 mm", "optd": "1095 mm.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of minimum hourly flow to the average flow of sewage is", "opta": "1/4", "optb": "1/3", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "3/4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bio-chemical oxygen demand (BOD) for the first 20 days in generally referred to", "opta": "initial demand", "optb": "first stage demand", "optc": "carbonaceous demand", "optd": "all of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flocculated particles do not change their", "opta": "size", "optb": "shape", "optc": "weight", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For non-scouring velocity 5 m/sec, the type of sewers generally preferred to, is", "opta": "cast iron sewers", "optb": "cement concrete sewers", "optc": "glazed bricks sewers", "optd": "stone ware sewers.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Disposal to sewage in large cities, is done in", "opta": "irrigation", "optb": "dilution", "optc": "oxidation", "optd": "putrifaction.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the COD test of sewage, organic matter is oxidised by K2Cr207 in the presence of", "opta": "H2SO4", "optb": "HNO3", "optc": "HCl", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In R.C. sewer pipes, the percentage longitudinal reinforcement to the cross-sectional area of concrete is kept", "opta": "10.0", "optb": "5.0", "optc": "2.0", "optd": "0.25", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The asbestos cement pipes are generally laid", "opta": "horizontally", "optb": "vertically", "optc": "at an angle of 30\u00b0", "optd": "at an angle of 60\u00b0.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chlorination of water is done for the removal of", "opta": "bacterias", "optb": "suspended solids", "optc": "sediments", "optd": "hardness.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For evaporation and measurement of settlable solids, the apparatus used, is", "opta": "a jar", "optb": "a breaker", "optc": "a test tube", "optd": "an Imhoff cone.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In SI units the power of sound is represented in", "opta": "kgs", "optb": "joules", "optc": "neutons", "optd": "watts.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rain sanitary sewer is constructed to carry", "opta": "sanitary sewage", "optb": "storm sewage", "optc": "surface water", "optd": "ground water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sewage is pumped up", "opta": "from low lying areas", "optb": "from flat areas", "optc": "from basements", "optd": "across a high ridge", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Removal of oil and grease from sewage, is known", "opta": "screening", "optb": "skimming", "optc": "filtration", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The gas which may cause explosion in sewers, is", "opta": "carbondioxide", "optb": "methane", "optc": "ammonia", "optd": "carbon monoxide.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In sewers the effect of scouring is more on", "opta": "top side", "optb": "bottom side", "optc": "horizontal side", "optd": "all sides.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water contains", "opta": "one hydrogen atom and one oxygen atom", "optb": "two hydrogen atoms and one oxygen atom", "optc": "one hydrogen atom and two oxygen atoms", "optd": "three hydrogen atoms and two oxygen atoms", "opte": "two hydrogen atoms and three oxygen atoms.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Unit Hydrograph theory was enunciated by", "opta": "Merril Bernard", "optb": "W.W. Horner", "optc": "Le-Roy K. Shermen", "optd": "Robert E. Horten.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The theory of infiltration capacity was given by", "opta": "Merrill Bernard", "optb": "W.W. Horner", "optc": "Le-Roy K. Shermen", "optd": "Robert E. Horten.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrology helps in", "opta": "predicting maximum flows", "optb": "deciding the minimum reservoir capacity", "optc": "forecasting the availability of quantity of water at reservoir site", "optd": "predicting the effects on the river water level on completion of dams", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Rivers, lakes, oceans and springs get water from the rains", "optb": "Rain water is obtained by evaporation from rivers, lakes and oceans", "optc": "Water remains in atmosphere as vapours", "optd": "Hydrologic cycle is a continuous process of evaporation and precipitation of water in atmosphere", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Rain which is intercepted by buildings, vegetations and other objects, is generally known as rainfall interception", "optb": "The difference between the total rainfall and intercepted rainfall, is generally called ground rainfall", "optc": "When rainfall exceeds the interception rainfall, water reaches the ground and infiltration starts", "optd": "The maximum rate of absorbing water by the soil in any given condition, is known as infiltration capacity", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The surface Run-off is the quantity of water", "opta": "absorbed by soil", "optb": "intercepted by buildings and vegetative cover", "optc": "required to fill surface depressions", "optd": "that reaches the stream channels", "opte": "that gets evaporated.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct equation from the following :", "opta": "Run off = Surface run off + Ground water flow", "optb": "Run off = Surface run off - Ground water flow", "optc": "Run off = Surface run off / Ground water flow", "optd": "Run off = Surface run off x Ground water flow.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Infiltration capacity of soil depends upon", "opta": "number of voids present in the soil", "optb": "shape and size of soil particles", "optc": "arrangement of soil particles", "optd": "compaction of the soil particles", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "When rainfall rate exceeds the infiltration capacity, the water enters the soil at full capacity rate", "optb": "When rainfall rate is less than the infiltration capacity, the infiltration rate is approximately equal to the rainfall rate", "optc": "The actual infiltration rate at any time may be equal to or less than the infiltration capacity", "optd": "The actual prevailing rate of infiltration of water in the soil at any time, is known as infiltration rate", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "The portion of pellicular water which remains unutilised, is called hygroscopic water", "optb": "The moisture content at which permanent wilting of plants takes place, is called the wilting point", "optc": "The path of the water required to bring the soil moisture content of a soil up to its field capacity is called soil moisture deficiency", "optd": "The moisture deficiency will be different at different points", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main factor which affects the infiltration capacity, is", "opta": "thickness of saturated layer", "optb": "depth of surface detention", "optc": "soil moisture", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Robert E. Horton, the equation of infiltration capacity curve, is (where letters carry their usual meanings)", "opta": "f = fc (fo - fc) ekt", "optb": "f = ft - (fo - fc) e-kt", "optc": "f = ft + (fo - fc) e-kt", "optd": "f = f + (fo - fc) ekt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Absolute humidity at a given temperature is equal to weight of moisture present in a unit volume", "optb": "Relative humidity is the ratio of actual vapour pressure and saturation vapour pressure at the same temperature", "optc": "Relative humidity is the ratio of the weight of the vapours present per unit volume to the weight of vapours which could be contained at the same temperature when fully saturated", "optd": "Humidity can be measured by psychrometer", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absolute humidity in air", "opta": "decreases at higher altitudes", "optb": "increases at higher altitudes", "optc": "remains constant at all altitudes", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Precipitation caused by lifting of an air mass due to the pressure difference, is called", "opta": "cyclonic precipitation", "optb": "convective precipitation", "optc": "orographic precipitation", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The standard height of a standard rain gauge, is", "opta": "10 cm", "optb": "20 cm", "optc": "30 cm", "optd": "50 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India, rain fall is generally recorded at", "opta": "8 A.M.", "optb": "12 Noon", "optc": "4 P.M.", "optd": "8 P.M.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A recording type rain gauge", "opta": "produces a mass curve of rain fall", "optb": "records the cumulative rain", "optc": "is sometimes called integrating rain gauge or continuous rain gauge", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India the recording type rain gauge generally used, is", "opta": "weighing type", "optb": "tipping type", "optc": "float recording type", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deficiency in rain catch due to vertical acceleration of air forced upward over the gauge, is", "opta": "greater for heavy rain", "optb": "greater for lighter rain", "optc": "greater for large drops", "optd": "lesser for small rain drops.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a gauge is installed perpendicular to the slope, its measurement is reduced by multiplying", "opta": "sine of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optb": "cosine of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optc": "tangent of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optd": "calibration coefficient of the gauge.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determination of average annual precipitation in a catchment basin, the best method is", "opta": "Arithmetical method", "optb": "Thiessen's mean method", "optc": "Isohyetal method", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While calculating the average depth of annual precipitation in a catchment basin, importance to individual raingauge station is given in", "opta": "Arithmetical method", "optb": "Thiessen's mean method", "optc": "Isohyetal method", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "opte": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical depth in a channel can be produced", "opta": "by raising the bottom of the channel", "optb": "by lowering the bottom of the channel", "optc": "by decreasing the width of the channel", "optd": "by increasing the width of the channel", "opte": "both (a) and (c) of above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic jump in a control meter will be formed above the control, if its original", "opta": "depth is more than critical depth", "optb": "depth is less than the critical depth", "optc": "depth is equal to critical depth", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Prof. Running suggested the method for extending the discharge curve. It is known as", "opta": "Logarithmic method", "optb": "y method", "optc": "General method", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If y is the depth of water at any section, then the mean velocity is", "opta": "0.1 y", "optb": "0.2 y", "optc": "0.3 y", "optd": "0.5 y", "opte": "0.6 y.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The run off is affected by", "opta": "type of precipitation", "optb": "rain intensity and duration of rainfall", "optc": "rain distribution and soil moisture deficiency", "optd": "direction of prevailing storm", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The initial basin recharge is equal to", "opta": "interception", "optb": "depression storage", "optc": "rain absorbed by the moisture deficiency", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The run off a drainage basin is", "opta": "Initial recharge + ground water accretion + precipitation", "optb": "Precipitation + ground water accretion + initial recharge", "optc": "Precipitation - ground water accretion + initial recharge", "optd": "Precipitation - ground water accretion - initial recharge.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For computing the run off volumes of large areas, number of infiltrations used are", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "From the Survey of India map, the distance of the critical point is 20 km and difference in elevation is 193 m. The over land flow time, is", "opta": "2 hours", "optb": "3 hours", "optc": "2 hours and 30 minutes", "optd": "3 hours and 30 minutes", "opte": "4 hours.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the area of storm hydrograph is equal to 102 cm, the ordinates of a unit hydrograph may be obtained by dividing the ordinates of the storm hydrograph by", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "opte": "4", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If s is the potential infiltration, P is rainfall in cm in a drainage of a soil with fair pasture cover, the direct run off Q in cm is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the potential infiltration of a water shed having a soil with fair pasture cover, is 10 cm and rainfall is 12 cm, the direct run off is :", "opta": "2 cm", "optb": "3 cm", "optc": "5 cm", "optd": "8 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quantity of water retained by the sub-soil against gravity, is known", "opta": "yield", "optb": "porosity", "optc": "specific yield", "optd": "specific retention", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following :", "opta": "The rate of flow of water through a unit cross-sectional area under a unit hydraulic gradient, is called coefficient of permeability", "optb": "The rate of flow of water through a vertical strip of the acquifer of unit width and full depth under a unit hydraulic gradient, is called coefficient of transmissibility", "optc": "The flow of water through acquifers, is governed by the Darcy's law", "optd": "The term 'transmissibility' was introduced by Meinzer", "opte": "The ratio of coefficient of transmissibility and coefficient of permeability, is equal to the depth of acquifer through which water flows.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With the usual meanings ofletters, the equation  is used for determining the velocity of ground water flow in metres per day. It is known as", "opta": "Meinzer's formula", "optb": "Slichter's formula", "optc": "Darcy's formula", "optd": "Hazen's formula.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the viscosity of ground water is 1.00, the Slitcher's constant is 400, the effective size of soil particles in acquifer is 0.5 mm and hydraulic gradient is 1 in 80, the velocity of flow is", "opta": "0.25 m/day", "optb": "0.50 m/day", "optc": "0.75 m/day", "optd": "1.00 m/day", "opte": "1.25 m/day.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Perched aquifer is found in unconfined aquifer", "optb": "The top surface of the water held in the perched aquifer, is known as perched water table", "optc": "Perched aquifer is formed in unfined accquifer if an impervious layer exists", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the derivation of Thiem's formula , the following assumption is not applicable", "opta": "The aquifer is homogeneous and isotropic", "optb": "Flow lines are radial and horizontal", "optc": "The slope of the water surface is too small", "optd": "The well has been sunk up to the surface of the unconfined aquifer", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A well penetrates to 30 m below the static water table. After 24 hours of pumping at 31.40 litres/minute, the water level in a test well at a distance of 80 m is lowered by 0.5 m and in a well 20 m away water is lowered by 1.0 m. The transmissibility of the auifer, is", "opta": "1.185 m2/minute", "optb": "1.285 m2/minute", "optc": "1.385 m2/minute", "optd": "1.485 m2/minute", "opte": "1.585 m2/minute.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shrouding is provided in", "opta": "cavity type tube wells", "optb": "slotted type tube wells", "optc": "strainer type tube wells", "optd": "perforated type tube wells.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a pump may be taken as", "opta": "0.55", "optb": "0.60", "optc": "0.65", "optd": "0.70", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consumptive use of a crop during growth, is the amount of", "opta": "interception", "optb": "transpiration", "optc": "evaporation", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For calculating the evaporation rate over a reservoir surface E = 0.771 (1.465 - 0.00732 B) (0.44 - 0.007375 V) (pe - pa), the equation is given by", "opta": "Roohwer's, formula in M.K.S.", "optb": "Roohwer's formula in F.P.S.", "optc": "Dalton's formula in F.P.S.", "optd": "Dalton's formula in M.K.S.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the estimate of high floods in fan-shaped catchment, the formula used is", "opta": "Dicken's formula", "optb": "Ryve's formula", "optc": "Inglis formula", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Burge formula  cumecs is based upon", "opta": "rainfall and drainage area", "optb": "run off and drainage area", "optc": "drainage area and its shape", "optd": "drainage area.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Surge tanks are used", "opta": "for storage water", "optb": "to increase the velocity in a pipeline", "optc": "as overflow valves", "optd": "to guard against water hammer.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As per IS : 1172-1963, water required per head per day for average domestic purposes, is", "opta": "50 litres", "optb": "65 litres", "optc": "85 litres", "optd": "105 litres", "opte": "135 litres.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In slow sland filters, the turbidity of raw water can be removed only up to", "opta": "60 mg/litre", "optb": "75 mg/litre", "optc": "100 gm/litre", "optd": "150 mg/litre.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Biochemical Oxygen Demand (B.O.D.) of safe drinking water must be", "opta": "nil", "optb": "5", "optc": "10", "optd": "15", "opte": "20", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acidity in water is caused due to", "opta": "Mineral acids", "optb": "Free CO2", "optc": "Iron sulphate", "optd": "Aluminium sulphate", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transitional middle portion of a logistic curve follows", "opta": "a geometric growth", "optb": "a logarithmic growth", "optc": "a first over curve", "optd": "a constant rate.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Excess quantities of iron and manganese in water, cause discolouration of clothes", "optb": "Lead and barium salts have toxic effect", "optc": "Arsenic and selenium are poisonous to human health", "optd": "Higher copper content affects the lungs", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following regarding fire hydrants", "opta": "Fire hydrants are fitted in water mains at 100 m to 150 m apart at fire", "optb": "The minimum water pressure hydrants, is kept 1.5 kg/cm2", "optc": "The water at pressure 1 to 1.5 kg/cm2 is made available for 4 to 5 hours for constant use", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific retention is least in case of", "opta": "Clay", "optb": "Sand", "optc": "Silt", "optd": "Coarse gravel.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "B.O.D. of treated water should be", "opta": "10 ppm", "optb": "25 ppm", "optc": "20 ppm", "optd": "30 ppm", "opte": "Nil.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used pump for lifting water in water supply mains, is", "opta": "axialflow pump", "optb": "reciprocating pump", "optc": "rotary type pump", "optd": "centrifugal pumps", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Economic height of a dam is the height corresponding to which", "opta": "cost of the dam per unit of storage is minimum", "optb": "amount of silting is less", "optc": "cost of dam per unit storage is maximum", "optd": "free board provided is least", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Distribution mains of any water supply, is normally designed for its average daily requirement", "opta": "100%", "optb": "150%", "optc": "200%", "optd": "225%.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of water is", "opta": "7 water it is said to be neutral", "optb": "less than 7 it is said to be acidic", "optc": "more than 7 it is said to be alkaline", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In pressure supply mains, water hammer pressure is reduced by providing", "opta": "sluice valves", "optb": "air valves", "optc": "pressure relief valves", "optd": "none of the these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P0, P1, P2 be the populations of a city at times t0, t1 and t2 = 2t1, the saturation value of the population Ps of the city, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water supply system includes", "opta": "digging a well for water", "optb": "construction of dams", "optc": "construction of canals", "optd": "entire arrangement from source to distribution.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of a pipe", "opta": "reduces its life span", "optb": "reduces its carrying capacity", "optc": "adds colour to water", "optd": "adds odour to water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most satisfactory formula for an estimate of fire demand Q for a city of population P in thousands for Indian conditions, is", "opta": "", "optb": "Q = 1640 P (1 - 0.01 P)", "optc": "Q = 3180 P", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Detention period for plain sedimentation tanks ranges between 4 to 8 hours", "optb": "Detention period for sedimentation tanks, using coagulants usually ranges between 2 to 4 hours", "optc": "The horizontally flow velocity in sedimentation tanks, is generally limited to 0.3 m/minute", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Kuichling's formula, fire demand in litres per minute for a population of P thousands, is", "opta": "3182 P", "optb": "", "optc": "4637 P [1 - 0.01 P]", "optd": "5663 P.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum permissible nitrites in public water supplies, is", "opta": "Nil", "optb": "0.5 P.P.M.", "optc": "1.0. P.P.M.", "optd": "1.5 P.P.M.", "opte": "200 P.P.M.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A high velocity of wash water is required for", "opta": "rapid gravity filter with strainers", "optb": "rapid gravity filter without strainers", "optc": "slow sand filter with strainers", "optd": "slow sand filter without strainers", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distribution pipes, drain valves are provided at", "opta": "lower point", "optb": "higher point", "optc": "junction points", "optd": "any where.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of well pipes may not be reduced by", "opta": "reducing the draw down and the pumping rate", "optb": "reducing the flow velocity", "optc": "using thicker pipes", "optd": "using screens having larger area of openings", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Manholes along the mains from the source to a city are provided at 500 m intervals in", "opta": "steel pipes", "optb": "R.C.C. pipes", "optc": "hume steel pipes", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The population growth curve is", "opta": "S-shaped curve", "optb": "parabolic curve", "optc": "circular curve", "optd": "straight line", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Turbidity of raw water is a measure of", "opta": "suspended solids", "optb": "acidity of water", "optc": "B.O.D.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If V is total consumption of water in litres for a population of N individuals, per capita consumption or water allowance for the water supply Q, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water supply includes", "opta": "collection, transportation and treatment of water", "optb": "distribution of water to consumers", "optc": "provision of hydrants for fire fighting", "optd": "mains, sub-mains and branch lines of water supply", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Asbestos pipes are", "opta": "light in weight and easy to transport", "optb": "highly resistant to corrosion", "optc": "high flexible to accommodate deflection upto 12\u00b0", "optd": "very much smooth and hydraulically efficient", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum depth of sedimentation tanks is limited to", "opta": "2 m", "optb": "3 m", "optc": "4 m", "optd": "5 m", "opte": "6 m.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By boiling water, hardness can be removed if it is due to", "opta": "calcium sulphate", "optb": "magnesium sulphate", "optc": "calcium nitrate", "optd": "calcium bicarbonate", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Q is the discharge from an unconfined tube well with depression head s through its pipe of radius rw. If the radius of influence is R, the length of the required strainer, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determining the velocity of flow of underground water, the most commonly used non-empirical formula is", "opta": "Darcy's formula", "optb": "Slichter's formula", "optc": "Hazen's formula", "optd": "Lacy's formula.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The least thickness of class B cast iron (spun) pipe, is", "opta": "7.2 mm", "optb": "7.9 mm", "optc": "8.6 mm", "optd": "10 mm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to IS : 1172-1963, a minimum of 135 litres of water capita per day, is required for", "opta": "Boarding schools", "optb": "Nurses home and medical quarters", "optc": "hostels", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The R.L. of ground water table on the sides of a valley is 1505 m whereas R.L. of the stream water is 1475 m. If 60\u00b0 slope consists of pervious soil between R.L. 1485 m to 1500 m, the gravity spring may be expected at the point of reduced level", "opta": "1500 m", "optb": "1505 m", "optc": "1475 m", "optd": "1485 m.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The factor affecting per capita demand, is", "opta": "size of the city", "optb": "climatic conditions", "optc": "pressure in water mains", "optd": "cost of water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following. The underground sources of water, is from", "opta": "wells", "optb": "springs", "optc": "infiltration wells", "optd": "storage reservoirs", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Disinfection of drinking water, is done to remove", "opta": "odour", "optb": "bacterias", "optc": "turbidity", "optd": "colour.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sunlight", "opta": "helps growth of bacterias", "optb": "impedes growth of algae", "optc": "increases dissolved oxygen content", "optd": "reduces turbidity.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expected discharge to be obtained from an open well sunk in coarse sand is 0.0059 cumec. If the working depression head of the well is 3 m, the minimum diameter of the well, is", "opta": "2 m", "optb": "2.25 m", "optc": "2.50 m", "optd": "2.75 m", "opte": "3.00 m.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Average annual rainfall at any station is the average of annual rainfall over a period of", "opta": "7 years", "optb": "14 years", "optc": "21 years", "optd": "28 years", "opte": "35 years.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Time of concentration", "opta": "is the time taken, for precipitation", "optb": "duration of rainfall.", "optc": "time taken for all the ran off to reach the drain", "optd": "time taken for the storm water to travel from the most remote point to the drain.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If four fires break out in a city of population 40 lakhs and if each hydrant has three streams and duration of each fire is four hours, the total quantity of water required, is", "opta": "1880 kilo litres", "optb": "2880 kilo litres", "optc": "3880 kilo litres", "optd": "4880 kilo litres.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fire demand of a city may be worked out by", "opta": "Kuichling's formula", "optb": "Freeman formula", "optc": "Under Writers formula", "optd": "Bustan's formula", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aeration of water is done to remove", "opta": "odour", "optb": "colour", "optc": "bacterias", "optd": "hardness", "opte": "turbidity.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The yield of a rapid gravity filter as compared to that of slow sand filter, is", "opta": "10 times", "optb": "15 times", "optc": "20 times", "optd": "30 times", "opte": "35 times.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}